<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>'Spectrum': Spectral Analysis in Python</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Thomas Cokelaer</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-6286-1138</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Juergen Hasch</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-9457-1220</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>spectral analysis</tag>
      <tag>periodogram</tag>
      <tag>yule-walker</tag>
      <tag>multi-tapering</tag>
      <tag>burg</tag>
      <tag>ARMA</tag>
      <tag>eigen-values</tag>
      <tag>tapering windows</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>2 August 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00348</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/cokelaer/spectrum</software_repository>
    <software_archive>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1037268</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00348/10.21105.joss.00348.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><strong>Spectrum</strong> is a Python library that includes tools to estimate Power Spectral Densities. Although the use of power spectrum of a signal is fundamental in electrical engineering (e.g. radio communications, radar), it has a wide range of applications from cosmology (e.g., detection of gravitational waves in 2016), to music (pattern detection) or biology (mass spectroscopy).</p>
    <p>Methods available are based on Fourier transform, parametric methods or eigenvalues analysis. Although standard methods such as periodogram are available, less common methods (e.g. multitapering) are also implemented:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The Fourier methods are based upon correlogram, periodogram and Welch estimates. Standard tapering windows (Hann, Hamming, Blackman) and more exotic ones are available (DPSS, Taylor, ...)<span class="citation">(Harris 1978; Welch 1967; Marple 1987)</span>.</li>
    <li>The parametric methods are based on Yule-Walker, BURG, MA and ARMA, covariance and modified covariance methods <span class="citation">(Marple 1987; Percival and Walden 1993)</span>.</li>
    <li>Non-parametric methods based on eigen analysis (e.g., MUSIC) and minimum variance analysis are also implemented <span class="citation">(Marple 1987)</span>.</li>
    <li>Multitapering method is also available <span class="citation">(Percival and Walden 1993)</span></li>
    <li>Classical tools useful to spectral analysis and more generally signal processing such as window tapering <span class="citation">(Harris 1978)</span> or transfer function are also available within the library.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>The following image shows the different methods of spectral estimation that are available in <strong>Spectrum</strong>.</p>
    <div class="figure">
    <img src="psd_all.png" alt="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5270866.v1" />
    <p class="caption">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5270866.v1</p>
    </div>
    <p><strong>Spectrum</strong> relies on Matplotlib <span class="citation">(Hunter 2007)</span> for the plotting. We also use Numpy <span class="citation">(Stéfan van der Walt and Varoquaux 2011)</span> for fast array manipulation and Scipy <span class="citation">(Jones et al. 2001–2001--)</span> for linear algebra.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-harris:1978">
    <p>Harris, F. J. 1978. “On the Use of Windows for Harmonic Analysis with the Discrete Fouriertransform.” <em>Proceedings of the IEEE</em> 66 (1). IEEE: 51–83. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/PROC.1978.10837">10.1109/PROC.1978.10837</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-matplotlib:2007">
    <p>Hunter, John D. 2007. “Matplotlib: A 2d Graphics Environment.” <em>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</em> 9: 90–95. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/DOI:10.1109/MCSE.2007.55">DOI:10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-scipy:2001">
    <p>Jones, Eric, Travis Oliphant, Pearu Peterson, and others. 2001–2001--. “SciPy: Open Source Scientific Tools for Python.” <a href="http://www.scipy.org/" class="uri">http://www.scipy.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-marple:1987">
    <p>Marple, S. L. 1987. <em>Digital Spectral Analysis with Applications</em>. Australia, Sydney: Prentice Hall.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-percival:1993">
    <p>Percival, Donald B, and Andrew T Walden. 1993. <em>Spectral Analysis for Physical Applications: Multitaper and Conventional Univariate Techniques.</em> cambridge university press.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-numpy:2011">
    <p>Stéfan van der Walt, S. Chris Colbert, and Gaël Varoquaux. 2011. “&quot;The Numpy Array: A Structure for Efficient Numerical Computation.” <em>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</em> 13: 22–30. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/DOI:10.1109/MCSE.2011.37">DOI:10.1109/MCSE.2011.37</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-welch:1967">
    <p>Welch, P. 1967. “The Use of Fast Fourier Transform for the Estimation of Power Spectra: A Method Based on Time Averaging over Short, Modified Periodograms.” <em>IEEE Transactions on Audio and Electroacoustics</em> 15 (2): 70–73.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
