<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Pymagicc: A Python wrapper for the simple climate model MAGICC</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Robert Gieseke</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-1236-5109</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Sven N Willner</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-6798-6247</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1, 2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Matthias Mengel</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-6724-9685</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>climate change</tag>
      <tag>simple climate model</tag>
      <tag>python-wrapper</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>13 December 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00516</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/openclimatedata/pymagicc</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1165153</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00516/10.21105.joss.00516.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Pymagicc is a Python interface for the Fortran-based reduced-complexity climate carbon cycle model MAGICC <span class="citation" data-cites="Meinshausen2011">(Meinshausen, Raper, and Wigley 2011)</span>. Aiming at broadening the user base of MAGICC<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a>, Pymagicc provides a wrapper around the MAGICC binary<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"><sup>2</sup></a>, which runs on Windows and has been published under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"><sup>3</sup></a>. Pymagicc itself is licensed under the GNU Affero General Public License v3.0<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4"><sup>4</sup></a>.</p>
    <p>Pymagicc runs on Windows, macOS and Linux and simplifies usage of the model by utilising DataFrames from the Pandas library <span class="citation" data-cites="McKinney2010">(McKinney 2010)</span> as a data structure for emissions scenarios. To read and write the text-based MAGICC configuration and output files in the Fortran Namelist format Pymagicc utilizes the f90nml library <span class="citation" data-cites="Ward2017">(Ward 2017)</span>. All MAGICC model parameters and emissions scenarios can thus easily be modified through Pymagicc from Python.</p>
    <p>MAGICC (Model for the Assessment of Greenhouse Gas Induced Climate Change) is widely used in the assessment of future emissions pathways in climate policy analyses, e.g. in the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change <span class="citation" data-cites="IPCC2014">(IPCC 2014)</span>. Many Integrated Assessment Models (IAMs) utilize MAGICC to model the physical aspects of climate change. It has also been used to emulate complex atmosphere-ocean general circulation models (AOGCM) from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Projects<a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5"><sup>5</sup></a>.</p>
    <p>Pymagicc also facilitates comparisons with other recently published simple climate models available from or written in Python, such as OSCAR<a href="#fn6" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref6"><sup>6</sup></a> (<span class="citation" data-cites="Gasser2017">Gasser et al. (2017)</span>), Pyhector<a href="#fn7" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref7"><sup>7</sup></a> (<span class="citation" data-cites="Willner17">Willner, Hartin, and Gieseke (2017)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="Hartin2015">Hartin et al. (2015)</span>), and FAIR<a href="#fn8" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref8"><sup>8</sup></a> (<span class="citation" data-cites="Millar2017">Millar et al. (2017)</span>.)</p>
    <p>It can be installed using <code>pip</code> from the Python Package Index.<a href="#fn9" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref9"><sup>9</sup></a> To enable Pymagicc to run under Linux and macOS the Wine<a href="#fn10" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref10"><sup>10</sup></a> compatibility layer is used, usually being available from package managers.</p>
    <p>Source code, documentation and issue tracker are available in Pymagicc’s GitHub repository<a href="#fn11" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref11"><sup>11</sup></a>. Usage examples are also contained in the repository as a Jupyter Notebook <span class="citation" data-cites="Perez2007 Kluyver2016">(Pérez and Granger 2007; Kluyver et al. 2016)</span>. Thanks to the Binder project<a href="#fn12" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref12"><sup>12</sup></a>, the example Notebook can also be run interactively and explored without the need to install Pymagicc locally.</p>
    <h2 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h2>
    <p>We thank the authors of MAGICC for making the binary available under a Creative Commons license and Johannes Gütschow and Louise Jeffery for helpful comments on earlier versions of Pymagicc and the manuscript.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Gasser2017">
    <p>Gasser, T., P. Ciais, O. Boucher, Y. Quilcaille, M. Tortora, L. Bopp, and D. Hauglustaine. 2017. “The Compact Earth System Model OSCAR V2.2: Description and First Results.” <em>Geoscientific Model Development</em> 10 (1):271–319. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-10-271-2017" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-10-271-2017</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Hartin2015">
    <p>Hartin, C. A., P. Patel, A. Schwarber, R. P. Link, and B. P. Bond-Lamberty. 2015. “A Simple Object-Oriented and Open-Source Model for Scientific and Policy Analyses of the Global Climate System – Hector V1.0.” <em>Geoscientific Model Development</em> 8 (4):939–55. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-8-939-2015" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-8-939-2015</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-IPCC2014">
    <p>IPCC. 2014. <em>Climate Change 2014: Mitigation of Climate Change. Contribution of Working Group III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</em>. Edited by O. Edenhofer, R. Pichs-Madruga, Y. Sokona, E. Farahani, S. Kadner, K. Seyboth, A. Adler, et al. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge; New York, NY.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Kluyver2016">
    <p>Kluyver, T., B. Ragan-Kelley, F. Pérez, B. Granger, M. Bussonnier, J. Frederic, K. Kelley, et al. 2016. “Jupyter Notebooks—a Publishing Format for Reproducible Computational Workflows.” <em>Positioning and Power in Academic Publishing: Players, Agents and Agendas</em>, 87–90. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3233/978-1-61499-649-1-87" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.3233/978-1-61499-649-1-87</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-McKinney2010">
    <p>McKinney, W. 2010. “Data Structures for Statistical Computing in Python.” In <em>Proceedings of the 9th Python in Science Conference</em>, edited by Stéfan van der Walt and Jarrod Millman, 51–56.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Meinshausen2011">
    <p>Meinshausen, M., S. C. B. Raper, and T. M. L. Wigley. 2011. “Emulating Coupled Atmosphere-Ocean and Carbon Cycle Models with a Simpler Model, MAGICC6 – Part 1: Model Description and Calibration.” <em>Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics</em> 11 (4):1417–56. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-11-1417-2011" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-11-1417-2011</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Millar2017">
    <p>Millar, R. J., Z. R. Nicholls, P. Friedlingstein, and M. R. Allen. 2017. “A Modified Impulse-Response Representation of the Global Near-Surface Air Temperature and Atmospheric Concentration Response to Carbon Dioxide Emissions.” <em>Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics</em> 17 (11):7213–28. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-17-7213-2017" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-17-7213-2017</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Perez2007">
    <p>Pérez, F., and B. E. Granger. 2007. “IPython: A System for Interactive Scientific Computing.” <em>Computing in Science and Engineering</em> 9 (3). IEEE Computer Society:21–29. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2007.53" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2007.53</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Ward2017">
    <p>Ward, Marshall. 2017. “f90nml - a Python Module for Parsing Fortran Namelist Files.” <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1112518" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1112518</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Willner17">
    <p>Willner, S. N., C. A. Hartin, and R. Gieseke. 2017. “Pyhector: A Python Interface for the Simple Climate Model Hector.” <em>The Journal of Open Source Software</em> 2 (12). The Open Journal. <a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00248" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00248</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
    <section class="footnotes">
    <hr />
    <ol>
    <li id="fn1"><p>http://magicc.org<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn2"><p>http://magicc.org/download6<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn3"><p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn4"><p>https://www.gnu.org/licenses/#AGPL<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn5"><p>https://cmip.llnl.gov/<a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn6"><p>https://github.com/tgasser/OSCAR<a href="#fnref6" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn7"><p>https://github.com/openclimatedata/pyhector<a href="#fnref7" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn8"><p>https://github.com/OMS-NetZero/FAIR<a href="#fnref8" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn9"><p><a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pymagicc" class="uri">https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pymagicc</a><a href="#fnref9" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn10"><p>https://www.winehq.org/<a href="#fnref10" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn11"><p><a href="https://github.com/openclimatedata/pymagicc" class="uri">https://github.com/openclimatedata/pymagicc</a><a href="#fnref11" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    <li id="fn12"><p><a href="https://mybinder.org/" class="uri">https://mybinder.org/</a><a href="#fnref12" class="footnote-back">↩</a></p></li>
    </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</article>
