<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>cbcbeat: an adjoint-enabled framework for computational cardiac electrophysiology</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Marie E. Rognes</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-6872-3710</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Patrick E. Farrell</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Simon W. Funke</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-4709-8415</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Johan E. Hake</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4042-0128</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            3
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Molly M. C. Maleckar</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-7012-3853</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            4
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>finite element method</tag>
      <tag>cardiac electrophysiology</tag>
      <tag>adjoint</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>29 March 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00224</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://bitbucket.org/meg/cbcbeat</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.801552</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/raw/master/joss.00224/10.21105.joss.00224.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>cbcbeat <span class="citation">(cbcbeat 2017)</span> is a Python-based software collection targeting computational cardiac electrophysiology problems. cbcbeat contains solvers of varying complexity and performance for the classical monodomain and bidomain equations coupled with cardiac cell models. The cbcbeat solvers are based on algorithms described in <span class="citation">(Sundnes et al. 2006)</span> and the core FEniCS Project software <span class="citation">(Logg et al. 2012)</span>. All solvers allow for automated derivation and computation of adjoint and tangent linear solutions, functional derivatives and Hessians via the dolfin-adjoint software <span class="citation">(Farrell et al. 2013)</span>. The computation of functional derivatives in turn allows for automated and efficient solution of optimization problems such as those encountered in data assimillation or other inverse problems.</p>
    <p>The cbcbeat source code is hosted with Bitbucket (https://bitbucket.org/meg/cbcbeat) with documentation on readthedocs (http://cbcbeat.readthedocs.io).</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-cbcbeat">
    <p>cbcbeat. 2017. “Cbcbeat: An Adjoint-Enabled Framework for Computational Cardiac Electrophysiology.” <a href="https://bitbucket.org/meg/cbcbeat" class="uri">https://bitbucket.org/meg/cbcbeat</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-FarrellEtAl2013">
    <p>Farrell, P. E., D. A. Ham, S. W. Funke, and M. E. Rognes. 2013. “Automated Derivation of the Adjoint of High-Level Transient Finite Element Programs.” <em>SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing</em> 35 (4): C369–C393. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/120873558">10.1137/120873558</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-LoggEtAl2012">
    <p>Logg, Anders, Kent-Andre Mardal, Garth N. Wells, and others. 2012. <em>Automated Solution of Differential Equations by the Finite Element Method</em>. Springer. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-23099-8">10.1007/978-3-642-23099-8</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-SundnesEtAl2006">
    <p>Sundnes, Joakim, Glenn Terje Lines, Xing Cai, Bjørn Fredrik Nielsen, Kent-Andre Mardal, and Aslak Tveito. 2006. <em>Computing the Electrical Activity in the Heart</em>. Springer-Verlag.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
