<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>1512cf36d4ff535efc7102d327f47dc9</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20190313170652</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>http://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>4</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>35</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>MIDI.jl: Simple and intuitive handling of MIDI data.</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>George</given_name>
            <surname>Datseris</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6427-2385</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Joel</given_name>
            <surname>Hobson</surname>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>03</month>
          <day>13</day>
          <year>2019</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>1166</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.01166</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2591437</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/1166</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.01166</doi>
          <resource>http://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.01166</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">http://www.theoj.org/openjournals/joss-papers/joss.01166/10.21105.joss.01166.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <doi>10.1137/141000671</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <unstructured_citation>Datseris, George and Ziereis, Annika and Albrecht, Thorsten and Hagmayer, York and Priesemann, Viola and Geisel, Theo, Does it Swing? Microtiming Deviations and Swing Feeling in Jazz, to be publ.</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <unstructured_citation>Pr&#xF6;gler, J. A., Searching for Swing: Participatory Discrepancies in the Jazz Rhythm Section, Ethnomusicology, 1995, 39, 1, 21&#x2013;54, :Proegler1995 - Searching for Swing_ Participatory Discrepancies in the Jazz Rhythm Section.pdf:PDF, University of Illinois Press, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <unstructured_citation>Janata, Petr and Tomic, Stefan T and Haberman, Jason M, Sensorimotor coupling in music and the psychology of the groove., J. Exp. Psychol. Gen., 2012, 141, 1, 54, :Janata2012 - Sensorimotor coupling in music and the psychology of the groove..pdf:PDF, US: American Psychological Association</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <unstructured_citation>The Harvard Dictionary of Music: Fourth Edition, Harvard University Press, 2003, Apel, W. and Randel, D.M., Harvard University Press reference library, 9780674011632, 2003058262</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <doi>10.1037/a0024323</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <doi>10.1525/mp.2010.27.3.157</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.1177/1029864913486793</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <doi>10.1525/mp.2013.30.5.497</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <doi>10.3389/fpsyg.2016.01487</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <unstructured_citation>Matsushita, Soyogu and Nomura, Shingo, The Asymmetrical Influence of Timing Asynchrony of Bass Guitar and Drum Sounds on Groove, Music Perception: An Interdisciplinary Journal, 2016, 34, 2, 123&#x2013;131, 0730-7829, Groove is a pleasant feeling that compels people to move their bodies along with music. In the past, there was some consensus among both musicians and researchers that the main factor in inducing this feeling is onset asynchrony of sounds. However, recent studies have asserted that no-asynchrony is the condition that will obtain the highest groove. The current study examined whether no-asynchrony exclusively elicits the highest groove. In Experiment 1, we measured the groove increment of a backbeat drum pattern as a function of the asynchronies between bass guitar and hi-hat cymbal sounds. Upon evaluation, the scores of no conditions exceeded those of the synchronous condition. However, the condition with slight bass guitar precedence over the hi-hat achieved an approximately equal score to the condition with complete synchrony, and that score was higher than the ones achieved with bass delay. In Experiment 2, we measured the participants&#x2019; sensitivities to timing discrimination. The results confirmed that the amount of bass precedence in Experiment 1 was perceptible to the listeners. These findings suggest that complete synchronization is not always the best condition to achieve groove and that listeners prefer perceivable asynchronies in some cases., :Matsushita2016 - The Asymmetrical Influence of Timing Asynchrony of Bass Guitar and Drum Sounds on Groove.pdf:PDF, groove, relevant, rank5, University of California Press Journals, 2017-02-24</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <doi>10.1080/09298215.2017.1355394</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <unstructured_citation>Kilchenmann, Lorenz and Senn, Olivier, Microtiming in Swing and Funk affects the body movement behavior of music expert listeners, Front. Psychol., 2015, 6, 1232, The theory of Participatory Discrepancies (or PDs) claims that minute temporal asynchronies (microtiming) in music performance are crucial for prompting bodily entrainment in listeners, which is a fundamental effect of the &#x201C;groove&#x201D; experience. Previous research has failed to find evidence to support this theory. The present study tested the influence of varying PD magnitudes on the beat-related body movement behavior of music listeners. 160 participants (79 music experts, 81 non-experts) listened to 12 music clips in either Funk or Swing style. These stimuli were based on two audio recordings (one in each style) of expert drum and bass duo performances. In one series of six clips, the PDs were downscaled from their originally performed magnitude to complete quantization in steps of 20%. In another series of six clips, the PDs were upscaled from their original magnitude to double magnitude in steps of 20%. The intensity of the listeners&#x2019; beat-related head movement was measured using video-based motion capture technology and Fourier analysis. A mixed-design Four-Factor ANOVA showed that the PD manipulations had a significant effect on the expert listeners&#x2019; entrainment behavior. The experts moved more when listening to stimuli with PDs that were downscaled by 60% compared to completely quantized stimuli. This finding offers partial support for PD theory: PDs of a certain magnitude do augment entrainment in listeners. But the effect was found to be small to moderately sized, and it affected music expert listeners only. Keywords: microtiming, groove, entrainment, body movement, participatory discrepancies, funk, swing, musical expertise, :Kilchenmann2015 - Microtiming in Swing and Funk affects the body movement behavior of music expert listeners.pdf:PDF, Microtiming Deviations, groove, relevant, Frontiers Media SA, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <unstructured_citation>Benadon, Fernando, Gridless Beats, Perspectives of New Music, 2009, 47, 1, 135&#x2013;164, 00316016, jAZZ MUSIC CONFLATES TWO seeming opposites: the fixed foundation of a regular beat and the fluidity of microrhythmic variation. By fuzzy- ing subdivision values and slicing beats asymmetrically, jazz musicians enrich the monotony of steady beat patterns with an elastic treatment of time. Because such rhythmic sophistication derives from spontaneous invention and not from the directives of music notation, a composer wishing to emulate jazz rubatos faces an interesting technical challenge. In this article I look at how certain microrhythmic properties of jazz can be simulated using standard music notation. My goal is to bridge aspects of jazz improvisation and contemporary composition by providing insights into the former and toolsets for the latter. J, Perspectives of New Music, http://www.jstor.org/stable/25652403</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <unstructured_citation>Butterfield, Matthew, Why do jazz musicians swing their eighth notes?, Music theory spectrum, 2011, 33, 1, 3&#x2013;26, In jazz, the function of durational inequality at the eighth-note level is the production of anacrusis on the offbeats, thereby generating the sense of forward propulsion and drive thought to typify the rhythmic quality known as &#x201C;swing.&#x201D; The common use of relatively &#x201C;straight&#x201D; eighth notes by improvising soloists helps to sustain forward momentum, whereas the less even, triplet-like &#x201C;swing&#x201D; eighth notes used more frequently by drummers facilitate the perception of a quarter-note beat. Varying the Beat-Upbeat Ratio (BUR)&#x2014;i.e., moving between straight and swing eighth notes&#x2014;enables jazz musicians to manipulate the flow of motional energy across a phrase in systematic ways in conjunction with other melodic processes. Analyses of melodic phrases by John Coltrane, Lee Konitz, and Sonny Clark reveal the centrality of such aspects of microrhythmic expression to the affective power of jazz improvisation. Keywords: anacrusis, beat-upbeat ratio, BUR, Sonny Clark, John Coltrane, rhythm, jazz, Lee Konitz, microrhythm, microtiming, motional energy, swing, swing eighth note, swing ratio, :Butterfield2011 - Why do jazz musicians swing their eighth notes_.pdf:PDF, Oxford University Press, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref16">
            <unstructured_citation>3, 53&#x2013;72, Metrical ambiguity or microrhythmic flexibility? Analysing groove in &#x201C;Nasty Girl&#x201D; by Destiny&#x2019;s Child, Ashgate Publishing, 2015, Danielsen, Anne, A. Doehring, D. Helms and Moore, A. F., Song Interpretation in 21\textsuperscriptst-Century Pop Music, &#xB7; Edited by, :Danielsen2015 - Metrical ambiguity or microrhythmic flexibility_ Analysing groove in &#x201C;Nasty Girl&#x201D; by Destiny&#x2019;s Child.pdf:PDF, Microtiming Deviations, groove, Song Interpretation in 21\textsuperscriptst-Century Pop Music, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref17">
            <unstructured_citation>Danielsen, Anne and Haugen, Mari Romarheim and Jensenius, Alexander Refsum, Moving to the Beat: Studying Entrainment to Micro-Rhythmic Changes in Pulse by Motion Capture, Timing &amp; Time Perception, 2015, 3, 1-2, 133&#x2013;154, Pulse is a fundamental reference for the production and perception of rhythm. In this paper, we study entrainment to changes in the micro-rhythmic design of the basic pulse of the groove in &#x2018;Left &amp; Right&#x2019; by D&#x2019;Angelo. In part 1 of the groove the beats have one specific position; in part 2, on the other hand, the different rhythmic layers specify two simultaneous but alternative beat positions that are approximately 50-80 ms apart. We first anticipate listeners&#x2019; perceptual response using the theories of entrainment and dynamic attending as points of departure. We then report on a motion capture experiment aimed at engaging listeners&#x2019; motion patterns in response to the two parts of the tune. The results show that when multiple onsets are introduced in part 2, the half note becomes a significant additional level of entrainment and the temporal locations of the perceived beats are drawn towards the added onsets., :Danielsen2015a - Moving to the Beat_ Studying Entrainment to Micro-Rhythmic Changes in Pulse by Motion Capture.pdf:PDF, Microtiming Deviations, Brill, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref18">
            <unstructured_citation>Senn, Olivier and Bullerjahn, Claudia and Kilchenmann, Lorenz and von Georgi, Richard, Rhythmic Density Affects Listeners&#x2019; Emotional Response to Microtiming, Front. Psychol., 2017, 8, 1709, :senn_et_al_2017_rhythmic_density_affects_listeners_emotional_response_to_microtiming.pdf:PDF, rank5, Frontiers</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref19">
            <unstructured_citation>McGuiness, Andy, Groove microtiming deviations as phase shifts, Proceedings of the 9\textsuperscriptth International Conference on Music Perception and Cognition (Bologna:), 2006, 188, Several studies of microtiming deviation in groove musics of the African diaspora have argued that deviations from a regular beat which do not affect the global tempo) are an essential component of the groove, rather than a product of poor timing by performers (Al&#xE9;n, 1995; Bilmes, 1993b; Cholakis, 1999; Freeman &amp; Lacey, 2002; Waadeland, 2001). Data available from two studies (Al&#xE9;n, 1995; McGuiness, 2005) yield phase deviations in the range of approximately 5msecs to 50msecs in absolute values. The existence of phase corrections in response to subliminal timing perturbations - below the detection threshold for ISI changes - has been established in a number of studies (Repp, 2000, 2001a, 2001b, 2002a, 2002b; M. Thaut, Tian, &amp; Azimi-Sadjadi, 1998; M. H. Thaut &amp; Kenyon, 2003). Entrainment models incorporating separate phase correction and period correction terms have been described by (E.W. Large &amp; Kolen, 1994), (Mates, 1994a), (M. H. Thaut, Miller, &amp; Schauer, 1998), and (E.W. Large &amp; Jones, 1999); but make no prediction about the respective location of period and phase within the Wing &amp; Kristofferson two-process model of internal clock and motor implementation (A.M. Wing &amp; Kristofferson, 1973a). This paper proposes that 1) systematic microtiming deviations are phase shifts; and that 2) phase correction processes in entrainment are located in the motor (implementation) stage of the Wing &amp; Kristofferson model. The idea of functional anticipation is introduced, which accounts for entrainment phase corrections, microtiming deviations, synchronisation error in tapping studies, and adaptation to latency in musical instruments., :McGuiness2006 - Groove microtiming deviations as phase shifts.pdf:PDF, Microtiming Deviations, groove, relevant, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref20">
            <unstructured_citation>Iyer, Vijay, Embodied mind, situated cognition, and expressive microtiming in African-American music, Music Perception: An Interdisciplinary Journal, 2002, 19, 3, 387&#x2013;414, The dual theories of embodied mind and situated cognition, in which physical/temporal embodiment and physical/social/cultural environment contribute crucially to the structure of mind, are brought to bear on issues in music perception. It is argued that cognitive universals grounded in human bodily experience are tempered by the cultural specificity that constructs the role of the body in musical performance. Special focus is given to microrhythmic techniques in specific forms of African-American music, using audio examples created by the author or sampled from well-known jazz recordings., :Iyer2002 - Embodied mind, situated cognition, and expressive microtiming in African-American music.pdf:PDF, Microtiming Deviations, University of California Press Journals, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref21">
            <unstructured_citation>Keil, Charles, Participatory discrepancies and the power of music, Cultural Anthropology, 1987, 2, 3, 275&#x2013;283, :Keil1987 - Participatory discrepancies and the power of music.pdf:PDF, Wiley Online Library, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref22">
            <unstructured_citation>Keil, Charles, Motion and Feeling through Music, The Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism, 1966, 24, 3, 337&#x2013;349, :Keil1966 - Motion and Feeling through Music.pdf:PDF, [Wiley, American Society for Aesthetics], 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref23">
            <unstructured_citation>Friberg, Anders and Sundstr&#xF6;&#xF6;m, Andreas, Swing ratios and ensemble timing in jazz performance: Evidence for a common rhythmic pattern, Music Perception: An Interdisciplinary Journal, 2002, 19, 3, 333&#x2013;349, The timing in jazz ensemble performances was investigated in order to approach the question of what makes the music &#x201C;swing.&#x201D; One well-known aspect of swing is that consecutive eighth notes are performed as longshort patterns. The exact duration ratio (the swing ratio) of the longshort pattern has been largely unknown. In this study, the swing ratio produced by drummers on the ride cymbal was measured. Three wellknown jazz recordings and a play-along record were used. A substantial and gradual variation of the drummers&#x2019; swing ratio with respect to tempo was observed. At slow tempi, the swing ratio was as high as 3.5:1, whereas at fast tempi it reached 1:1. The often-mentioned &#x201C;triple-feel,&#x201D; that is, a ratio of 2:1, was present only at a certain tempo. The absolute duration of the short note in the long-short pattern was constant at about 100 ms for medium to fast tempi, suggesting a practical limit on tone duration that may be due to perceptual factors. Another aspect of swing is the soloist&#x2019;s timing in relation to the accompaniment. For example, a soloist can be characterized as playing &#x201C;behind the beat.&#x201D; In the second part, the swing ratio of the soloist and its relation to the cymbal accompaniment was measured from the same recordings. In slow tempi, the soloists were mostly playing their downbeats after the cymbal but were synchronized with the cymbal at the off-beats. This implied that the swing ratio of the soloist was considerably smaller than the cymbal accompaniment in slow tempi. It may give an impression of &#x201C;playing behind&#x201D; but at the same time keep the synchrony with the accompaniment at the off-beat positions. Finally, the possibilities of using computer tools in jazz pedagogy are discussed., :Friberg2002 - Swing ratios and ensemble timing in jazz performance_ Evidence for a common rhythmic pattern.pdf:PDF, swingratio, tempo, University of California Press Journals, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref24">
            <unstructured_citation>Ellis, Mark C, An analysis of &#x201C;swing&#x201D; subdivision and asynchronization in three jazz saxophonists, Percept. Mot. Skills, 1991, 73, 3, 707&#x2013;713, :Ellis1991-an analysis of swing subdivision.pdf:PDF, SAGE Publications Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref25">
            <unstructured_citation>Wesolowski, Brian C, Timing deviations in jazz performance: The relationships of selected musical variables on horizontal and vertical timing relations: A case study, Psychology of Music, 2016, 44, 1, 75&#x2013;94, The purpose of this study was to examine the effects and relationships of selected musical variables on the horizontal (i.e., successive eighth note timing relationships) and vertical (i.e., the degree of ensemble synchronicity between separate parts) timing properties of jazz rhythm. A total of 949 eighth note samples from five improvised solos by saxophonist Chris Potter were analysed. Musical variables included metrical beat placement, melodic character, intervals, articulation, underlying harmony, and tempo. Results of the simultaneous multiple regression analyses revealed that intervals preceding and intervals succeeding the sample eighth notes had a significant effect on eighth note durations. Articulation had a significant effect on upbeat beat ratio. The relationships between the relative onset timing data of the saxophone, bass, and drums yielded significant results. There was a large, negative correlation between the relative timing onsets of saxophone and bass, a large negative correlation between saxophone and drums, and a moderate, negative correlation between bass and drums. Implications for the fields of music education, pedagogy, and cognitive psychology are discussed., :Wesolowski2016 - Timing deviations in jazz performance_ The relationships of selected musical variables on horizontal and vertical timing relations_ A case study.pdf:PDF, 2017-03-27</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref26">
            <unstructured_citation>Benadon, Fernando, Time warps in early jazz, Music Theory Spectrum, 2009, 31, 1, 1&#x2013;25, Expressive timing can be viewed as a process whereby a rhythmic template is transformed into a new rhythm that departs from the underlying metric grid. In this paper I examine two types of transformation within the context of 1920s jazz. The Flux (F) transformation distorts the original rhythmic template by molding it into an acceleration, a deceleration, or a combination of these. The Shift (S) transformation changes the global tempo of the template. At the heart of these oper- ations lies the concept of an anchor, an on-the-beat synchronization point between soloist and accom- paniment that metrically grounds the transformation. Soloists use F and S&#x2014;often in conjunction&#x2014; to shape their rhythms and to control the level of tension/resolution in relation to the underlying beat. Keywords: jazz, rhythm, microtiming, improvisation, transformation, rubato, Louis Armstrong, Bubber Miley, :Benadon2009b - Time warps in early jazz.pdf:PDF, swing, rank2, University of California Press, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref27">
            <unstructured_citation>Merker, Bjorn H. and Madison, Guy S. and Eckerdal, Patricia, On the role and origin of isochrony in human rhythmic entrainment, Cortex, 2009, 45, 1, 4&#x2013;17, Wherever human beings live, and however they may organise their affairs, they gather from time to time to sing and dance together, often in a ritual setting. In doing so they synchronise their voices and bodily movements to a shared, repeating interval of time, the musical pulse, beat or tactus. We take this capacity to &#x201C;entrain&#x201D; to an evenly paced stimulus (isochrony) so much for granted that it may come as a surprise to learn that from a biological point of view such behaviour is exceptional. But it is not altogether unique. There are a number of other species, none of them closely related to humans, that also engage in group synchrony of behaviour through entrainment to an isochronous pulse. Despite their evolutionary distance from us their life circumstances throw an interesting light on the possible origin and nature of our own entrainment capacity. Here we consider this capacity in terms of its possible origin, functional mechanisms, and ontogenetic development., :Merker2009 - On the role and origin of isochrony in human rhythmic entrainment.pdf:PDF, Entrainment, Entrainment, Isochrony, Origin of music, Rhythmicity, Synchrony, 2018-04-22</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref28">
            <unstructured_citation>Fitch, W Tecumseh and Rosenfeld, Andrew J, Perception and production of syncopated rhythms, Music Perception: An Interdisciplinary Journal, 2007, 25, 1, 43&#x2013;58, :FitchRosenfeld20071.pdf:PDF, University of California Press Journals</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref29">
            <unstructured_citation>Grahn, Jessica A and Brett, Matthew, Rhythm and beat perception in motor areas of the brain, J. Cognit. Neurosci., 2007, 19, 5, 893&#x2013;906, :grahn2007- rhythm and.pdf:PDF, MIT Press</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref30">
            <doi>10.1177/0305735617697507</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref31">
            <doi>10.1177/0305735617697507</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref32">
            <unstructured_citation>Song, Chunyang and Simpson, Andrew J. R. and Harte, Christopher A. and Pearce, Marcus T. and Sandler, Mark B., Syncopation and the Score, PLoS One, 2013, 8, 9, 1&#x2013;7, The score is a symbolic encoding that describes a piece of music, written according to the conventions of music theory, which must be rendered as sound (e.g., by a performer) before it may be perceived as music by the listener. In this paper we provide a step towards unifying music theory with music perception in terms of the relationship between notated rhythm (i.e., the score) and perceived syncopation. In our experiments we evaluated this relationship by manipulating the score, rendering it as sound and eliciting subjective judgments of syncopation. We used a metronome to provide explicit cues to the prevailing rhythmic structure (as defined in the time signature). Three-bar scores with time signatures of 4/4 and 6/8 were constructed using repeated one-bar rhythm-patterns, with each pattern built from basic half-bar rhythm-components. Our manipulations gave rise to various rhythmic structures, including polyrhythms and rhythms with missing strong- and/or down-beats. Listeners (N = 10) were asked to rate the degree of syncopation they perceived in response to a rendering of each score. We observed higher degrees of syncopation in time signatures of 6/8, for polyrhythms, and for rhythms featuring a missing down-beat. We also found that the location of a rhythm-component within the bar has a significant effect on perceived syncopation. Our findings provide new insight into models of syncopation and point the way towards areas in which the models may be improved., :Song2013 - Syncopation and the Score.pdf:PDF, Public Library of Science, 2017-03-12</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref33">
            <unstructured_citation>Keller, Peter E and Schubert, Emery, Cognitive and affective judgements of syncopated musical themes, Advances in Cognitive Psychology, 2011, 7, 142&#x2013;156, :keller - cognitive and affective judgements of syncopation.pdf:PDF, University of Finance and Management in Warsaw</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref34">
            <unstructured_citation>Sioros, George and Miron, Marius and Davies, Matthew and Gouyon, Fabien and Madison, Guy, Syncopation creates the sensation of groove in synthesized music examples, Front. Psychol., 2014, 5, 1036, 1664-1078, In order to better understand the musical properties which elicit an increased sensation of wanting to move when listening to music &#x2013; groove &#x2013; we investigate the effect of adding syncopation to simple piano melodies, under the hypothesis that syncopation is correlated to groove. Across two experiments we examine listeners&#x2019; experience of groove to synthesized musical stimuli covering a range of syncopation levels and densities of musical events, according to formal rules implemented by a computer algorithm that shifts musical events from strong to weak metrical positions. Results indicate that moderate levels of syncopation lead to significantly higher groove ratings than melodies without any syncopation or with maximum possible syncopation. A comparison between the various trans-formations and the way they were rated shows that there is no simple relation between syncopation magnitude and groove., :Sioros2014 - Syncopation creates the sensation of groove in synthesized music examples.pdf:PDF, groove, 2017-02-23</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref35">
            <unstructured_citation>Witek, Maria A. G. and Clarke, Eric F. and Wallentin, Mikkel and Kringelbach, Morten L. and Vuust, Peter, Syncopation, Body-Movement and Pleasure in Groove Music, PLoS One, 2014, 9, 4, 1&#x2013;12, Moving to music is an essential human pleasure particularly related to musical groove. Structurally, music associated with groove is often characterised by rhythmic complexity in the form of syncopation, frequently observed in musical styles such as funk, hip-hop and electronic dance music. Structural complexity has been related to positive affect in music more broadly, but the function of syncopation in eliciting pleasure and body-movement in groove is unknown. Here we report results from a web-based survey which investigated the relationship between syncopation and ratings of wanting to move and experienced pleasure. Participants heard funk drum-breaks with varying degrees of syncopation and audio entropy, and rated the extent to which the drum-breaks made them want to move and how much pleasure they experienced. While entropy was found to be a poor predictor of wanting to move and pleasure, the results showed that medium degrees of syncopation elicited the most desire to move and the most pleasure, particularly for participants who enjoy dancing to music. Hence, there is an inverted U-shaped relationship between syncopation, body-movement and pleasure, and syncopation seems to be an important structural factor in embodied and affective responses to groove., :Witek2014 - Syncopation, Body-Movement and Pleasure in Groove Music.pdf:PDF, groove, relevant, Public Library of Science, 2017-02-24</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref36">
            <doi>10.1371/journal.pone.0026457</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref37">
            <doi>10.1371/journal.pone.0127902</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref38">
            <doi>10.1371/journal.pone.0186361</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref39">
            <unstructured_citation>Rankin, Summer K and Large, Edward W and Fink, Philip W, Fractal tempo fluctuation and pulse prediction, Music Perception: An Interdisciplinary Journal, 2009, 26, 5, 401&#x2013;413, :rankin2009_fractal tempo fluctuation and pulse prediction.pdf:PDF, University of California Press Journals</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref40">
            <unstructured_citation>Christensen, R. H. B., ordinal&#x2014;Regression Models for Ordinal Data, 2018, R package version 2018.4-19. http://www.cran.r-project.org/package=ordinal/</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref41">
            <unstructured_citation>K, Barton, MuMIn, Multi-model inference. R package version 1.15. 6.; 2016, 2016</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref42">
            <doi>10.1007/978-1-4612-0919-5_38</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref43">
            <unstructured_citation>Hauck Jr, Walter W and Donner, Allan, Wald&#x2019;s test as applied to hypotheses in logit analysis, J. Am. Stat. Assoc., 1977, 72, 360a, 851&#x2013;853, Taylor &amp; Francis</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref44">
            <unstructured_citation>DeLong, Elizabeth R and DeLong, David M and Clarke-Pearson, Daniel L, Comparing the areas under two or more correlated receiver operating characteristic curves: a nonparametric approach, Biometrics, 1988, 837&#x2013;845, JSTOR</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref45">
            <unstructured_citation>Fitch, W Tecumseh and Rosenfeld, Andrew J, Perception and production of syncopated rhythms, Music Perception: An Interdisciplinary Journal, 2007, 25, 1, 43&#x2013;58, :FitchRosenfeld20071.pdf:PDF, University of California Press Journals</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref46">
            <unstructured_citation>Schaal, Nora K and Bauer, Anna-Katharina R and M&#xFC;llensiefen, Daniel, Der Gold-MSI: replikation und validierung eines fragebogeninstrumentes zur messung musikalischer erfahrenheit anhand einer deutschen stichprobe, Musicae Scientiae, 2014, 18, 4, 423&#x2013;447, Die vorliegende Studie stellt das deutschsprachige Gold-MSI-Fragebogeninventar vor, mit dessen Hilfe selbsteingesch&#xE4;tzte musikalische F&#xE4;higkeiten und musikalische Expertise erhoben werden k&#xF6;nnen. Der Gold-MSI orientiert sich am mehrdimensionalen Konstrukt der Musikalischen Erfahrenheit, das davon ausgeht, dass musikalische F&#xE4;higkeiten und Umgangsweisen nicht allein durch Unterricht an einem Musikinstrument, sondern auch durch die aktive Auseinandersetzung mit Musik in all ihren Facetten erworben werden k&#xF6;nnen. Der an einer gro&#xDF;en englischsprachigen Stichprobe entwickelte Fragebogen (M&#xFC;llensiefen et al., 2014) erfasst musikalische Expertise mittels f&#xFC;nf Faktoren sowie einem globalen Faktor der Allgemeinen Musikalischen Erfahrenheit. Der englische Gold-MSI-Fragebogen wurde ins Deutsche &#xFC;bersetzt, und anhand einer deutschsprachigen Stichprobe (N = 641) konnte die Faktorenstruktur mittels einer konfirmatorischen Faktorenanalyse best&#xE4;tigt werden. Des Weiteren weisen alle f&#xFC;nf Einzelfaktoren sowie der globale Faktor Allgemeine Musikalische Erfahrenheit gute bis sehr gute Reliabilit&#xE4;ten auf (Werte von Cronbach&#x2018;s alpha zwischen 0,72 und 0,91). Zus&#xE4;tzlich werden Zusammenh&#xE4;nge zwischen Variablen des sozio&#xF6;konomischen Status und den Faktoren des Gold-MSI in der deutschen Stichprobe anhand eines Strukturgleichungsmodells dargelegt. Das statistische Modell zeigt positive Zusammenh&#xE4;nge zwischen Einkommen und beruflichem Status auf der einen und musikalischer Ausbildung, Wahrnehmungsf&#xE4;higkeiten und emotionalem Umgang mit Musik auf der anderen Seite auf  . Das Fragebogeninventar ist frei verf&#xFC;gbar und soll zur differenzierten Untersuchung Musikalischer Erfahrenheit und Expertise im deutschsprachigen Raum beitragen. Keywords musikalische Expertise, Musikalische Erfahrenheit, sozio&#xF6;konomischer Status, Gold-MSI-Fragebogen, :D\:\\Masterarbeit\\literature\\003musicalityassessment\\schaal_bauer_muellensiefen_2014_der_gold-msi_deutsch_replikation.pdf:LaTeX, Musicality Assessment, musical assessment, rank4, SAGE Publications Sage UK: London, England</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref47">
            <unstructured_citation>M&#xFC;llensiefen, Daniel and Gingras, Bruno and Musil, Jason and Stewart, Lauren, The musicality of non-musicians: an index for assessing musical sophistication in the general population, PloS one, 2014, 9, 2, :D\:\\Masterarbeit\\literature\\003musicalityassessment\\muellensiefen_et_al_2014_the_musicality_of_non-musicians.pdf:LaTeX, Musicality Assessment, musical assessment, rank4, Public Library of Science, 2017-03-12</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref48">
            <doi>10.1371/journal.pone.0127902</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref49">
            <doi>10.1073/pnas.1324142111</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref50">
            <unstructured_citation>Treadwell, Bill, Big Book of Swing, Cambridge House, New York, 1946</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref51">
            <unstructured_citation>Intuitive analysis, creation and manipulation of MIDI data with pretty_midi, Raffel, Colin and Ellis, Daniel PW, 15th International Society for Music Information Retrieval Conference Late Breaking and Demo Papers, 84&#x2013;93, 2014</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
