<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>MDEntropy: Information-Theoretic Analyses for Molecular Dynamics</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Carlos X. Hernández</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-8146-5904</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Vijay S. Pande</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Python</tag>
      <tag>information theory</tag>
      <tag>molecular dynamics</tag>
      <tag>time-series</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>1 October 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00427</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/msmbuilder/mdentropy/</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1049032</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00427/10.21105.joss.00427.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><em>MDEntropy</em> is a Python package for information-theoretic (IT) analysis of data generated from molecular dynamics simulations. While correlation studies have long been of interest to the molecular dynamics (MD) community <span class="citation">(McCammon, Gelin, and Karplus 1977, <span class="citation">McClendon et al. (2009)</span>)</span>, IT tools to analyze MD trajectories have been much less developed. <em>MDEntropy</em> seeks to fill this niche by providing an easy-to-use Python API that works seamlessly with other Python packages, such as <code>mdtraj</code>, <code>msmbuilder</code>, and <code>numpy</code> <span class="citation">(R. T. McGibbon et al. 2015, <span class="citation">Walt, Colbert, and Varoquaux (2011)</span>, <span class="citation">M. P. Harrigan et al. (2017)</span>)</span>.</p>
    <p>Functionality in <em>MDEntropy</em> is centered around <code>mdtraj</code> trajectories and the statistical tools available in <code>msmbuilder</code>. Leveraging these tools allows for statistically robust analyses of many IT estimators across a variety of biomolecular feature-spaces <span class="citation">(Schreiber 2000, <span class="citation">Kraskov, Stögbauer, and Grassberger (2004)</span>)</span>.</p>
    <p><em>MDEntropy</em> is actively developed and maintained by researchers at Stanford University. Source code for <em>MDEntropy</em> is hosted on GitHub and is continuously archived to Zenodo <span class="citation">(Hernández and Pande 2017)</span>. Full documentation, including Jupyter Notebook tutorials, can be found at <a href="http://msmbuilder.org/mdentropy" class="uri">http://msmbuilder.org/mdentropy</a>.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-msmbuilder">
    <p>Harrigan, Matthew P., Mohammad M. Sultan, Carlos X. Hernández, Brooke E. Husic, Peter Eastman, Christian R. Schwantes, Kyle A. Beauchamp, Robert T. McGibbon, and Vijay S. Pande. 2017. “MSMBuilder: Statistical Models for Biomolecular Dynamics.” <em>Biophysical Journal</em> 112 (1): 10–15. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2016.10.042">10.1016/j.bpj.2016.10.042</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-mdent_archive">
    <p>Hernández, Carlos X., and Vijay S. Pande. 2017. “Msmbuilder/Mdentropy: V0.3.” doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1000997">10.5281/zenodo.1000997</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-grassberger">
    <p>Kraskov, Alexander, Harald Stögbauer, and Peter Grassberger. 2004. “Estimating mutual information.” <em>Physical Review E</em> 69 (6). American Physical Society: 066138. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.69.066138">10.1103/PhysRevE.69.066138</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-mccammon">
    <p>McCammon, J. Andrew, Bruce R. Gelin, and Martin Karplus. 1977. “Dynamics of folded proteins.” <em>Nature</em> 267 (5612). Nature Publishing Group: 585–90. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/267585a0">10.1038/267585a0</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-mcclendon">
    <p>McClendon, Christopher L, Gregory Friedland, David L Mobley, Homeira Amirkhani, and Matthew P Jacobson. 2009. “Quantifying Correlations Between Allosteric Sites in Thermodynamic Ensembles.” <em>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</em> 5 (9): 2486–2502. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/ct9001812">10.1021/ct9001812</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-mdtraj">
    <p>McGibbon, Robert T, Kyle A Beauchamp, Matthew P Harrigan, Christoph Klein, Jason M Swails, Carlos X Hernández, Christian R Schwantes, Lee-Ping Wang, Thomas J Lane, and Vijay S Pande. 2015. “MDTraj: A Modern Open Library for the Analysis of Molecular Dynamics Trajectories.” <em>Biophysical Journal</em> 109 (8). Elsevier: 1528–32. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2015.08.015">10.1016/j.bpj.2015.08.015</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-schreiber">
    <p>Schreiber, Thomas. 2000. “Measuring Information Transfer.” <em>Physical Review Letters</em> 85 (2): 461–64. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.85.461">10.1103/PhysRevLett.85.461</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-numpy">
    <p>Walt, Stéfan van der, S Chris Colbert, and Gael Varoquaux. 2011. “The NumPy Array: A Structure for Efficient Numerical Computation.” <em>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</em> 13 (2): 22–30. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2011.37">10.1109/MCSE.2011.37</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
