<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>GeneNetwork: framework for web-based genetics</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Zachary Sloan</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-8099-1363</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University of Tennessee Health Science Center, USA
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Danny Arends</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-8738-0162</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Karl W. Broman</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4914-6671</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University of Wisconsin, USA
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Arthur Centeno</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-3142-2081</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University of Tennessee Health Science Center, USA
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Nicholas Furlotte</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-9096-6276</orcid>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Harm Nijveen</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-9167-4945</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            Wageningen University, The Netherlands
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Lei Yan</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-5259-3379</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University of Tennessee Health Science Center, USA
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Xiang Zhou</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4331-7599</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University of Michigan
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Robert W. WIlliams</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-8924-4447</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University of Tennessee Health Science Center, USA
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Pjotr Prins</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-8021-9162</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University Medical Center Utrecht, The Netherlands, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, USA
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>bioinformatics</tag>
      <tag>genetics</tag>
      <tag>genomics</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>29 May 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00025</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/genenetwork/genenetwork2</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.53740</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00025/10.21105.joss.00025.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>GeneNetwork (GN) is a free and open source (FOSS) framework for web-based genetics that can be deployed anywhere. GN allows biologists to upload high-throughput experimental data, such as expression data from microarrays and RNA-seq, and also `classic' phenotypes, such as disease phenotypes. These phenotypes can be mapped interactively against genotypes using embedded tools, such as R/QTL <span class="citation">(Arends et al. 2010)</span> mapping, interval mapping for model organisms and pylmm; an implementation of FaST-LMM <span class="citation">(Lippert et al. 2011)</span> which is more suitable for human populations and outbred crosses, such as the mouse diversity outcross. Interactive D3 graphics are included from R/qtlcharts and presentation-ready figures can be generated. Recently we have added functionality for phenotype correlation <span class="citation">(Wang et al. 2016)</span> and network analysis <span class="citation">(Langfelder and Horvath 2008)</span>.</p>
    <p>-<img src="qtl2.png" alt="Mouse LMM mapping example" /></p>
    <p>GN is written in python and javascript and contains a rich set of tools and libraries that can be written in any computer language. A full list of included software can be found in the package named `genenetwork2' and defined in <a href="https://github.com/genenetwork/guix-bioinformatics/blob/master/gn/packages/genenetwork.scm">guix-bioinformatics</a>. To make it easy to install GN locally in a byte reproducible way, including all dependencies and a 2GB MySQL test database (the full database is 160GB and growing), GN is packaged with <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/guix/">GNU Guix</a>, as described <a href="https://github.com/genenetwork/genenetwork2/blob/staging/doc/README.org">here</a>. GNU Guix deployment makes it feasible to deploy and rebrand GN anywhere.</p>
    <h1 id="future-work">Future work</h1>
    <p>More mapping tools will be added, including support for Genome-wide Efficient Mixed Model Association (GEMMA). The <a href="http://www.biodalliance.org/">Biodiallance genome browser</a> is being added as a Google Summer of Code project with special tracks related to QTL mapping and network analysis. Faster LMM solutions are being worked on, including GPU support.</p>
    <p>A REST interface is being added so that data can be uploaded to a server, analysis run remotely on high performance hardware, and results downloaded and used for further analysis. This feature will allow biologist-programmers to use R and Python on their computer and execute computations on GN enabled servers.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Arends:2010">
    <p>Arends, D., P. Prins, R. C. Jansen, and K. W. Broman. 2010. “R/qtl: high-throughput multiple QTL mapping.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 26 (23): 2990–2. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq565">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq565</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-WGCNA:2008">
    <p>Langfelder, P., and S. Horvath. 2008. “WGCNA: an R package for weighted correlation network analysis.” <em>BMC Bioinformatics</em> 9: 559. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-9-559">10.1186/1471-2105-9-559</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Lippert:2011">
    <p>Lippert, C., J. Listgarten, Y. Liu, C. M. Kadie, R. I. Davidson, and D. Heckerman. 2011. “FaST linear mixed models for genome-wide association studies.” <em>Nat Methods</em> 8 (10): 833–35. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1681">10.1038/nmeth.1681</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Wang:2016">
    <p>Wang, X., A. K. Pandey, M. K. Mulligan, E. G. Williams, K. Mozhui, Z. Li, V. Jovaisaite, et al. 2016. “Joint mouse-human phenome-wide association to test gene function and disease risk.” <em>Nat Commun</em> 7: 10464. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms10464">10.1038/ncomms10464</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
