<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Histogram-weighted Networks for Feature Extraction, Connectivity and Advanced Analysis in Neuroscience</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Pradeep Reddy Raamana</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-4662-0558</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Stephen C. Strother</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3198-217X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1, 2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>connectivity</tag>
      <tag>neuroscience</tag>
      <tag>graph</tag>
      <tag>histogram</tag>
      <tag>machine-learning</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>21 August 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00380</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/raamana/hiwenet</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1064012</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00380/10.21105.joss.00380.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Network-level analysis of various features, especially if it can be individualized for a single-subject, is proving to be a valuable tool in many applications<span class="citation">(Raamana and Strother 2017; Evans 2013; Palaniyappan et al. 2015; Tijms et al. 2012; Xu et al. 2017; Raamana et al. 2015; Lerch et al. 2006; He, Chen, and Evans 2007)</span>. This package extracts single-subject (individualized, or intrinsic) networks from node-wise data by computing the edge weights based on histogram distance between the distributions of values within each node. Input features could be from any modality (fMRI, MEG, EEG, eye-tracking), so long as they can be turned into numbers. Individual nodes could be an ROI or a patch or a cube, or any other unit of relevance in your application. This is a great way to take advantage of the full distribution of values available within each node, relative to the simpler use of averages (or another summary statistic). A rough scheme of computation is shown in Figure 1.</p>
    <div class="figure">
    <img src="illustration.png" alt="illustration" />
    <p class="caption">illustration</p>
    </div>
    <h2 id="note-on-applicability-and-target-audience">Note on applicability and target audience</h2>
    <p>Although this technique was originally developed for cortical thickness analysis in neuroimaging research, this is a generic and powerful technique that could be applied to any features such as gray matter density, PET uptake values, functional activation data, EEG features or any other domain. All that is needed is a set of nodes/parcellation that have one-to-one correspondence across samples/subjects in your dataset.</p>
    <p>The target audience is users of almost all neuroimaging modalities who 1. preprocessed dataset already, 2. have some base features (node- or patch-wise, that are native to the given modality) extracted using other packages (metioned above), and 3. who would like to analyze network-level or covariance-type or connectivity relations among the base features.</p>
    <h1 id="what-does-the-hiwenet-package-do">What does the hiwenet package do?</h1>
    <ul>
    <li>This packages takes in vector of features and their membership labels (denoting which features belong to which groups - alternatively referred to as nodes in a graph), and computes their pair-wise histogram distances, using a chosen method.</li>
    <li>This package is designed to be domain-agnostic, and hence a generic input format was chosen.</li>
    <li>This <code>hiwenet.extract</code> could be used to extract advanced network-level /connectome features producing feature similar to the following tools from nilearn and MNE, but on a per-subject basis:
    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://martinos.org/mne/stable/generated/mne.SourceEstimate.html#mne.SourceEstimate.extract_label_time_course">MNE.extract_label_time_course</a></li>
    <li>or nilearn.input_data.NiftiLabelsMasker.transform - see <a href="http://nilearn.github.io/connectivity/functional_connectomes.html#extracting-signals-on-a-parcellation">here</a> and <a href="http://nilearn.github.io/modules/generated/nilearn.input_data.NiftiLabelsMasker.html#nilearn.input_data.NiftiLabelsMasker.transform">here</a>.</li>
    </ul></li>
    <li>However, we plan to add interfaces to tools e.g. via a scikit-learn compatible API/interface is also in the works. Stay tuned.</li>
    <li>Users also have the ability to input an arbitrary function (outside histogram distance family) to extract networks that is appropriate for their application.</li>
    <li>Refer to <a href="../examples">examples</a> directory and the <a href="hiwenet.readthedocs.io">docs</a> for more detailed and usage examples.</li>
    </ul>
    <h2 id="requirements">requirements</h2>
    <p><code>hiwenet</code> package is built on the following packages: <span class="citation">(Oliphant 2007; Walt, Colbert, and Varoquaux 2011; Hagberg, Swart, and S Chult 2008; Maier et al. 2017)</span></p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-evans2013networks">
    <p>Evans, Alan C. 2013. “Networks of Anatomical Covariance.” <em>Neuroimage</em> 80. Elsevier: 489–504.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-hagberg2008exploring">
    <p>Hagberg, Aric, Pieter Swart, and Daniel S Chult. 2008. “Exploring Network Structure, Dynamics, and Function Using Networkx.” Los Alamos National Laboratory (LANL).</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-he2007small">
    <p>He, Yong, Zhang J Chen, and Alan C Evans. 2007. “Small-World Anatomical Networks in the Human Brain Revealed by Cortical Thickness from Mri.” <em>Cerebral Cortex</em> 17 (10). Oxford University Press: 2407–19.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-lerch2006mapping">
    <p>Lerch, Jason P, Keith Worsley, W Philip Shaw, Deanna K Greenstein, Rhoshel K Lenroot, Jay Giedd, and Alan C Evans. 2006. “Mapping Anatomical Correlations Across Cerebral Cortex (Macacc) Using Cortical Thickness from Mri.” <em>Neuroimage</em> 31 (3). Elsevier: 993–1003.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-oskar_maier_2017_886618">
    <p>Maier, Oskar, Pradeep Reddy Raamana, mamrehn, and Rémi Bèges. 2017. “Loli/Medpy: MedPy 0.2.2.” doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.886618">10.5281/zenodo.886618</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-oliphant2007python">
    <p>Oliphant, Travis E. 2007. “Python for Scientific Computing.” <em>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</em> 9 (3). IEEE.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-palaniyappan2015abnormalities">
    <p>Palaniyappan, Lena, Bert Park, Vijender Balain, Raj Dangi, and Peter Liddle. 2015. “Abnormalities in Structural Covariance of Cortical Gyrification in Schizophrenia.” <em>Brain Structure and Function</em> 220 (4). Springer: 2059–71.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Raamana170381">
    <p>Raamana, Pradeep Reddy, and Stephen C. Strother. 2017. “Impact of Spatial Scale and Edge Weight on Predictive Power of Cortical Thickness Networks.” <em>bioRxiv</em>. Cold Spring Harbor Labs Journals. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/170381">10.1101/170381</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-raamana2015thickness">
    <p>Raamana, Pradeep Reddy, Michael W Weiner, Lei Wang, Mirza Faisal Beg, Alzheimer’s Disease Neuroimaging Initiative, and others. 2015. “Thickness Network Features for Prognostic Applications in Dementia.” <em>Neurobiology of Aging</em> 36. Elsevier: S91–S102.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-tijms2012similarity">
    <p>Tijms, Betty M, Peggy Seriès, David J Willshaw, and Stephen M Lawrie. 2012. “Similarity-Based Extraction of Individual Networks from Gray Matter Mri Scans.” <em>Cerebral Cortex</em> 22 (7). Oxford University Press: 1530–41.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-walt2011numpy">
    <p>Walt, Stéfan van der, S Chris Colbert, and Gael Varoquaux. 2011. “The Numpy Array: A Structure for Efficient Numerical Computation.” <em>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</em> 13 (2). IEEE: 22–30.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-xu2017abnormalities">
    <p>Xu, Jinping, Jiuquan Zhang, Jinlei Zhang, Yue Wang, Yanling Zhang, Jian Wang, Guanglin Li, Qingmao Hu, and Yuanchao Zhang. 2017. “Abnormalities in Structural Covariance of Cortical Gyrification in Parkinson’s Disease.” <em>Frontiers in Neuroanatomy</em> 11. Frontiers Media SA.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
