<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>c7b3a3abeba23358b15fd732a48236b5</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20220105225614</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>7</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>69</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>AIBECS.jl: A tool for exploring global marine biogeochemical cycles.</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Benoît</given_name>
            <surname>Pasquier</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3838-5976</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>François</given_name>
            <surname>Primeau</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7452-9415</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Seth</given_name>
            <surname>John</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8257-626X</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>01</month>
          <day>05</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>3814</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.03814</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5787531”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/3814</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.03814</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03814</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03814.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <doi>10.7289/V5C8276M</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <doi>10.1029/1999GB001216</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <doi>10.1016/j.ocemod.2013.09.008</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <doi>10.1016/j.ocemod.2016.07.003</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <doi>10.18637/jss.v098.i16</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <doi>10.1137/141000671</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <doi>10.1016/B978-0-12-438150-6.50018-2</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.5281/zenodo.1409237</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <doi>10.1016/j.ocemod.2019.01.005</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <doi>10.1002/2015GB005334</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <doi>10.5065/D6V69H1T</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <doi>10.1175/1525-7541(2002)003</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <doi>10.21105/joss.03349</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <doi>10.1038/ngeo2300</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <doi>10.5194/bg-10-2481-2013</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref16">
            <doi>10.1038/nature21068</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref17">
            <doi>10.1029/2018JC014716</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref18">
            <doi>10.1175/JPO-D-10-05011.1</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref19">
            <doi>10.1002/2016GB005551</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref20">
            <doi>10.1029/2012GL051963</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref21">
            <doi>10.1002/2013GB004739</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref22">
            <doi>10.5281/zenodo.4284133</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref23">
            <doi>10.1175/2009JPO4043.1</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref24">
            <doi>10.1016/j.epsl.2017.11.008</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref25">
            <doi>10.1016/j.pocean.2018.09.008</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref26">
            <unstructured_citation>Ge, Hong and Xu, Kai and Ghahramani, Zoubin, Turing: a language for flexible probabilistic inference, International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics, AISTATS 2018, 9-11 April 2018, Playa Blanca, Lanzarote, Canary Islands, Spain, 1682–1690, 2018, http://proceedings.mlr.press/v84/ge18b.html, https://dblp.org/rec/bib/conf/aistats/GeXG18</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref27">
            <doi>10.1029/2020GB006863</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref28">
            <doi>10.1016/j.ocemod.2021.101762</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref29">
            <doi>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2019.119403</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref30">
            <doi>10.1137/1.9780898718898.ch1</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref31">
            <doi>10.1016/j.ocemod.2004.04.002</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref32">
            <doi>10.1029/2007GB002923</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref33">
            <doi>10.5194/acp-21-8169-2021</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref34">
            <doi>10.5194/gmd-10-2425-2017</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref35">
            <doi>10.5194/essd-8-325-2016</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref36">
            <doi>10.1594/PANGAEA.907641</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref37">
            <doi>10.1038/s41467-020-15064-8</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref38">
            <doi>10.5194/essd-8-297-2016</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref39">
            <doi>10.5194/bg-15-7177-2018</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref40">
            <doi>10.5281/zenodo.2864051</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref41">
            <doi>10.1002/jgrc.20181</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref42">
            <doi>10.5334/jors.151</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref43">
            <unstructured_citation>Forward-Mode Automatic Differentiation in Julia, Revels, J. and Lubin, M. and Papamarkou, T., arXiv:1607.07892 [cs.MS], 2016, https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.07892</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref44">
            <doi>10.1038/s41467-017-02227-3</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref45">
            <unstructured_citation>Sarmiento, J. L. and Gruber, N., Ocean Biogeochemical Dynamics, 503, Princeton Univ. Press, Princeton and Oxford, 2006</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref46">
            <unstructured_citation>Schlitzer, Reiner and Anderson, Robert F. and Dodas, Elena Masferrer and Lohan, Maeve and Geibert, Walter and Tagliabue, Alessandro and Bowie, Andrew and Jeandel, Catherine and Maldonado, Maria T and Landing, William M and Cockwell, Donna and Abadie, Cyril and Abouchami, Wafa and Achterberg, Eric P and Agather, Alison and Aguliar-Islas, Ana and van Aken, Hendrik M and Andersen, Morten and Archer, Corey and Auro, Maureen and de Baar, Hein J and Baars, Oliver and Baker, Alex R and Bakker, Karel and Basak, Chandranath and Baskaran, Mark and Bates, Nicholas R and Bauch, Dorothea and van Beek, Pieter and Behrens, Melanie K and Black, Erin and Bluhm, Katrin and Bopp, Laurent and Bouman, Heather and Bowman, Katlin and Bown, Johann and Boyd, Philip and Boye, Marie and Boyle, Edward A. and Branellec, Pierre and Bridgestock, Luke and Brissebrat, Guillaume and Browning, Thomas and Bruland, Kenneth W and Brumsack, Hans-Jürgen and Brzezinski, Mark and Buck, Clifton S and Buck, Kristen N and Buesseler, Ken and Bull, Abby and Butler, Edward and Cai, Pinghe and Mor, Patricia Cámara and Cardinal, Damien and Carlson, Craig and Carrasco, Gonzalo and Casacuberta, Núria and Casciotti, Karen L and Castrillejo, Maxi and Chamizo, Elena and Chance, Rosie and Charette, Matthew A and Chaves, Joaquin E and Cheng, Hai and Chever, Fanny and Christl, Marcus and Church, Thomas M and Closset, Ivia and Colman, Albert and Conway, Tim M and Cossa, Daniel and Croot, Peter and Cullen, Jay T and Cutter, Gregory A and Daniels, Chris and Dehairs, Frank and Deng, Feifei and Dieu, Huong Thi and Duggan, Brian and Dulaquais, Gabriel and Dumousseaud, Cynthia and Echegoyen-Sanz, Yolanda and Edwards, R Lawrence and Ellwood, Michael and Fahrbach, Eberhard and Fitzsimmons, Jessica N and Flegal, A Russell and Fleisher, Martin Q and van de Flierdt, Tina and Frank, Martin and Friedrich, Jana and Fripiat, François and Fröllje, Henning and Galer, Stephen J G and Gamo, Toshitaka and Ganeshram, Raja S and Garcia-Orellana, Jordi and Garcia-Solsona, Ester and Gault-Ringold, Melanie and George, Ejin and Gerringa, Loes J A and Gilbert, Melissa and Godoy, Jose M and Goldstein, Steven L. and Gonzalez, Santiago R and Grissom, Karen and Hammerschmidt, Chad and Hartman, Alison and Hassler, Christel S and Hathorne, Ed C and Hatta, Mariko and Hawco, Nicholas and Hayes, Christopher T and Heimbürger, Lars-Eric and Helgoe, Josh and Heller, Maija and Henderson, Gideon M and Henderson, Paul B and van Heuven, Steven and Ho, Peng and Horner, Tristan J and Hsieh, Yu-Te and Huang, Kuo-Fang and Humphreys, Matthew P and Isshiki, Kenji and Jacquot, Jeremy E and Janssen, David J and Jenkins, William J and John, Seth and Jones, Elizabeth M and Jones, Janice L and Kadko, David C and Kayser, Rick and Kenna, Timothy C and Khondoker, Roulin and Kim, Taejin and Kipp, Lauren and Klar, Jessica K and Klunder, Maarten and Kretschmer, Sven and Kumamoto, Yuichiro and Laan, Patrick and Labatut, Marie and Lacan, François and Lam, Phoebe J and Lambelet, Myriam and Lamborg, Carl H and Le Moigne, Frédéric A C and Le Roy, Emilie and Lechtenfeld, Oliver J and Lee, Jong-Mi and Lherminier, Pascale and Little, Susan and López-Lora, Mercedes and Lu, Yanbin and Masque, Pere and Mawji, Edward and Mcclain, Charles R and Measures, Christopher and Mehic, Sanjin and Barraqueta, Jan-Lukas Menzel and van der Merwe, Pier and Middag, Rob and Mieruch, Sebastian and Milne, Angela and Minami, Tomoharu and Moffett, James W and Moncoiffe, Gwenaelle and Moore, Willard S and Morris, Paul J and Morton, Peter L and Nakaguchi, Yuzuru and Nakayama, Noriko and Niedermiller, John and Nishioka, Jun and Nishiuchi, Akira and Noble, Abigail and Obata, Hajime and Ober, Sven and Ohnemus, Daniel C and van Ooijen, Jan and O’Sullivan, Jeanette and Owens, Stephanie and Pahnke, Katharina and Paul, Maxence and Pavia, Frank and Pena, Leopoldo D and Peters, Brian and Planchon, Frederic and Planquette, Helene and Pradoux, Catherine and Puigcorbé, Viena and Quay, Paul and Queroue, Fabien and Radic, Amandine and Rauschenberg, S and Rehkämper, Mark and Rember, Robert and Remenyi, Tomas and Resing, Joseph A and Rickli, Joerg and Rigaud, Sylvain and Rijkenberg, Micha J A and Rintoul, Stephen and Robinson, Laura F. and Roca-Martı́, Montserrat and Rodellas, Valenti and Roeske, Tobias and Rolison, John M and Rosenberg, Mark and Roshan, Saeed and van der Loeff, Michiel M Rutgers and Ryabenko, Evgenia and Saito, Mak A and Salt, Lesley A and Sanial, Virginie and Sarthou, Geraldine and Schallenberg, Christina and Schauer, Ursula and Scher, Howie and Schlosser, Christian and Schnetger, Bernhard and Scott, Peter and Sedwick, Peter N and Semiletov, Igor and Shelley, Rachel…, The GEOTRACES Intermediate Data Product 2017, Chemical Geology, 2018, 493, 210–223, aug, 8</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref47">
            <doi>10.1175/1520-0485(1993)023</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref48">
            <unstructured_citation>Applying the adjoint method for biogeochemical modeling: export of particulate organic matter in the world ocean, Schlitzer, Reiner, Geophysical Monograph-American Geophysical Union, 114, 107–124, 2000, AGU</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref49">
            <doi>10.5194/os-15-1207-2019</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref50">
            <doi>10.1038/ngeo2303</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref51">
            <doi>10.1029/JC094iC05p06177</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref52">
            <doi>10.1038/s41586-019-0911-2</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref53">
            <doi>10.1038/nature09403</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref54">
            <doi>10.1073/pnas.1604414113</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref55">
            <doi>10.1126/science.aap8532</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref56">
            <doi>10.5334/jors.244</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref57">
            <unstructured_citation>Garcia, H. E. and Weathers, K. and Paver, C. R. and Smolyar, I. and Boyer, T. P. and Locarnini, R. A. and Zweng, M. M. and Mishonov, A. V. and Baranova, O. K. and Seidov, D. and Reagan, J. R., World Ocean Atlas 2018: Dissolved Inorganic Nutrients (phosphate, nitrate and nitrate+nitrite, silicate), 4, 2018, NOAA National Centers for Environmental Information, A. Mishonov Technical Ed.</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref58">
            <doi>10.1073/pnas.1808838115</doi>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
