<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>osmdata</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Mark Padgham</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Robin Lovelace</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            3
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Maëlle Salmon</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Bob Rudis</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            4
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>openstreetmap</tag>
      <tag>spatial</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>Simple Features</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>8 March 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00305</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropensci/osmdata</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.803231</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/raw/master/joss.00305/10.21105.joss.00305.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><code>osmdata</code> imports OpenStreetMap (OSM) data into R as either Simple Features or <code>R</code> Spatial objects, respectively able to be processed with the R packages <code>sf</code> and <code>sp</code>. OSM data are extracted from the Overpass API and processed with very fast C++ routines for return to R. The package enables simple Overpass queries to be constructed without the user necessarily understanding the syntax of the Overpass query language, while retaining the ability to handle arbitrarily complex queries. Functions are also provided to enable recursive searching between different kinds of OSM data (for example, to find all lines which intersect a given point). The package is faster than current alternatives for importing OSM data into R and is the only one compatible with <code>sf</code>.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-eugster_osmar:_2012">
    <p>Eugster, Manuel J a, and Thomas Schlesinger. 2012. “Osmar: OpenStreetMap and R.” <em>The R Journal</em> 5 (1): 53–64.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-johnson_models_2017">
    <p>Johnson, Peter A. 2017. “Models of Direct Editing of Government Spatial Data: Challenges and Constraints to the Acceptance of Contributed Data.” <em>Cartography and Geographic Information Science</em> 44 (2): 128–38. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/15230406.2016.1176536">10.1080/15230406.2016.1176536</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-lovelace_harnessing_2014">
    <p>Lovelace, Robin. 2014. “Harnessing Open Street Map Data with R and QGIS.” <em>EloGeo</em>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-mashhadi2015impact">
    <p>Mashhadi, Afra, Giovanni Quattrone, and Licia Capra. 2015. “The Impact of Society on Volunteered Geographic Information: The Case of Openstreetmap.” In <em>OpenStreetMap in Giscience</em>, 125–41. Springer.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-neis2012analyzing">
    <p>Neis, Pascal, and Alexander Zipf. 2012. “Analyzing the Contributor Activity of a Volunteered Geographic Information Project—The Case of Openstreetmap.” <em>ISPRS International Journal of Geo-Information</em> 1 (2). Molecular Diversity Preservation International: 146–65.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-olbricht2015data">
    <p>Olbricht, Roland M. 2015. “Data Retrieval for Small Spatial Regions in Openstreetmap.” In <em>OpenStreetMap in Giscience</em>, 101–22. Springer.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-OpenStreetMap">
    <p>OpenStreetMap contributors. 2017. “Planet dump retrieved from http://planet.osm.org.” <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org" class="uri">http://www.openstreetmap.org</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-osmplotr">
    <p>Padgham, Mark. 2016. <em>Osmplotr: Customisable Images of Openstreetmap Data</em>. <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=osmplotr" class="uri">https://cran.r-project.org/package=osmplotr</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
