<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>ClimDown: Climate Downscaling in R</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>James Hiebert</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4171-9586</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Alex J. Cannon</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Trevor Murdock</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Stephen Sobie</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Arelia Werner</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>climate</tag>
      <tag>downscaling</tag>
      <tag>spatiotemporal</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>1 February 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00360</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/pacificclimate/ClimDown</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1184647</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00360/10.21105.joss.00360.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>The ClimDown R package publishes the routines and techniques of the <a href="https://pacificclimate.org/">Pacific Climate Impacts Consortium</a> (PCIC) for downscaling coarse scale Global Climate Models (GCMs) to fine scale spatial resolution.</p>
    <p>PCIC’s overall downscaling algorithm is named Bias-corrected constructed analogues with quantile mapping reordering (BCCAQ) <span class="citation" data-cites="cannon15 werner16">(Cannon, Sobie, and Murdock 2015; Werner and Cannon 2016)</span>. BCCAQ is a hybrid downscaling method that combines outputs from Constructed Analogues (CA) <span class="citation" data-cites="maurer10">(Maurer et al. 2010)</span> and quantile mapping at the fine-scale resolution. First, the CA and Climate Imprint (CI) <span class="citation" data-cites="hunter05">(Hunter and Meentemeyer 2005)</span> plus quantile delta mapping (QDM) <span class="citation" data-cites="cannon15">(Cannon, Sobie, and Murdock 2015)</span> algorithms are run independently. BCCAQ then combines outputs from the two by taking the daily QDM outputs at each fine-scale grid point and reordering them within a given month according to the daily CA ranks, i.e., using a form of Empirical Copula Coupling <span class="citation" data-cites="schefzik13">(Schefzik, Thorarinsdottir, and Gneiting 2013)</span>.</p>
    <p>The package exports high-level wrapper functions that perform each of three downscaling steps: CI, CA, and QDM, as well as one wrapper that runs the entire BCCAQ pipeline.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-cannon15">
    <p>Cannon, A. J., S. R. Sobie, and T. Q. Murdock. 2015. “Bias Correction of Gcm Precipitation by Quantile Mapping: How Well Do Methods Preserve Changes in Quantiles and Extremes?” <em>Journal of Climate</em> 28(17):6938–59. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-14-00754.1" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-14-00754.1</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-hunter05">
    <p>Hunter, R. D., and R. K. Meentemeyer. 2005. “Climatologically Aided Mapping of Daily Precipitation and Temperature.” <em>Journal of Applied Meteorology</em> 44(10):1501–10.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-maurer10">
    <p>Maurer, E. P., H. G. Hidalgo, T. Das, M. D. Dettinger, and D. R Cayan. 2010. “The Utility of Daily Large-Scale Climate Data in the Assessment of Climate Change Impacts on Daily Streamflow in California.” <em>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences</em> 14(6):1125–38.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-schefzik13">
    <p>Schefzik, R., T. L. Thorarinsdottir, and T. Gneiting. 2013. “Uncertainty Quantification in Complex Simulation Models Using Ensemble Copula Coupling.” <em>Statistical Science</em> 28(4):616–40.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-werner16">
    <p>Werner, A. T., and A. J. Cannon. 2016. “Hydrologic Extremes - an Intercomparison of Multiple Gridded Statistical Downscaling Methods.” <em>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences</em> 20(4):1483–1508. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-20-1483-2016" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-20-1483-2016</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
