<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>qqman: an R package for visualizing GWAS results using Q-Q and manhattan plots</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Stephen D. Turner</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-9140-9028</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1, 2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>genetic epidemiology</tag>
      <tag>gwas</tag>
      <tag>manhattan plot</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>25 April 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00731</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/stephenturner/qqman/</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.591547</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00731/10.21105.joss.00731.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have been successful in identifying thousands of trait and disease-associated single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). The primary result of a GWAS analysis is a list of SNPs, their associated chromosomal position, and a P-value representing the statistical significance of the association. A commonly used method used to visualize GWAS results is the “manhattan plot” – a plot of the <span class="math inline">−<em>l</em><em>o</em><em>g</em><sub>10</sub>(<em>P</em>)</span> of the association statistic on the <em>y</em>-axis versus the chromosomal position of the SNP on the <em>x</em>-axis. Another commonly used results diagnostic plot is the quantile-quantile (“Q-Q”) plot. Q-Q plots display the observed association <em>P</em>-value for all SNPs on the y-axis versus the expected uniform distribution of P-values under the null hypothesis of no association on the <em>x</em>-axis.</p>
    <p>One of the most commonly used software packages for manipulating and analyzing GWAS data is PLINK (<span class="citation" data-cites="purcell2007plink">Purcell et al. (2007)</span>). <code>qqman</code> is an R package that allows for quick and flexible generation of publication-ready Q-Q and manhattan plots directly from PLINK results files. The <code>qqman</code> package is a user-friendly tool to visualize results from GWAS experiments using Q-Q and manhattan plots. The <code>manhattan()</code> function in the <code>qqman</code> package takes a data frame with columns containing the chromosome number, chromosomal position, P-value, and optionally the SNP name. By default, <code>manhattan()</code> looks for column names corresponding to those output by the <code>plink --assoc</code> command, namely, “CHR,” “BP,” “P,” and “SNP,” although different column names can be specified by the user. Thresholds for suggestive and genome-wide significance are drawn, and users also have the ability to highlight/annotate SNPs of interest. Finally, the <code>qq()</code> function can be used to generate a Q-Q plot to visualize the distribution of association <em>P</em>-values. An example of the plots produced by <code>qqman</code> is shown in Figure 1.</p>
    <p>These graphics can be created in other software, such as the standalone desktop software Haploview (<span class="citation" data-cites="barrett2004haploview">Barrett et al. (2004)</span>), or for focused regions using the web-based application LocusZoom (<span class="citation" data-cites="pruim2010locuszoom">Pruim et al. (2010)</span>). Conversely, <code>qqman</code> is distributed as an R package with no other dependencies that can be easily integrated into existing R-based scripted workflows to further enable automated reproducible research. Furthermore, users can take advantage of R’s very granular control of graphical output, enabling a high degree of customizability in creating high-resolution, publication-ready figures. The <code>qqman</code> package ships with example data and a detailed vignette illustrating its usage and further features not described here. The package is available on GitHub under the GNU General Public License at <a href="https://github.com/stephenturner/qqman" class="uri">https://github.com/stephenturner/qqman</a> and on the Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN) at <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=qqman" class="uri">https://cran.r-project.org/package=qqman</a>.</p>
    <figure>
    <img src="fig1.png" alt="Manhattan plot highlighting SNPs of interest on chromosome 3, with Q-Q plot showing substantial deviation from the diagonal (inset)." /><figcaption>Manhattan plot highlighting SNPs of interest on chromosome 3, with Q-Q plot showing substantial deviation from the diagonal (inset).</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-barrett2004haploview">
    <p>Barrett, Jeffrey C, B Fry, JDMJ Maller, and Mark J Daly. 2004. “Haploview: Analysis and Visualization of Ld and Haplotype Maps.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 21 (2). Oxford University Press:263–65. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bth457" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bth457</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-pruim2010locuszoom">
    <p>Pruim, Randall J, Ryan P Welch, Serena Sanna, Tanya M Teslovich, Peter S Chines, Terry P Gliedt, Michael Boehnke, Gonçalo R Abecasis, and Cristen J Willer. 2010. “LocusZoom: Regional Visualization of Genome-Wide Association Scan Results.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 26 (18). Oxford University Press:2336–7. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq419" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq419</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-purcell2007plink">
    <p>Purcell, Shaun, Benjamin Neale, Kathe Todd-Brown, Lori Thomas, Manuel AR Ferreira, David Bender, Julian Maller, et al. 2007. “PLINK: A Tool Set for Whole-Genome Association and Population-Based Linkage Analyses.” <em>The American Journal of Human Genetics</em> 81 (3). Elsevier:559–75. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/519795" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1086/519795</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
