<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>The psycho Package: an Efficient and Publishing-Oriented Workflow for Psychological Science</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Dominique Makowski</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-5375-9967</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1,2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>Psychology</tag>
      <tag>Interpratation</tag>
      <tag>Formatting</tag>
      <tag>Correlation</tag>
      <tag>Assessement</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>01 January 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00470</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/neuropsychology/psycho.R</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1165620</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00470/10.21105.joss.00470.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Statistics are a vital aspect of psychological science. Unfortunately, the process of analyzing, formatting and reporting results is often fastidious, time-consuming and prone to errors, resulting in frustration and aversion. On top of that, many available tools for professionals and students are either overpriced, too complex (<em>i.e.</em>, displaying vast amounts of raw information neither demanded nor needed by the user) or too basic (<em>i.e.</em>, not supporting advanced statistical procedures). These factors contribute to the reproducibility crisis in psychological science <span class="citation" data-cites="Chambers2014">(Chambers et al. 2014, <span class="citation" data-cites="Etz2016">Etz and Vandekerckhove (2016)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="Szucs2016">Szucs and Ioannidis (2016)</span>)</span>.</p>
    <figure>
    <img src="figure1.PNG" alt="psycho-workflow" /><figcaption>psycho-workflow</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>Psycho is an R package <span class="citation" data-cites="team2000r">(Team 2000)</span> whose main goal is to fill the gap between statistical analyses and publication-ready documents, involving information selection, results transformation and text formatting. These steps, beyond being the most time-consuming part of statistical analysis in psychological science, are the source of many human errors and can lead to a badly formatted results section, veiling the general quality of a paper. The <code>psycho</code> package, built for psychologists, neuropsychologists and neuroscientists, also implements commonly used routines such as correlation matrices, assessment plot creation or standardization. The package revolves around the <code>psychobject</code>, returned by most of its functions. Additionally, the <code>analyze()</code> function transforms other R objects into psychobjects. Four methods can then be applied to them: <code>summary()</code>, <code>print()</code>, <code>plot()</code> and <code>values()</code>, resulting in a simple yet flexible workflow.</p>
    <p>A special focus has been dedicated to the support of cutting-edge statistical routines, such as mixed-models. Moreover, a specific attention has been devoted to the promotion, through support and documentation, of the Bayesian framework. Indeed, beyond the many methodological reasons to prefer this approach (better accuracy in noisy data, the possibility of introducing prior knowledge into the analysis and, critically, results intuitiveness and their straightforward interpretation; <span class="citation" data-cites="lee2012bayesian">(Lee 2012, <span class="citation" data-cites="gabry2016rstanarm">Gabry and Goodrich (2016)</span>)</span>), its core ideology (computing the probability of different effects compatible with the observed data) sets it as the right way of answering the questions of psychology.</p>
    <p>Contrary to many other packages, whose goal is to produce statistical analyses, <code>psycho</code> bridges statistical R outputs with statistical reports writing, with a focus on APA formatting guidelines, to enhance the standardization of results reporting. Complex outputs, such as those of Bayesian and frequentist mixed models, are automatically transformed into readable text, tables, and plots that illustrate the effects. With this package, results can be easily incorporated into shareable reports and publications, promoting data exploration, saving time and preventing errors for better, reproducible, science.</p>
    <p>The <code>psycho</code> package can be downloaded and installed from CRAN <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=psycho">1</a>. Source code is available from its GitHub repository <a href="https://github.com/neuropsychology/psycho.R">2</a>. Documentation <a href="https://www.rdocumentation.org/packages/psycho">3</a>, examples <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=psycho/vignettes/overview.html">4</a> and issues tracker <a href="https://github.com/neuropsychology/psycho.R/issues">5</a> are also provided for a user-friendly interface.</p>
    <h1 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h1>
    <p>We warmly thank all the <a href="https://github.com/neuropsychology/psycho.R/graphs/contributors">contributors</a> as well as Maurice Moss for its insights.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Chambers2014">
    <p>Chambers, Christopher D., Eva Feredoes, D. Muthukumaraswamy, Suresh, and Peter J. Etchells. 2014. “Instead of ‘playing the game’ it is time to change the rules: Registered Reports at AIMS Neuroscience and beyond.” <em>AIMS Neuroscience</em> 1 (1):4–17. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3934/Neuroscience.2014.1.4" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.3934/Neuroscience.2014.1.4</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Etz2016">
    <p>Etz, Alexander, and Joachim Vandekerckhove. 2016. “A Bayesian perspective on the reproducibility project: Psychology.” <em>PLoS ONE</em> 11 (2). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0149794" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0149794</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-gabry2016rstanarm">
    <p>Gabry, Jonah, and Ben Goodrich. 2016. “Rstanarm: Bayesian Applied Regression Modeling via Stan.” <em>R Package Version</em> 2 (1).</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-lee2012bayesian">
    <p>Lee, Peter M. 2012. <em>Bayesian Statistics: An Introduction</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Szucs2016">
    <p>Szucs, Denes, and John PA Ioannidis. 2016. “Empirical assessment of published effect sizes and power in the recent cognitive neuroscience and psychology literature.” <em>bioRxiv</em>, 071530. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/071530" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1101/071530</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-team2000r">
    <p>Team, R Core. 2000. “R Language Definition.” <em>Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing</em>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
