<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>simpleCache: R caching for reproducible, distributed, large-scale projects</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Nathan Sheffield</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-5643-4068</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>VP Nagraj</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-0060-566X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Vince Reuter</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-7967-976X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <date>28 October 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00463</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/databio/simpleCache</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1140853</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00463/10.21105.joss.00463.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><code>simpleCache</code> is an R<span class="citation" data-cites="R">(R Core Team 2016)</span> package that provides functions for caching R objects. Its purpose is to encourage writing reusable, restartable, and reproducible analysis for projects with large data and computational requirements. Like its name indicates, <code>simpleCache</code> is intended to be simple. Users specify a location to store caches, and then provide nothing more than a cache name and instructions (R code) for how to produce an R object. <code>simpleCache</code> either creates and saves or simply loads the result as necessary with just a single function call.</p>
    <p>In addition to this basic functionality, <code>simpleCache</code> has advanced options for assigning objects to specific environments, recreating caches, reloading caches, and even distributing caching operations to cluster computing resources via the <code>batchools</code><span class="citation" data-cites="batchtools">(Lang, Bischl, and Surmann 2017)</span> interface. These features make the package particularly useful for large-scale data analysis and research projects. <code>simpleCache</code> is most helpful for caching objects that are computationally expensive to create, but used in multiple scripts or by multiple users.</p>
    <p><code>simpleCache</code> is also useful to enhance performance in a package that relies on large databases. For example, <code>simpleCache</code> has been incorporated with the LOLA R package<span class="citation" data-cites="LOLA">(Sheffield and Bock 2016)</span> to more efficiently cache and retrieve genomic region databases. Similarly, <code>simpleCache</code> has been used to store cached baseline statistical tables for faster lookup to determine statistical differences on tables with hundreds of millions of data points <span class="citation" data-cites="RPIM">(Sheffield et al. 2017)</span>.</p>
    <p>In summary, <code>simpleCache</code> provides a user-friendly interface to help the R programmer manage computationally intensive, repeated data analysis.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-batchtools">
    <p>Lang, Michel, Bernd Bischl, and Dirk Surmann. 2017. “Batchtools: Tools for R to Work on Batch Systems.” <em>The Journal of Open Source Software</em> 2 (10). <a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00135" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00135</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R">
    <p>R Core Team. 2016. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-LOLA">
    <p>Sheffield, N. C., and C. Bock. 2016. “LOLA: Enrichment Analysis for Genomic Region Sets and Regulatory Elements in R and Bioconductor.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 32 (4):587–89. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btv612" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btv612</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-RPIM">
    <p>Sheffield, N. C., G. Pierron, J. Klughammer, P. Datlinger, A. Schonegger, M. Schuster, J. Hadler, et al. 2017. “DNA Methylation Heterogeneity Defines a Disease Spectrum in Ewing Sarcoma.” <em>Nature Medicine</em> 23 (3):386–95. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.4273" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.4273</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
