<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>hydroscoper: R interface to the Greek National Data Bank for Hydrological and Meteorological Information</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Konstantinos Vantas</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-6387-8791</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>tidy data</tag>
      <tag>Hydrology</tag>
      <tag>Meteorology</tag>
      <tag>Greece</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>01 Mar 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00625</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropensci/hydroscoper</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1196540</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00625/10.21105.joss.00625.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>The Greek National Data bank for Hydrological and Meteorological Information, Hydroscope <span class="citation" data-cites="hydroscope2018">(Hydroscope 2018)</span>, is the result of long-standing efforts by numerous Greek scientists in collaboration with various companies and associations. Its main purpose is the formation of the basic infrastructure for the implementation of the European Community Directives 2000/60/EC (i.e. establishment of a framework for Community action in the field of water policy) and 2007/60/EC, (i.e. assessment and management of flood risks).</p>
    <p>Hydroscope offers several national data sources in HTML and plain text files via a web interface, using the Enhydris database system <span class="citation" data-cites="christofides2011enhydris">(Christofides et al. 2011)</span>. These data are well structured but are in Greek, thus limiting their usefulness. Furthermore, fully reproducible research <span class="citation" data-cites="peng2011reproducible">(Peng 2011)</span> can be tedious and error-prone using Hydroscope’s web interface. On the contrary, using the Enhydris API for reproducibility requires external programs and scripting to import the data.</p>
    <p><code>hydroscoper</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="hydroscoper2018">(Vantas 2018)</span> provides functionality for automatic retrieval and translation of Hydroscope’s data to English for use in R <span class="citation" data-cites="Rbase">(R Core Team 2018)</span>. The main functions that can be utilized is the family of functions, <code>get_stations</code>, <code>get_timeseries</code>, <code>get_data</code>, etc., to easily download JSON and TXT files as tidy data frames <span class="citation" data-cites="Wickham2014">(Wickham 2014)</span>. The internal databases of the package can be used to run queries on the available stations and time series, reducing the time needed for downloading and data wrangling <span class="citation" data-cites="kandel2011research">(Kandel et al. 2011)</span>, as these data are rarely modified.</p>
    <p>The data have many applications. In general, availability of meteorological and hydrological information is essential for water resources management, water quality assessment and global change studies <span class="citation" data-cites="vafiadis1994hydroscope">(Vafiadis, Tolikas, and Koutsoyiannis 1994)</span>. Also, these data can be used by researchers to forward their studies when specific requirements of time series are required, such as the estimation of rainfall erosivity <span class="citation" data-cites="vantas_sid2017">(Vantas and Sidiropoulos 2017)</span>. Finally, the data are crucial to Greek organizations for the implementation of the Water Framework Directive 2000-2027 <span class="citation" data-cites="WFD">(European Commission 2018)</span>.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-christofides2011enhydris">
    <p>Christofides, Antonis, Stefanos Kozanis, George Karavokiros, Yannis Markonis, and Andreas Efstratiadis. 2011. “Enhydris: A Free Database System for the Storage and Management of Hydrological and Meteorological Data.” <em>European Geosciences Union General Assembly Geophysical Research Abstracts</em> 13.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-WFD">
    <p>European Commission, EC. 2018. “Water Framework Directive: Timetable for Implementation.” <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/water/water-framework/info/timetable_en.htm" class="uri">http://ec.europa.eu/environment/water/water-framework/info/timetable_en.htm</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-hydroscope2018">
    <p>Hydroscope. 2018. “Greek National Data Bank for Hydrological and Meteorological Information.” <a href="http://www.hydroscope.gr/" class="uri">http://www.hydroscope.gr/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-kandel2011research">
    <p>Kandel, Sean, Jeffrey Heer, Catherine Plaisant, Jessie Kennedy, Frank van Ham, Nathalie Henry Riche, Chris Weaver, Bongshin Lee, Dominique Brodbeck, and Paolo Buono. 2011. “Research Directions in Data Wrangling: Visualizations and Transformations for Usable and Credible Data.” <em>Information Visualization</em> 10 (4). Sage Publications Sage UK: London, England:271–88. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1473871611415994" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1177/1473871611415994</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-peng2011reproducible">
    <p>Peng, Roger D. 2011. “Reproducible Research in Computational Science.” <em>Science</em> 334 (6060). American Association for the Advancement of Science:1226–7. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1213847" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1213847</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Rbase">
    <p>R Core Team. 2018. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-vafiadis1994hydroscope">
    <p>Vafiadis, M, D Tolikas, and D Koutsoyiannis. 1994. “HYDROSCOPE: The new Greek national database system for meteorological, hydrological and hydrogeological information.” In <em>WIT Transactions on Ecology and the Environment</em>, 1–8.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-hydroscoper2018">
    <p>Vantas, Konstantinos. 2018. “Hydroscoper: R Interface to the Greek National Data Bank for Hydrological and Meteorological Information.” <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1196540" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1196540</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-vantas_sid2017">
    <p>Vantas, Konstantinos, and Epameinontas Sidiropoulos. 2017. “Imputation of Erosivity Values Under Incomplete Rainfall Data by Machine Learning Methods.” <em>European Water</em> 57:193–97.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Wickham2014">
    <p>Wickham, Hadley. 2014. “Tidy Data.” <em>Journal of Statistical Software</em> 59 (1):1–23. <a href="https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v059.i10" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v059.i10</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
