<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>USAboundaries: Historical and Contemporary Boundaries of the United States of America</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Lincoln A. Mullen</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-5103-6917</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Jordan Bratt</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-9051-7203</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>spatial</tag>
      <tag>history</tag>
      <tag>digital-history</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>20 March 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00314</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropensci/USAboundaries</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.825218</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00314/10.21105.joss.00314.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <p>The <code>USAboundaries</code> package for R provides contemporary and historical boundaries of the United States of America <span class="citation" data-cites="USAboundaries">(Mullen and Bratt 2017)</span>. (The package is available on <a href="https://github.com/ropensci/USAboundaries/">GitHub</a> and archived on <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.825218">Zenodo</a>.) Historical data in the package includes state and county boundaries from 1629 to 2000 from the Newberry Library’s “Atlas of Historical County Boundaries” <span class="citation" data-cites="ahcb">(Long and others 2010)</span>. Also included is historical city population data from Erik Steiner’s “United States Historical City Populations, 1790-2010” <span class="citation" data-cites="steiner-cities">(Steiner 2016)</span>. Contemporary data in the package includes state, county, and Congressional district boundaries, as well as Zip Code Tabulation Area centroids. These data are all drawn from the U.S. Census Burea <span class="citation" data-cites="census">(U.S. Census Bureau 2017)</span>.</p>
    <p>These historical and contemporary boundaries are provided at different resolutions suitable for national and state-level mapping. A consistent interface provides a way to easily select historical boundaries for any specific date. The package includes helper functions and datasets, including tables of state names, abbreviations and FIPS codes for joining to attribute date as well as functions and date to get State Plane Coordinate System projections as EPSG codes or PROJ.4 strings <span class="citation" data-cites="stateplane">(Stem 1989)</span>. A first step in many spatial analyses is joining data of interest to spatial data, which the datasets in this package enable.</p>
    <p>This package underlies the <a href="http://earlyamericanelections.org/"><em>Mapping Early American Elections</em></a> project created by a team at the Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media <span class="citation" data-cites="meae">(team 2016–2019)</span>. That project maps Congressional elections and state legislative elections from 1787 to 1825. The USAboundaries package provides access to the frequently changing state and county boundaries during that time period.</p>
    <p><em>Development of this package was partially funded by a Humanities Collections and Reference Resources grant from the Division of Preservation and Access at the National Endowment for the Humanities (grant number PW-234776-16). The package is part of <a href="https://ropensci.org/">rOpenSci</a>.</em></p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-ahcb">
    <p>Long, John H., and others. 2010. “Atlas of Historical County Boundaries.” Dr. William M. Scholl Center for American History; Culture, The Newberry Library; <a href="http://publications.newberry.org/ahcbp/" class="uri">http://publications.newberry.org/ahcbp/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-USAboundaries">
    <p>Mullen, Lincoln, and Jordan Bratt. 2017. <em>USAboundaries: Historical and Contemporary Boundaries of the United States of America</em>. <a href="http://lincolnmullen.com/software/usaboundaries/" class="uri">http://lincolnmullen.com/software/usaboundaries/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-steiner-cities">
    <p>Steiner, Erik. 2016. “United States Historical City Populations, 1790-2010.” Spatial History Project, Center for Spatial; Textual Analysis, Stanford University; <a href="https://github.com/cestastanford/historical-us-city-populations/" class="uri">https://github.com/cestastanford/historical-us-city-populations/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-stateplane">
    <p>Stem, James E. 1989. “State Plane Coordinate System of 1983.” National Oceanographic; Atmospheric Administration; <a href="https://www.ngs.noaa.gov/PUBS_LIB/ManualNOSNGS5.pdf" class="uri">https://www.ngs.noaa.gov/PUBS_LIB/ManualNOSNGS5.pdf</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-meae">
    <p>team, Mapping Early American Elections project. 2016–2019. “Mapping Early American Elections.” Roy Rosenzweig Center for History; New Media, George Mason University; <a href="http://earlyamericanelections.org/" class="uri">http://earlyamericanelections.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-census">
    <p>U.S. Census Bureau. 2017. “Cartographic Boundary Shapefiles.” <a href="https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger-cart-boundary.html" class="uri">https://www.census.gov/geo/maps-data/data/tiger-cart-boundary.html</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
