<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3504</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03504</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Finnish Media Scrapers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8366-8414</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Mäkelä</surname>
<given-names>Eetu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0003-0872-7098</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Toivanen</surname>
<given-names>Pihla</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Helsinki</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">* E-mail: <email></email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2021-06-21">
<day>21</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>68</issue>
<fpage>3504</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>Web scraping</kwd>
<kwd>Media research</kwd>
<kwd>Python</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Finnish Media Scrapers is a package for extracting articles from
  Finnish journalistic media websites. Included are scrapers for the
  four biggest Finnish journalistic media:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.yle.fi/uutiset/">YLE</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hs.fi/">Helsingin
  Sanomat</ext-link>,
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iltalehti.fi/">Iltalehti</ext-link>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.is.fi/">Iltasanomat</ext-link>.
  The scrapers have been designed for researchers needing a local corpus
  of news article texts matching a specified set of query keywords as
  well as temporal limitations. As a design principle, these scrapers
  have been designed to extract the articles in as trustworthy a manner
  as possible, as required for content-focused research targetting the
  text of those articles. Further, the process is split into distinct
  parts that 1) query, 2) fetch, 3) convert to text and 4) post-filter
  the articles separately. Each of these steps also records its output
  as separate files. This way, the tools can be used in a versatile
  manner. Further, a good record is maintained of the querying and
  filtering process for reproducibility as well as error analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>There is an increasing need for user-friendly computational tools
  in the humanities and social sciences. For example, a common workflow
  in media research is to collect a large amount of data and combine
  quantitative and qualitative methods in the analysis phase (Koivunen
  et al.
  (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-Koivunen" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>),
  Weber &amp; Monge
  (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-Weber2011" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)).
  This package responds to the research needs by providing easy-to-use
  tools for scraping Finnish media articles and extracting the article
  texts from the scraped HTML files. At the same time, the functionality
  has also been packaged as a Python module for the benefit of more
  computationally-savvy users.</p>
  <p>The scripts were originally developed for a data journalism article
  (Suomen Kuvalehti et al.
  (<xref alt="2021" rid="ref-SKarticle" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>))
  analyzing how Finnish members of parliament were represented in the
  media in 2020. Further developing and packaging the scripts into a
  reusable package was based on an expressed interest from the Finnish
  computational science community. Since initial beta release a couple
  of months ago, the package is now known to be already used in at least
  two research projects targeting Finnish media analysis.</p>
  <sec id="related-work">
    <title>Related work</title>
    <p>For a more general library for crawling media articles, have a
    look at
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://newspaper.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html">newspaper3k</ext-link>
    as well as
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/fhamborg/news-please">news-please</ext-link>,
    which has been built on top of it. Do note however that at the time
    of writing this, it is
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/codelucas/newspaper/issues/878">unclear</ext-link>
    whether newspaper3k is being maintained any more. More importantly
    for content research purposes, note that 1) newspaper3k does not
    handle the Finnish news sources targeted by this crawler very well
    and 2) it is based more on a best-effort principle (suitable for
    extracting masses of data for e.g. NLP training) as opposed to
    completeness and verisimilitude (required for trustworthy
    content-focused research targetting a particular set of news). Thus,
    given an article URL, newspaper3k will happily try to return
    something from it, but not guarantee completeness. This crawler on
    the other hand has been designed to be conservative, and to complain
    loudly through logging whenever it encounters problems that may
    hinder extracting the actual text of the article, such as article
    layouts that haven’t been yet handled and verified to extract
    correctly.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="general-workflow">
  <title>General workflow</title>
  <p>The general workflow for using the scrapers is as follows: 1. The
  scrapers support specifying a keyword as well as a timespan for
  extraction, and output a CSV of all matching articles with links. 2. A
  second set of scripts then allows downloading the matched articles in
  HTML format. 3. Third, there are further scripts for extracting plain
  text versions of the article texts out of the HTML. 4. Finally, a
  script exists to post-filter the resulting plain texts again with
  keywords.</p>
  <p>Important to know when applying the workflow is that due to the
  fact that all the sources use some kind of stemming for their search,
  they can often return also spurious hits. Further, if searching for
  multiple words, the engines often perform a search for either word
  instead of the complete phrase. The post-filtering script above exists
  to counteract this by allowing the refiltering of the results more
  rigorously and uniformly locally.</p>
  <p>At the same time and equally importantly, the stemming for a
  particular media may not cover e.g. all inflectional forms of words.
  Thus, it often makes sense to query for at least all common inflected
  variants and merge the results. For a complete worked up example of
  this kind of use, see the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/hsci-r/finnish-media-scraper/tree/master/members_of_parliament">members_of_parliament</ext-link>
  folder, which demonstrates how one can collect and count how many
  articles in each media mention the members of the Finnish
  Parliament.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We acknowledge contributions from the Suomen Kuvalehti team (Samuel
  Nyroos, Salla Vuorikoski and Leena Sharma) during the testing phase of
  the scrapers.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref id="ref-Koivunen">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Koivunen</surname><given-names>Anu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kanner</surname><given-names>Antti</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Janicki</surname><given-names>Maciej</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Harju</surname><given-names>Auli</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hokkanen</surname><given-names>Julius</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Mäkelä</surname><given-names>Eetu</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Emotive, evaluative, epistemic: A linguistic analysis of affectivity in news journalism</article-title>
      <source>Journalism</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021">2021</year>
      <volume>22</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1464884920985724</pub-id>
      <fpage>1190</fpage>
      <lpage>1206</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Weber2011">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>Matthew S.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Monge</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>The flow of digital news in a network of sources, authorities, and hubs</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Communication</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
      <volume>61</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-2466.2011.01596.x</pub-id>
      <fpage>1062</fpage>
      <lpage>1081</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-SKarticle">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <string-name>Suomen Kuvalehti</string-name>
        <name><surname>Mäkelä</surname><given-names>Eetu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Toivanen</surname><given-names>Pihla</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Vuosi valokeilassa: Kuka sai medialta huomiota? Kuka jäi varjoon? Suomen kuvalehti selvitti tutkijoiden kanssa, miten kansanedustajat näkyivät neljässä suuressa uutismediassa vuonna 2020</article-title>
      <source>Suomen Kuvalehti</source>
      <publisher-name>Yhtyneet kuvalehdet</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2021-05-21">2021</year><month>05</month><day>21</day>
      <issn>0039-5552</issn>
      <fpage>24</fpage>
      <lpage>33</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
