<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Suppdata: Downloading Supplementary Data from Published Manuscripts</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>William D Pearse</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-6241-3164</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Scott A Chamberlain</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-1444-9135</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>supplementary materials</tag>
      <tag>supplemental information</tag>
      <tag>open data</tag>
      <tag>meta-analysis</tag>
      <tag>DOI</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>2 May 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00721</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropensci/suppdata</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1238947</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00721/10.21105.joss.00721.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><code>suppdata</code> is an R <span class="citation" data-cites="R2018">(R Core Team 2018)</span> package to provide easy, reproducible access to supplemental materials within R. Thus <code>suppdata</code> facilitates open, reproducible research workflows: scientists re-analyzing published datasets can work with them as easily as if they were stored on their own computer, and others can track their analysis workflow painlessly.</p>
    <p>For example, imagine you were conducting an analysis of the evolution of body mass in mammals. Without <code>suppdata</code>, such an analysis would require manually downloading body mass and phylogenetic data from published manuscripts. This is time-consuming, difficult (if not impossible) to make truly reproducible without re-distributing the data, and hard to follow. With <code>suppdata</code>, such an analysis is straightforward, reproducible, and the sources of the data <span class="citation" data-cites="Fritz2009">(S. A. Fritz, Bininda-Emonds, and Purvis 2009, <span class="citation" data-cites="Jones2009">Jones et al. (2009)</span>)</span> are clear because their DOIs are embedded within the code:</p>
    <pre class="{r}"><code># Load phylogenetics packages
    library(ape)
    library(caper)
    library(phytools)
    
    # Load suppdata
    library(suppdata)
    
    # Load two published datasets
    tree &lt;- read.nexus(suppdata(&quot;10.1111/j.1461-0248.2009.01307.x&quot;, 1))[[1]]
    traits &lt;- read.delim(suppdata(
            &quot;E090-184&quot;, &quot;PanTHERIA_1-0_WR05_Aug2008.txt&quot;,
            &quot;esa_archives&quot;))
    
    # Merge datasets
    traits &lt;- with(traits, data.frame(body.mass = log10(X5.1_AdultBodyMass_g),
                           species=gsub(&quot; &quot;,&quot;_&quot;,MSW05_Binomial)))
    c.data &lt;- comparative.data(tree, traits, species)
    
    # Calculate phylogenetic signal
    phylosig(c.data$phy, c.data$data$body.mass)</code></pre>
    <p>The above example makes use of code from the packages <code>ape</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="Paradis2004">(Paradis, Claude, and Strimmer 2004)</span>, <code>caper</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="Orme2013">(D. Orme et al. 2013)</span>, and <code>phytools</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="Revell2012">(Revell 2012)</span>.</p>
    <p>As <code>suppdata</code> was, originally, part of <code>fulltext</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="Chamberlain2018">(Chamberlain 2018)</span>, it is already being used in a number of research projects. One such project is <code>natdb</code>, a package that builds a database of functional traits from published sources. The software is currently available on GitHub (https://github.com/willpearse/suppdata), and we plan to distribute it through ROpenSci and CRAN.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Chamberlain2018">
    <p>Chamberlain, Scott. 2018. <em>Fulltext: Full Text of ’Scholarly’ Articles Across Many Data Sources</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=fulltext" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=fulltext</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Fritz2009">
    <p>Fritz, Susanne A, Olaf RP Bininda-Emonds, and Andy Purvis. 2009. “Geographical Variation in Predictors of Mammalian Extinction Risk: Big Is Bad, but Only in the Tropics.” <em>Ecology Letters</em> 12 (6):538–49.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Jones2009">
    <p>Jones, Kate E, Jon Bielby, Marcel Cardillo, Susanne A Fritz, Justin O’Dell, C David L Orme, Kamran Safi, et al. 2009. “PanTHERIA: A Species-Level Database of Life History, Ecology, and Geography of Extant and Recently Extinct Mammals: Ecological Archives E090-184.” <em>Ecology</em> 90 (9):2648–8.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Orme2013">
    <p>Orme, David, Rob Freckleton, Gavin Thomas, Thomas Petzoldt, Susanne Fritz, Nick Isaac, and William D Pearse. 2013. <em>Caper: Comparative Analyses of Phylogenetics and Evolution in R</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=caper" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=caper</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Paradis2004">
    <p>Paradis, E., J. Claude, and K. Strimmer. 2004. “APE: Analyses of Phylogenetics and Evolution in R Language.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 20:289–90.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R2018">
    <p>R Core Team. 2018. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Revell2012">
    <p>Revell, Liam J. 2012. “Phytools: An R Package for Phylogenetic Comparative Biology (and Other Things).” <em>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</em> 3 (2):217–23.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
