<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>0cfd32963b0d3f4bc1c34a2f70edf08c</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20210718070954</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>07</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>6</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>63</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>Traja: A Python toolbox for animal trajectory analysis</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Justin</given_name>
            <surname>Shenk</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0664-7337</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Wolf</given_name>
            <surname>Byttner</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9525-9730</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Saranraj</given_name>
            <surname>Nambusubramaniyan</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7314-0261</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Alexander</given_name>
            <surname>Zoeller</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4043-3420</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>07</month>
          <day>18</day>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>3202</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.03202</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5069231”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/3202</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.03202</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03202</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03202.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <unstructured_citation>Trajectory Data Mining: An Overview, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/trajectory-data-mining-an-overview/, ACM Transaction on Intelligent Systems and Technology, Zheng, Yu, 2015, Type: Journal Article</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <unstructured_citation>Gillies, Sean and others, toblerity.org, Shapely: manipulation and analysis of geometric objects, 2007–, https://github.com/Toblerity/Shapely</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <unstructured_citation>The package adehabitat for the R software: tool for the analysis of space and habitat use by animals, Ecological Modelling, 197, 1035, 2006, Calenge, C.</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <doi>10.1021/ac60214a047</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <doi>10.1038/s41598-018-32949-3</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <doi>10.1007/s10182-017-0302-7</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <unstructured_citation>Cambridge, MA, USA, Adaptive Computation and Machine Learning, Gaussian Processes for Machine Learning, Biologische Kybernetik, Rasmussen, CE. and Williams, CKI., jan, 2006, Backup Publisher: Max-Planck-Gesellschaft, 1</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <unstructured_citation>Gaussian Process Regression for Trajectory Analysis, Cognitive scientists have begun collecting the trajectories of hand movements as participants make decisions in experiments. These response trajectories offer a ﬁne-grained glimpse into ongoing cognitive processes. For example, difﬁcult decisions show more hesitation and deﬂection from the optimal path than easy decisions. However, many summary statistics used for trajectories throw away much information, or are correlated and thus partially redundant. To alleviate these issues, we introduce Gaussian process regression for the purpose of modeling trajectory data collected in psychology experiments. Gaussian processes are a well-developed statistical model that can ﬁnd parametric differences in trajectories and their derivatives (e.g., velocity and acceleration) rather than a summary statistic. We show how Gaussian process regression can be implemented hierarchically across conditions and subjects, and used to model the actual shape and covariance of the trajectories. Finally, we demonstrate how to construct a generative hierarchical Bayesian model of trajectories using Gaussian processes., en, Cox, Gregory E and Kachergis, George and Shiffrin, Richard M, 2012, 6</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <doi>10.1007/BF00379695</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <unstructured_citation>Modeling Trajectory as Image: Convolutional Neural Networks for Multi-scale Taxi Trajectory Prediction, Modeling Trajectory as Image, https://www.academia.edu/34767293/Modeling_Trajectory_as_Image_Convolutional_Neural_Networks_for_Multi-scale_Taxi_Trajectory_Prediction, Precise destination prediction of Taxi trajectories can benefit both efficient schedule of taxies and accurate advertisement for customers.In this paper, we propose T-CONV, a novel trajectory prediction algorithm, which models trajectories as, en, 2019-11-23, Wang, Xintong, 2017</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <doi>10.1553/giscience2019_01_s54</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <unstructured_citation>Distributed Representations of Words and Phrases and their Compositionality, Mikolov, Tomas and Sutskever, Ilya and Chen, Kai and Corrado, Greg and Dean, Jeffrey, 2013, 1310.4546, arXiv, cs.CL</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <doi>10.1214/aoms/1177703732</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <doi>10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2003.06.004</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <doi>10.1007/s10651-006-0015-7</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref16">
            <doi>10.5281/zenodo.4521178</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref17">
            <doi>10.1101/770271</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref18">
            <doi>10.5281/zenodo.1134016</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref19">
            <doi>10.1371/journal.pone.0235750</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref20">
            <doi>10.1038/s41593-018-0209-y</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref21">
            <unstructured_citation>PyTorch: An Imperative Style, High-Performance Deep Learning Library, Paszke, Adam and Gross, Sam and Massa, Francisco and Lerer, Adam and Bradbury, James and Chanan, Gregory and Killeen, Trevor and Lin, Zeming and Gimelshein, Natalia and Antiga, Luca and Desmaison, Alban and Kopf, Andreas and Yang, Edward and DeVito, Zachary and Raison, Martin and Tejani, Alykhan and Chilamkurthy, Sasank and Steiner, Benoit and Fang, Lu and Bai, Junjie and Chintala, Soumith, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 32, Wallach, H. and Larochelle, H. and Beygelzimer, A. and d’ Alché-Buc, F. and Fox, E. and Garnett, R., 8024–8035, 2019, Curran Associates, Inc., http://papers.neurips.cc/paper/9015-pytorch-an-imperative-style-high-performance-deep-learning-library.pdf</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref22">
            <doi>10.1109/cvprw.2019.00358</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref23">
            <doi>10.1109/cvprw.2019.00359</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref24">
            <doi>10.1016/j.cognition.2015.12.015</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref25">
            <doi>10.1037/xhp0000198</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref26">
            <doi>10.1007/s00265-015-1948-3</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref27">
            <doi>10.1002/ecy.2379</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref28">
            <doi>10.1371/journal.pone.0185968</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref29">
            <doi>10.1037/0096-1523.29.2.326</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref30">
            <doi>10.1371/journal.pone.0058464</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref31">
            <doi>10.1109/TVCG.2009.182</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref32">
            <doi>10.1101/2020.09.14.295808</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref33">
            <doi>10.1111/eth.12739</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref34">
            <doi>10.1016/S0031-9384(01)00530-3</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref35">
            <doi>10.1109/seaa.2018.00018</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref36">
            <doi>10.25080/Majora-92bf1922-00a</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref37">
            <doi>10.1037/0096-1523.16.4.755</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref38">
            <doi>10.5281/zenodo.3509134</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref39">
            <doi>10.1186/s40462-019-0177-1</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref40">
            <doi>10.1046/j.1365-2656.1999.00279.x</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref41">
            <doi>10.1007/978-3-540-74553-2_44</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref42">
            <doi>10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref43">
            <doi>10.21105/joss.03021</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref44">
            <doi>10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref45">
            <doi>10.1111/j.2041-210X.2012.00197.x</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref46">
            <unstructured_citation>New York, Information Science and Statistics, Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning, 978-0-387-31073-2, https://www.springer.com/de/book/9780387310732, The dramatic growth in practical applications for machine learning over the last ten years has been accompanied by many important developments in the underlying algorithms and techniques. For example, Bayesian methods have grown from a specialist niche to become mainstream, while graphical models have emerged as a general framework for describing and applying probabilistic techniques. The practical applicability of Bayesian methods has been greatly enhanced by the development of a range of approximate inference algorithms such as variational Bayes and expectation propagation, while new models based on kernels have had a significant impact on both algorithms and applications. This completely new textbook reflects these recent developments while providing a comprehensive introduction to the fields of pattern recognition and machine learning. It is aimed at advanced undergraduates or first-year PhD students, as well as researchers and practitioners. No previous knowledge of pattern recognition or machine learning concepts is assumed. Familiarity with multivariate calculus and basic linear algebra is required, and some experience in the use of probabilities would be helpful though not essential as the book includes a self-contained introduction to basic probability theory. The book is suitable for courses on machine learning, statistics, computer science, signal processing, computer vision, data mining, and bioinformatics. Extensive support is provided for course instructors, including more than 400 exercises, graded according to difficulty. Example solutions for a subset of the exercises are available from the book web site, while solutions for the remainder can be obtained by instructors from the publisher. The book is supported by a great deal of additional material, and the reader is encouraged to visit the book web site for the latest information. Christopher M. Bishop is Deputy Director of Microsoft Research Cambridge, and holds a Chair in Computer Science at the University of Edinburgh. He is a Fellow of Darwin College Cambridge, a Fellow of the Royal Academy of Engineering, and a Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh. His previous textbook “Neural Networks for Pattern Recognition” has been widely adopted. Coming soon: <em>For students, worked solutions to a subset of exercises available on a public web site (for exercises marked “www” in the text) </em>For instructors, worked solutions to remaining exercises from the Springer web site <em>Lecture slides to accompany each chapter </em>Data sets available for download, en, 2020-06-28, Springer-Verlag, Bishop, Christopher, 2006</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref47">
            <doi>10.4018/978-1-7998-5101-1.ch001</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref48">
            <doi>10.3389/fnins.2020.00518</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref49">
            <unstructured_citation>Beijing, Data Science from Scratch: First Principles with Python, 978-1-4919-0142-7, http://my.safaribooksonline.com/97814919-01427, Data science libraries, frameworks, modules, and toolkits are great for doing data science, but they’re also a good way to dive into the discipline without actually understanding data science. In this book, you’ll learn how many of the most fundamental data science tools and algorithms work by implementing them from scratch. If you have an aptitude for mathematics and some programming skills, author Joel Grus will help you get comfortable with the math and statistics at the core of data science, and with hacking skills you need to get started as a data scientist., O’Reilly, Grus, Joel, 2015, 01624 103 safari book ai software development data pattern recognition analysis python</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref50">
            <doi>10.1109/cvpr.2019.00868</doi>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
