<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>EFAshiny: An User-Friendly Shiny Application for Exploratory Factor Analysis</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Chi-Lin Yu</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4381-7163</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Ching-Fan Sheu</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-5978-5768</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Exploratory Factor Analysis (EFA)</tag>
      <tag>Data Management</tag>
      <tag>Data Visualization</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>Shiny</tag>
      <tag>ggplot2</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>8 February 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00567</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/PsyChiLin/EFAshiny</software_repository>
    <software_archive></software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00567/10.21105.joss.00567.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><code>EFAshiny</code> is a user-friendly web application for exploratory factor analysis (EFA) <span class="citation" data-cites="efa">(David J. Bartholomew 2011)</span>. The motivation to create <code>EFAshiny</code> is to streamline the routine work flow of EFA so that users unfamiliar with R can perform the analysis interactively in a web browser.</p>
    <p>Employing the graphical user interface (GUI) of <code>shiny</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="shiny">(Chang et al. 2017)</span> framework (Figure 1), <code>EFAshiny</code> provides an integrated platform to perform EFA with a drop-down menu, offering a number of choices to manage, explore, analyze and visualize data. <code>EFAshiny</code> automates these processes by wrappings together several <code>R</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="r">(Team 2000)</span> packages, such as <code>ggplot2</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="ggplot2">(Wickham 2016)</span>, <code>psych</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="psych">(Revelle 2017)</span>, <code>psycho</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="psycho">(Makowski 2018)</span>, and <code>EGA</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="EGA">(Golino and Epskamp 2017)</span>, etc. For example, users can point-and-click to obtain graphical display of confidence intervals for factor loadings, which is not available in many commercial software. Moreover, results of analysis are presented on-line as tables and graphs and they can be saved and exported by the user.</p>
    <p>Key features of <code>EFAshiny</code> include:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>An easy-to-use GUI to free users from scripting in R</li>
    <li>A step by step analysis flow to perform EFA</li>
    <li>Quick ways to summarize data by tables or graphs</li>
    <li>Several ways to explore factor retention numerically or graphically</li>
    <li>Several ways to explore factor extraction and rotation numerically or graphically</li>
    <li>A display of confidence intervals for factor loadings</li>
    <li>Several ways to link visualization of correlation matrix with factor structure</li>
    <li>Default options are chosen according to recommendations in the literature <span class="citation" data-cites="efaguide">(Henson and Roberts 2006)</span></li>
    <li>A demonstration using a real psychological scale dataset</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Although the <code>EFAshiny</code> application is primarily aimed at behavioral researchers who want to perform EFA on a set of associated variables (e.g., item-level scale dataset), it can also be used to explore FA-based connectivity analyses <span class="citation" data-cites="mclaughlin1992potential">(McLaughlin et al. 1992)</span> in instrument data, such as event related potentials (ERPs) and functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS).</p>
    <p>In conclusion, <code>EFAshiny</code> allows researchers to harness the combined power of many R packages together for performing interactive EFA and obtaining numerical and graphical results in a user-friendly menu-driven GUI. Documentation, tutorials and usages can be found on <a href="https://github.com/PsyChiLin/EFAshiny"><strong>our page</strong></a>.</p>
    <h1 id="references">References</h1>
    <figure>
    <img src="Introduction.png" alt="The GUI of EFAshiny" /><figcaption>The GUI of <code>EFAshiny</code></figcaption>
    </figure>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-shiny">
    <p>Chang, Winston, Joe Cheng, JJ Allaire, Yihui Xie, and Jonathan McPherson. 2017. <em>Shiny: Web Application Framework for R</em>. <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/shiny/" class="uri">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/shiny/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-efa">
    <p>David J. Bartholomew, Irini Moustaki, Martin Knott. 2011. <em>Latent Variable Models and Factor Analysis: A Unified Approach</em>. New Jersey.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-EGA">
    <p>Golino, Hudson F, and Sacha Epskamp. 2017. “Exploratory Graph Analysis: A New Approach for Estimating the Number of Dimensions in Psychological Research.” <em>PLOS ONE</em> 12 (6). Public Library of Science:1–26. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0174035" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0174035</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-efaguide">
    <p>Henson, Robin K., and J. Kyle Roberts. 2006. “Use of Exploratory Factor Analysis in Published Research: Common Errors and Some Comment on Improved Practice.” <em>Educational and Psychological Measurement</em> 66 (3):393–416. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0013164405282485" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1177/0013164405282485</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-psycho">
    <p>Makowski, Dominique. 2018. “The Psycho Package: An Efficient and Publishing-Oriented Workflow for Psychological Science.” <em>Journal of Open Source Software</em> 3 (22):470. <a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00470" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00470</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-mclaughlin1992potential">
    <p>McLaughlin, Thomas, Bruce Steinberg, Birger Christensen, Ian Law, Agnete Parving, and Lars Friberg. 1992. “Potential Language and Attentional Networks Revealed Through Factor Analysis of rCBF Data Measured with Spect.” <em>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &amp; Metabolism</em> 12 (4):535–45. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/jcbfm.1992.77" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/jcbfm.1992.77</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-psych">
    <p>Revelle, William. 2017. <em>Psych: Procedures for Psychological, Psychometric, and Personality Research</em>. <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/psych/" class="uri">https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/psych/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-r">
    <p>Team, R Core. 2000. “R Language Definition.” <em>Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing</em>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-ggplot2">
    <p>Wickham, Hadley. 2016. <em>Ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</em>. <em>Springer</em>. New York.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
