<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>CheSweet: An application to predict glycan’s chemicals shifts</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Pablo G Garay</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-6604-0329</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Jorge A Vila</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Osvaldo A Martin</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-7419-8978</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>glycans</tag>
      <tag>chemical shifts</tag>
      <tag>python</tag>
      <tag>carbohydrates</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>1 December 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00488</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/BIOS-IMASL/chesweet</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1157129</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00488/10.21105.joss.00488.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Glycans are the most abundant and structurally diverse biomolecules in nature. The knowledge of the tridimensional structure of these molecules is necessary to understand in detail, at atomic level, the molecular processes in which they are involved. Chemical shifts (CS) are observables obtained from Nuclear Magnetic Resonance experiments and are highly sensitive probes to sense conformational changes (<span class="citation" data-cites="Swalina2001">Swalina et al. (2001)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="Martin2012">Martin, Vila, and Scheraga (2012)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="Garay2016">Garay et al. (2016)</span>). Here we present CheSweet a Python module to compute CS for glycans. The core of CheSweet is the fast calculation of CS, based on the pre-calculated values of CS at DFT level of theory, from the values of the torsional angles (<span class="math inline"><em>ϕ</em></span>, <span class="math inline"><em>ψ</em></span>, <span class="math inline"><em>ω</em></span> and <span class="math inline"><em>χ</em></span>, depending on its availability) of the glycosidic bond (<span class="citation" data-cites="Garay2014">Garay et al. (2014)</span>). This calculation of CS is done through a linear interpolation (based on the existence of 4 points, two for <span class="math inline"><em>ϕ</em></span> and two for <span class="math inline"><em>ψ</em></span>), or by nearest neighbor interpolation if there is less information available. Is possible to have less than 4 values because the lookup table, from were CheSweet do the interpolation, have been constructed from low-energy conformations of disaccharides, thus not all <span class="math inline"><em>ϕ</em></span>-<span class="math inline"><em>ψ</em></span> pairs exist. If the number of dihedral angles is less than 4 (3, 2 or 1) is not possible to do a linear interpolation, in such a case, CheSweet returns the CS value of the nearest neighbor. If all the torsional values in the lookup table are at a distance larger than 10<span class="math inline"><em></em><sup>∘</sup></span>, from the provided torsionals, it is considered that there are no neighbors, then CheSweet returns  (positive infinite). In a similar fashion CheSweet can be used to solve the inverse problem, i.e. to compute a set of torsional angles compatible with the provided CS values, from the carbons of the glycosidic bond. CheSweet has the potential to be used as part of more complex methods to predict, validate and refine glycan’s structures.</p>
    <h1 id="funding">Funding</h1>
    <p>This research was supported by CONICET-Argentina (PIP-0087) and ANPCyT-Argentina (PICT-0556, PICT-0767, PICT-0218).</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Garay2014">
    <p>Garay, Pablo G., Osvaldo A. Martin, Harold A. Scheraga, and Jorge A. Vila. 2014. “Factors affecting the computation of the &lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt; C shielding in disaccharides.” <em>Journal of Computational Chemistry</em> 35 (25):1854–64. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/jcc.23697" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1002/jcc.23697</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Garay2016">
    <p>———. 2016. “Detection of methylation, acetylation and glycosylation of protein residues by monitoring 13 C chemical-shift changes: A quantum-chemical study.” <em>PeerJ</em> 4 (July). PeerJ Inc.:e2253. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.2253" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.2253</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Martin2012">
    <p>Martin, Osvaldo A., Jorge A. Vila, and Harold A. Scheraga. 2012. “CheShift-2: graphic validation of protein structures.” <em>Bioinformatics (Oxford, England)</em> 28 (11):1538–9. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bts179" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bts179</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Swalina2001">
    <p>Swalina, C. W., R. J. Zauhar, M. J. DeGrazia, and Guillermo Moyna. 2001. “Derivation of 13C chemical shift surfaces for the anomeric carbons of oligosaccharides and glycopeptides using ab initio methodology.” <em>Journal of Biomolecular NMR</em> 21 (1):49–61. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1011928919734" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1011928919734</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
