<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>0bae6d76505f5caa37029504982cca06</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20191117211538</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>http://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>4</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>37</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>UralicNLP: An NLP Library for Uralic Languages</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Mika</given_name>
            <surname>Hämäläinen</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9315-1278</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>05</month>
          <day>09</day>
          <year>2019</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>1345</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.01345</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.2668061</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/1345</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.01345</doi>
          <resource>http://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.01345</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.01345/10.21105.joss.01345.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <unstructured_citation>Hämäläinen, Mika and Rueter, Jack, Advances in Synchronized XML-MediaWiki Dictionary Development in the Context of Endangered Uralic Languages, Proceedings of the Eighteenth EURALEX International Congress, 967-978, 2018</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <unstructured_citation>Beesley, Kenneth R. and Karttunen, Lauri, Finite-State Morphology, Stanford, CA: CSLI Publications, 451–454, 2003</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <unstructured_citation>Hämäläinen, Mika, Extracting a Semantic Database with Syntactic Relations for Finnish to Boost Resources for Endangered Uralic Languages, Proceedings of the Logic and Engineering of Natural Language Semantics 15 (LENLS15), 2018, https://helda.helsinki.fi/handle/10138/282733</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <unstructured_citation>Harnessing NLG to Create Finnish Poetry Automatically, Hämäläinen, Mika, Proceedings of the Ninth International Conference on Computational Creativity, 9-15, 2018</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <unstructured_citation>Bick, Eckhard and Didriksen, Tino, GrammarSoft ApS, Denmark, Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics, NODALIDA 2015, May 11-13, 2015, Vilnius, Lithuania, 109, 31-39, Linköping University Electronic Press, Linköpings universitet, CG-3 — Beyond Classical Constraint Grammar, 2015, 1650-3740, , This paper discusses methodological strengths and shortcomings of the Constraint Grammar paradigm (CG), showing how the classical CG formalism can be extended to achieve greater expressive power and how it can be enhanced and hybridized with techniques from other parsing paradigms. We present a new, largely theory-independent CG framework and rule compiler (CG-3), that allows the linguist to write CG rules incorporating different types of linguistic information and methodology from a wide range of parsing approaches, covering not only CG’s native topological technique, but also dependency grammar, phrase structure grammar and unification grammar. In addition, we allow the integration of statistical-numerical constraints and non-discrete tag and string sets.</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <unstructured_citation>Moshagen, Sjur N. and Pirinen, Tommi A. and Trosterud, Trond, University of Tromsø, Norway, Proceedings of the 19th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics (NODALIDA 2013); May 22-24; 2013; Oslo University; Norway. NEALT Proceedings Series 16, 85, 343-352, Linköping University Electronic Press, Building an open-source development infrastructure for language technology projects, 2013, 1650-3740,  Multilinguality, The article presents the Giellatekno &amp; Divvun language technology resources; more specifically the effort to utilise open-source tools to improve the build infrastructure; and the solutions to help adapt to best practices for software development. The article especially discusses how the infrastructure has been remade to cope with an increasing number of languages without incurring extra overhead for the maintainers; and at the same time let the linguists concentrate on the linguistic work. Finally; the article discusses how a uniform infrastructure like the one presented can be used to easily compare languages in terms of morphological or computational complexity; coverage or for cross-lingual applications.</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <unstructured_citation>Constraint Grammar: a language-independent system for parsing unrestricted text, Karlsson, Fred and Voutilainen, Atro and Heikkilä, Juha and Anttila, Arto, 4, 1995, Natural Language Processing, Berlin &amp; New York, Walter de Gruyter</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.1007/978-3-642-40486-3_4</doi>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
