<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>ENASearch: A Python library for interacting with ENA's API</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Bérénice Batut</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-9852-1987</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Björn Grüning</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3079-6586</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>European Nucleotide Archive</tag>
      <tag>Python</tag>
      <tag>API</tag>
      <tag>REST</tag>
      <tag>Galaxy</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>11 September 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00418</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/bebatut/enasearch</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1034619</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00418/10.21105.joss.00418.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>The European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) <span class="citation">(Leinonen et al. 2010)</span> is a database with a comprehensive record of nucleotide sequencing information (raw sequencing data, sequence assembly information and functional annotation). The data contained in ENA can be accessed manually or programmatically via REST URLs. However, building HTTP-based REST requests is not always straightforward - a user friendly, high-level access is needed to make it easier to interact with ENA programmatically.</p>
    <p>We developed ENASearch, a Python library to search and retrieve data from ENA database. It also allows for rich querying support by accessing different fields, filters or functions offered by ENA. ENASearch can be used as a Python package, through a command-line interface or inside Galaxy <span class="citation">(Afgan et al. 2016)</span>.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-afgan2016galaxy">
    <p>Afgan, Enis, Dannon Baker, Marius Van den Beek, Daniel Blankenberg, Dave Bouvier, Martin Čech, John Chilton, et al. 2016. “The Galaxy Platform for Accessible, Reproducible and Collaborative Biomedical Analyses: 2016 Update.” <em>Nucleic Acids Research</em> 44 (W1). Oxford University Press: W3–W10.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-leinonen2010european">
    <p>Leinonen, Rasko, Ruth Akhtar, Ewan Birney, Lawrence Bower, Ana Cerdeno-Tárraga, Ying Cheng, Iain Cleland, et al. 2010. “The European Nucleotide Archive.” <em>Nucleic Acids Research</em> 39 (suppl_1). Oxford University Press: D28–D31.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
