<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>visdat: Visualising Whole Data Frames</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Nicholas Tierney</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-1460-8722</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>visualisation</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>exporatory data analysis</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>01 August 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00355</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropensci/visdat</software_repository>
    <software_archive></software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/raw/master/joss.00355/10.21105.joss.00355.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>When you receive a new dataset you need to look at the data to get a sense of what is in it, and understand potential problems and challenges to get it analysis-ready. &quot;Taking a look at the data&quot; can mean different things. For example: examining statistical summaries (minimum, maximum, mean, inter-quartile range), finding missing values, checking data formatting, creating graphical summaries such as histograms, scatter plots, box plots, and more.</p>
    <p>When handling typical real-world data, these preliminary exploratory steps can become difficult to perform when values are not what you expect. For example, income might be a factor instead of numeric, date could be a number not a character string or a date class, or values could be missing when they shouldn't be. Often times, you discover that you had expectations of the data, which are hard to realise until they are a problem. This is similar to how one might not think to buy more light bulbs until one goes out: when you use data in an exploratory scatter plot, or a preliminary model, you often don't realise your data is in the wrong format until that moment. What is needed is a birds eye view of the data, which tells you what classes are in the dataframe, and where the missing data are.</p>
    <p><code>visdat</code> is an R <span class="citation">(R Core Team 2016)</span> package that provides a tool to &quot;get a look at the data&quot; by creating heatmap-like visualisations of an entire dataframe, which provides information on: classes in the data, missing values, and also comparisons between two datasets. <code>visdat</code> takes inspiration from <a href="https://github.com/setosa/csv-fingerprint"><code>csv-fingerprint</code></a>, and is powered by ggplot2 <span class="citation">(Wickham, Chang, and RStudio 2016)</span>, which provides a consistent, powerful framework for visualisations that can be extended if needed.</p>
    <p>Plots are presented in an intuitive way, reading top down, just like your data. Below is a plot using <code>vis_dat()</code> of some typical data containing missing values and data of a variety of classes.</p>
    <div class="sourceCode"><pre class="sourceCode r"><code class="sourceCode r"><span class="kw">library</span>(visdat)
    <span class="kw">vis_dat</span>(typical_data)</code></pre></div>
    <p><img src="paper_files/figure-html/load-data-1.png" /><!-- --></p>
    <p><code>visdat</code> will continue to be improved over time, to improve speed in computation and improve interactive plotting.</p>
    <h1 id="acknowlegements">Acknowlegements</h1>
    <p>I would like to thank the two reviewers, Mara Averick and Sean Hughes, for their helpful suggestions that resulted in a much better package, and rOpenSci for providing the support of the onboarding package review that facilitated these improvements.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Rcore">
    <p>R Core Team. 2016. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-ggplot2">
    <p>Wickham, Hadley, Winston Chang, and RStudio. 2016. <em>Ggplot2: An Implementation of the Grammar of Graphics</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggplot2" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggplot2</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
