<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Scowl: a Scala DSL for programming with the OWL API</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>James P Balhoff</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-8688-6599</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            RTI International
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>OWL</tag>
      <tag>ontology</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>17 May 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00023</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/phenoscape/scowl</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.51556</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00023/10.21105.joss.00023.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Scowl is a domain-specific language (DSL) which provides a convenient Scala-based syntax for composing OWL (Web Ontology Language, <span class="citation">(W3C OWL Working Group 2009)</span>) expressions and axioms. Effective use of complex, community developed ontologies within research applications, such as those from the OBO library (Open Biomedical Ontologies, <span class="citation">(Smith et al. 2007)</span>), often requires custom programmatic manipulation of ontologies and data, along with input to and output from automated reasoners. Allowing deeply nested OWL constructs to be coded in a readable, declarative style, Scowl facilitates use cases at the interface of application programming and OWL modeling: 1) tabular data ingest and transformation into OWL; 2) ontology manipulation via programmatic generation of axioms from existing content; and 3) reporting on ontology content using pattern matching on OWL objects.</p>
    <p>Within Scala applications, Scowl adds extension methods to native Java OWL API objects <span class="citation">(“The OWL API,” n.d.)</span>, supporting two syntax styles: the pseudo-English Manchester syntax <span class="citation">(Horridge and Patel-Schneider 2009)</span>, as well as the OWL Functional syntax <span class="citation">(Motik et al. 2009)</span>. Integration with the standard Java OWL API provides compatibility with multiple freely available OWL reasoners.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Horridge2009">
    <p>Horridge, Matthew, and Peter F Patel-Schneider. 2009. “OWL 2 Web Ontology Language Manchester Syntax.” <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-manchester-syntax/" class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-manchester-syntax/</a>. <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-manchester-syntax/" class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-manchester-syntax/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Motik2009">
    <p>Motik, Boris, Peter F Patel-Schneider, Bijan Parsia, Conrad Bock, Achille Fokoue, Peter Haase, Rinke Hoekstra, Ian Horrocks, Alan Ruttenberg, and Uli Sattler. 2009. “OWL 2 Web Ontology Language: Structural Specification and Functional-Style Syntax.” <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-syntax/" class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-syntax/</a>. <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-syntax/" class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-syntax/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Smith2007">
    <p>Smith, Barry, Michael Ashburner, Cornelius Rosse, Jonathan Bard, William Bug, Werner Ceusters, Louis J Goldberg, et al. 2007. “The OBO Foundry: Coordinated Evolution of Ontologies to Support Biomedical Data Integration.” <em>Nature Biotechnology</em> 25 (11): 1251–5. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt1346">10.1038/nbt1346</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-OWLAPI">
    <p>“The OWL API.” n.d. <a href="http://owlapi.sourceforge.net/" class="uri">http://owlapi.sourceforge.net/</a>. <a href="http://owlapi.sourceforge.net/" class="uri">http://owlapi.sourceforge.net/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-OWL2009">
    <p>W3C OWL Working Group. 2009. “OWL 2 Web Ontology Language Document Overview.” <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/" class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/</a>. <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/" class="uri">https://www.w3.org/TR/owl2-overview/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
