<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-publishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>Journal of Open Source Software</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title>JOSS</abbrev-journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn publication-format="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Open Journals</publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3839</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.03839</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sepia, a taxonomy oriented read classifier in
Rust</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-4086-1580</contrib-id>
<string-name>Henk C. den Bakker</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1"><sup>*</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-2533-9161</contrib-id>
<string-name>Lee S. Katz</string-name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Center for Food Safety, University of Georgia, Griffin, GA,
USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
<aff id="aff-2">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>Enteric Diseases Laboratory Branch (EDLB), Centers for
Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, USA</institution>
</institution-wrap>
</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">* E-mail: <email></email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>68</issue>
<fpage>3839</fpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the
work under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC
BY 4.0)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>The article authors</copyright-holder>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
<license-p>Authors of papers retain copyright and release the work under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC BY
4.0)</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>read classification</kwd>
<kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="summary">
  <title>Summary</title>
  <p>Here we present Sepia, a fast and accurate read classifier. It is
  implemented in Rust, has the ability to switch between different
  taxonomies, can detect inconsistencies in taxonomies, and can estimate
  similarities between organisms in a query dataset and reference
  sequences in the index.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="statement-of-need">
  <title>Statement of need</title>
  <p>Bioinformatics tools to infer the taxonomic composition of sets of
  biological sequences are quintessential for taxonomic profiling and
  contamination checking. A variety of tools have been developed to
  accomplish taxonomic profiling and these tools can be roughly
  classified into two categories: (i) read alignment based tools such as
  MIDAS
  (<xref alt="Nayfach et al., 2016" rid="ref-nayfach2016integrated" ref-type="bibr">Nayfach
  et al., 2016</xref>) and MetaPhlan
  (<xref alt="Segata et al., 2012" rid="ref-segata2012metagenomic" ref-type="bibr">Segata
  et al., 2012</xref>) , which map reads against a database of reference
  sequences or taxon specific marker sequences, and (ii) read
  classification based tools, such as Kraken
  (<xref alt="Wood &amp; Salzberg, 2014" rid="ref-wood2014kraken" ref-type="bibr">Wood
  &amp; Salzberg, 2014</xref>), Kraken2
  (<xref alt="Wood et al., 2019" rid="ref-wood2019improved" ref-type="bibr">Wood
  et al., 2019</xref>) and Centrifuge
  (<xref alt="Kim et al., 2016" rid="ref-kim2016centrifuge" ref-type="bibr">Kim
  et al., 2016</xref>). Many read classifiers use a least common
  ancestor (LCA) approach where reads in common among sibling taxa get
  assigned to the rank and taxonomy in common with those taxa; e.g., a
  kmer in common with both Escherichia and Salmonella, both members of
  the family Enterobacteriaceae, would be elevated to be associated in a
  database with the higher order taxon Enterobacteriaceae instead. While
  all these tools heavily rely on taxonomies, changing the taxonomies
  (e.g., correcting wrong placements of accessions or adapting a novel
  taxonomy) is not easily done. In response, we wrote Sepia, a taxonomic
  read classifier to address rapidly changing developments in taxonomy
  (e.g., the genome-based GTDB taxonomy
  (<xref alt="Parks et al., 2018" rid="ref-parks2018standardized" ref-type="bibr">Parks
  et al., 2018</xref>)) and algorithm development. There are three areas
  where Sepia directly addresses issues needing improvement: (i)
  taxonomy, (ii) classification accuracy, and (iii) the ability to
  perform fast batch classification for multiple datasets.</p>
  <sec id="taxonomy">
    <title>Taxonomy</title>
    <p>Taxonomic read classifiers that use an LCA approach work on the
    assumption that biological taxonomies reflect evolutionary
    relationships, thus making it possible to use taxonomies as a
    predictive framework in read classification. Inclusion of artificial
    taxa that are not supported by a genome-based phylogeny (e.g.,
    garbage bin taxa or taxa with an unknown placement ‘incertae sedis’)
    or artifactual errors (e.g., a genus placed erroneously in the wrong
    family in some of but not all of the accessions in the taxonomy)
    have a deleterious effect on the accuracy LCA based classification
    algorithms, potentially leading to some taxa not being classified at
    all or consistently classified as the wrong taxon. To address these
    issues Sepia uses human-readable taxonomy strings as input. While
    building the index putative ambiguities or inconsistencies in the
    taxonomy are flagged and logged to a file for the user to
    address.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sequence-similarity-and-classification-accuracy">
    <title>Sequence similarity and classification accuracy</title>
    <p>Read classifiers tend to miss- or overclassify reads, especially
    in situations where a lot of reads represent a taxon that is not
    present in the indexed reference dataset. To address this issue
    Sepia records the per read k-mer ratio, which is the ratio of k-mers
    supporting the proposed classification versus the total number of
    k-mers used for the classification. The average k-mer ratio highly
    correlates to the Average Nucleotide Identity (ANI) between
    reference strains in an index and strains in a query dataset (Figure
    1), and low k-mer ratios can be used to remove over- or
    misclassified reads after classification.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="batch-classification">
    <title>Batch classification</title>
    <p>While the process of taxonomic read classification is usually
    fast, the time needed to load a large index into RAM (e.g., 47,894
    accessions for reference sequences of GTDB rs202 requires a minimum
    of 98 Gb of RAM) can take longer than the actual classification
    process. When used repeatedly on a batch of sequence datasets, this
    can make the use of a read classifier time prohibitive. To overcome
    this time expensive hurdle, a batch classify function is included in
    Sepia; a user generated file containing sequence datasets for
    multiple samples is used as input, the index is read only once into
    RAM and subsequently the sequence data for the individual samples
    are classified.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="figures">
  <title>Figures</title>
  <fig>
    <caption><p>Correlation of Average Nucleotide Identity (ANI) as
    inferred by fastANI with minimizer-based estimation of k-mer
    similarity (p-value: &lt;&lt; 0.001, Multiple R-squared:
    0.96)</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="kmer_similarity_vs_fastANI.png" xlink:title="" />
  </fig>
</sec>
<sec id="implementation">
  <title>Implementation</title>
  <p>Sepia is written in the Rust programming language. The k-mer or
  minimizer index is an implementation of the compact hash table
  described by
  (<xref alt="Wood et al., 2019" rid="ref-wood2019improved" ref-type="bibr">Wood
  et al., 2019</xref>). Briefly, this hash table consists of a fixed
  array of 32 bits hash cells to store key-value pairs with a generic
  hash function (i.e., murmurHash3
  (<xref alt="Appleby, 2011" rid="ref-appleby2011murmurhash3" ref-type="bibr">Appleby,
  2011</xref>) in Kraken 2 and Sepia) and a load factor of 70% for
  collision resolution, thus needing considerably more space than
  key-value pairs. Alternatively, the user can choose to use an
  experimental index with a perfect hash function
  (<xref alt="Limasset et al., 2017" rid="ref-limasset2017fast" ref-type="bibr">Limasset
  et al., 2017</xref>) as implemented in Rust
  (https://github.com/10XGenomics/rust-boomphf). A perfect hash function
  maps a set of actual key values to the table without any collisions,
  thereby potentially decreasing the space requirement of the hash table
  compared to the compact hash table of Kraken 2. Next, taxonomy
  information is encoded into unsigned 32 values such that higher order
  taxa always have a lower value than lower order taxa, allowing for
  rapid set operations to infer LCAs for a set k-mers or minimizers
  within a single read or read pair. There is no limit to the number of
  taxonomic levels in a taxonomy string. This allows for the user to
  combine different taxonomies for different taxonomic domains (e.g.,
  NCBI viral taxonomy combined with GTDB taxonomy for Archaea and
  Bacteria). The unsigned 32 encoded taxonomy is compactly stored in a
  directed acyclic graph, the direction being from child to ancestral
  node. This allows for a rapid look-up of lineages and generation of
  sets for LCA inference. Upon completion Sepia produces two files; (i)
  a file with the per read or read pair classification, and (ii) a
  summary file, reporting the read count per taxon, the average k-mer
  ratio and the total length of all reads classified as a specific
  taxon. Using simulated and real datasets we found Sepia to be very
  similar in performance to Kraken 2; We found not significant
  differences in sensitivity and specificity of read classifications,
  however, we found Kraken 2 to be between 30% and 15% faster for
  Illumina short read datasets (HiSeq 125bp paired-end and MiSeq 300bp
  paired-end, respectively), however Sepia and Kraken 2 classified reads
  at a similar speed for an Oxford Nanopore dataset (NCBI SRA accession
  SRR15372305).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="acknowledgements">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>Financial support for the development of Sepia was provided by the
  Center for Food Safety at the University of Georgia, USA. The findings
  and conclusions in this report are those of the authors and do not
  necessarily represent the official position of the Centers for Disease
  Control and Prevention.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
  <ref-list>
    <ref id="ref-wood2019improved">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>Derrick E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>Ben</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Improved metagenomic analysis with kraken 2</article-title>
        <source>Genome biology</source>
        <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
        <volume>20</volume>
        <issue>1</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-wood2014kraken">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>Derrick E</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>Steven L</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Kraken: Ultrafast metagenomic sequence classification using exact alignments</article-title>
        <source>Genome biology</source>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
        <volume>15</volume>
        <issue>3</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-kim2016centrifuge">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Daehwan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Breitwieser</surname><given-names>Florian P</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>Steven L</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Centrifuge: Rapid and sensitive classification of metagenomic sequences</article-title>
        <source>Genome research</source>
        <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Lab</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <issue>12</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-limasset2017fast">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Limasset</surname><given-names>Antoine</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rizk</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chikhi</surname><given-names>Rayan</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Peterlongo</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Fast and scalable minimal perfect hashing for massive key sets</article-title>
        <source>arXiv preprint arXiv:1702.03154</source>
        <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-parks2018standardized">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>Donovan H</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chuvochina</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>David W</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rinke</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Skarshewski</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Chaumeil</surname><given-names>Pierre-Alain</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>A standardized bacterial taxonomy based on genome phylogeny substantially revises the tree of life</article-title>
        <source>Nature biotechnology</source>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
        <volume>36</volume>
        <issue>10</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-appleby2011murmurhash3">
      <element-citation>
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>MurmurHash3 hash function</article-title>
        <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-nayfach2016integrated">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Nayfach</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Rodriguez-Mueller</surname><given-names>Beltran</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Garud</surname><given-names>Nandita</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>Katherine S</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>An integrated metagenomics pipeline for strain profiling reveals novel patterns of bacterial transmission and biogeography</article-title>
        <source>Genome research</source>
        <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Lab</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year>
        <volume>26</volume>
        <issue>11</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
    <ref id="ref-segata2012metagenomic">
      <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
        <person-group person-group-type="author">
          <name><surname>Segata</surname><given-names>Nicola</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>Levi</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Ballarini</surname><given-names>Annalisa</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>Vagheesh</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Jousson</surname><given-names>Olivier</given-names></name>
          <name><surname>Huttenhower</surname><given-names>Curtis</given-names></name>
        </person-group>
        <article-title>Metagenomic microbial community profiling using unique clade-specific marker genes</article-title>
        <source>Nature methods</source>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
        <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
        <volume>9</volume>
        <issue>8</issue>
      </element-citation>
    </ref>
  </ref-list>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>
