<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>PyTransport: A Python package for the calculation of inflationary correlation functions</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>David J. Mulryne</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>John W. Ronayne</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-6464-6466</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Inflation</tag>
      <tag>Cosmology</tag>
      <tag>Early Universe</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>23 November 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00494</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/jronayne/PyTransport</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1209239</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00494/10.21105.joss.00494.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><img src="PyTransLogo-1.png" /> PyTransport constitutes a straightforward code written in C++ together with Python scripts which automatically edit, compile and run the C++ code as a Python module. It has been written for Unix-like systems (OS X and Linux). The transport method we utilise means only coupled differential equations need to be solved, and the implementation presented here combines the speed of C++ with the functionality and convenience of Python.</p>
    <p>The code is intended to be a reusable resource for inflationary cosmology. It enables users to quickly create a complied Python module(s) for any given model(s) of multi-field inflation. Primarily the module employs the transport approach to inflationary cosmology to calculate the tree-level power-spectrum and bispectrum of user specified models of multi-field inflation, accounting for all sub and super-horizon effects. To this end, the module contains a number functions that can be called from Python and that perform tasks such as calculating the background evolution of the cosmology, as well as the evolution of the two and three point functions. We also provide a number of further functions written in Python that perform common tasks such as calculating the power spectrum or bispectrum over a range of scales by utilising the compiled module. The true power of the approach, however, is that users can rapidly write their own scripts, or adapt ours, to suit their own needs.</p>
    <p>The transport approach to inflationary perturbation theory that the code employs can be seen as the differential version of the integral expressions of the In-In formalism. It is helpful numerically because it provides a set of ordinary differential equations for the correlation functions of inflationary perturbations. The code solves these equations from deep inside the horizon until some desired time after horizon crossing using a standard variable step size ordinary differential equation (ODE) routine with error control. Such off the shelf routines are extremely well tested, and provide an easy way to change the required accuracy. This is helpful in order to check convergence of the numerical solutions, or to respond to needs of models with very fine features. Details of the transport method itself that the code is based on can be found in the recent paper <span class="citation" data-cites="Dias">(Dias et al. 2016)</span> <span class="citation" data-cites="Ronayne">(Ronayne and Mulryne 2017)</span>. We highly recommend reading this guide in combination with that paper.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Dias">
    <p>Dias, Mafalda, Jonathan Frazer, David Mulryne, and David Seery. 2016. “Numerical Evaluation of the Bispectrum in Multiple Field Inflation - the Transport Approach with Code.”</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Ronayne">
    <p>Ronayne, John, and David Mulryne. 2017. “Numerically Evaluating the Bispectrum in Curved Field-Space – with Pytransport 2.0.”</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
