<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>tidytext: Text Mining and Analysis Using Tidy Data Principles in R</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Julia Silge</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3671-836X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            Datassist
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>David Robinson</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-8466-088X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            Stack Overflow
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>text mining</tag>
      <tag>natural language processing</tag>
      <tag>tidy data</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>6 July 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00037</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/juliasilge/tidytext</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.56714</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00037/10.21105.joss.00037.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>The tidytext package <span class="citation">(Silge, Robinson, and Hester 2016)</span> is an R package <span class="citation">(R Core Team 2016)</span> for text mining using tidy data principles. As described by Hadley Wickham <span class="citation">(Wickham 2014)</span>, tidy data has a specific structure:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>each variable is a column</li>
    <li>each observation is a row</li>
    <li>each type of observational unit is a table</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Tidy data sets allow manipulation with a standard set of &quot;tidy&quot; tools, including popular packages such as dplyr <span class="citation">(Wickham, Francois, and RStudio 2015)</span>, ggplot2 <span class="citation">(Wickham, Chang, and RStudio 2016)</span>, and broom <span class="citation">(Robinson et al. 2015)</span>. These tools do not yet, however, have the infrastructure to work fluently with text data and natural language processing tools. In developing this package, we provide functions and supporting data sets to allow conversion of text to and from tidy formats, and to switch seamlessly between tidy tools and existing text mining packages.</p>
    <p>We define the tidy text format as being one-token-per-document-per-row, and provide functionality to tokenize by commonly used units of text including words, n-grams, and sentences. At the same time, the tidytext package doesn't expect a user to keep text data in a tidy form at all times during an analysis. The package includes functions to <code>tidy</code> objects (see the broom package <span class="citation">(Robinson et al. 2015)</span>) from popular text mining R packages such as tm <span class="citation">(Ingo Feinerer and Meyer 2008)</span> and quanteda <span class="citation">(Benoit and Nulty 2016)</span>. This allows, for example, a workflow with easy reading, filtering, and processing to be done using dplyr and other tidy tools, after which the data can be converted into a document-term matrix for machine learning applications. The models can then be re-converted into a tidy form for interpretation and visualization with ggplot2.</p>
    <p>The following is an example visualization made using tidytext's text mining and sentiment analysis tools.</p>
    <div class="figure">
    <img src="README-unnamed-chunk-9-1.png" alt="Sentiment in Jane Austen&#39;s Novels" />
    <p class="caption">Sentiment in Jane Austen's Novels</p>
    </div>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-R-quanteda">
    <p>Benoit, Kenneth, and Paul Nulty. 2016. <em>Quanteda: Quantitative Analysis of Textual Data</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=quanteda" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=quanteda</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-tm">
    <p>Ingo Feinerer, Kurt Hornik, and David Meyer. 2008. “Text Mining Infrastructure in R.” <em>Journal of Statistical Software</em> 25 (5): 1–54. <a href="http://www.jstatsoft.org/v25/i05/" class="uri">http://www.jstatsoft.org/v25/i05/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R-base">
    <p>R Core Team. 2016. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R-broom">
    <p>Robinson, David, Matthieu Gomez, Boris Demeshev, Dieter Menne, Benjamin Nutter, Luke Johnston, Ben Bolker, Francois Briatte, and Hadley Wickham. 2015. <em>Broom: Convert Statistical Analysis Objects into Tidy Data Frames</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=broom" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=broom</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-tidytext-archive">
    <p>Silge, Julia, David Robinson, and Jim Hester. 2016. “Tidytext: Text Mining Using Dplyr, Ggplot2, and Other Tidy Tools.” doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.56714">10.5281/zenodo.56714</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-tidydata">
    <p>Wickham, Hadley. 2014. “Tidy Data.” <em>Journal of Statistical Software</em> 59 (1): 1–23. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v059.i10">10.18637/jss.v059.i10</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R-ggplot2">
    <p>Wickham, Hadley, Winston Chang, and RStudio. 2016. <em>Ggplot2: An Implementation of the Grammar of Graphics</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggplot2" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=ggplot2</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R-dplyr">
    <p>Wickham, Hadley, Romain Francois, and RStudio. 2015. <em>Dplyr: A Grammar of Data Manipulation</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=dplyr" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=dplyr</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
