<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>ezknitr: Avoid the Typical Working Directory Pain When Using 'knitr'</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Dean Attali</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-5645-3493</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            UBC
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>reproducible research</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>7 August 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00075</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropenscilabs/ezknitr</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3545363</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00075/10.21105.joss.00075.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>'knitr' <span class="citation">(Xie 2014)</span> is a popular R package <span class="citation">(R Core Team 2016)</span> that implements the concept of literate programming <span class="citation">(Knuth 1984)</span> in R. It has been widely adopted in the R community as a means of generating dynamic reports. Despite its popularity, one common source of frustration with 'knitr' is that it makes important assumptions about the directory structure of the input files and does not offer much flexibility in deciding where the different output files are generated. The 'ezknitr' package <span class="citation">(Attali 2016)</span> is an R package that addresses these problems and enhances the functionality of 'knitr'. 'ezknitr' provides the user with complete control over where all the inputs and outputs are, and adds several other convenient features to make the process of generating dynamic documents more streamlined and efficient.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-ezknitr-archive">
    <p>Attali, Dean. 2016. “Ezknitr: Avoid the Typical Working Directory Pain When Using ’Knitr’.” doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3545363">10.6084/m9.figshare.3545363</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-knuth1984literate">
    <p>Knuth, Donald Ervin. 1984. “Literate Programming.” <em>The Computer Journal</em> 27 (2). Br Computer Soc: 97–111.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R-base">
    <p>R Core Team. 2016. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R-knitr">
    <p>Xie, Yihui. 2014. <em>Knitr: A General-Purpose Package for Dynamic Report Generation in R</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
