<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>a3e921c874b27413d79ccd5f34c9f028</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20220215121231</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2022</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>7</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>70</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>QXTools: A Julia framework for distributed quantum circuit simulation</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>John</given_name>
            <surname>Brennan</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4428-6798</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Lee</given_name>
            <surname>O’Riordan</surname>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Kenneth</given_name>
            <surname>Hanley</surname>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Myles</given_name>
            <surname>Doyle</surname>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Momme</given_name>
            <surname>Allalen</surname>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>David</given_name>
            <surname>Brayford</surname>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Luigi</given_name>
            <surname>Iapichino</surname>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Niall</given_name>
            <surname>Moran</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2619-5040</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>02</month>
          <day>15</day>
          <year>2022</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>3711</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.03711</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6089938”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/3711</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.03711</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03711</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03711.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <doi>10.1137/141000671</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <unstructured_citation>JuliaQX, 2021, GitHub, GitHub organization, https://github.com/JuliaQX</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <doi>10.22331/q-2020-10-11-341</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <unstructured_citation>Tensor Networks in a Nutshell, Biamonte, Jacob and Bergholm, Ville, 2017, 1708.00006, arXiv, quant-ph</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <doi>10.1088/1751-8121/aa6dc3</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <unstructured_citation>Tensor networks and graphical calculus for open quantum systems, Wood, Christopher J. and Biamonte, Jacob D. and Cory, David G., 2011, 1111.6950, arXiv, quant-ph</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <unstructured_citation>Villalonga, Benjamin and Lyakh, Dmitry and Boixo, Sergio and Neven, Hartmut and Humble, Travis S. and Biswas, Rupak and Rieffel, Eleanor G. and Ho, Alan and Mandrà, Salvatore, 1–11, Establishing the Quantum Supremacy Frontier with a 281 Pflop/s Simulation, http://arxiv.org/abs/1905.00444, 2019, arXiv, 1905.00444, quant-ph</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.1145/3173045</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <unstructured_citation>Tensor Network Circuit Simulation at Exascale, http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.09894, Tensor network methods are incredibly effective for simulating quantum circuits. This is due to their ability to efficiently represent and manipulate the wave-functions of large interacting quantum systems. We describe the challenges faced when scaling tensor network simulation approaches to Exascale compute platforms and introduce QuantEx, a framework for tensor network circuit simulation at Exascale., 2021-12-14, arXiv:2110.09894 [quant-ph], Brennan, John and Allalen, Momme and Brayford, David and Hanley, Kenneth and Iapichino, Luigi and O’Riordan, Lee J. and Doyle, Myles and Moran, Niall, oct, 2021, arXiv: 2110.09894, Quantum Physics, arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/PDGXHGPG/Brennan et al. - 2021 - Tensor Network Circuit Simulation at Exascale.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/QDJ7EDKT/2110.html:text/html, 10</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <unstructured_citation>Deploying Containerized QuantEx Quantum Simulation Software on HPC Systems, http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.05162, The simulation of quantum circuits using the tensor network method is very computationally demanding and requires significant High Performance Computing (HPC) resources to find an efficient contraction order and to perform the contraction of the large tensor networks. In addition, the researchers want a workflow that is easy to customize, reproduce and migrate to different HPC systems. In this paper, we discuss the issues associated with the deployment of the QuantEX quantum computing simulation software within containers on different HPC systems. Also, we compare the performance of the containerized software with the software running on bare metal., 2021-12-14, arXiv:2110.05162 [cs], Brayford, David and Brennan, John and Allalen, Momme and Hanley, Kenneth and Iapichino, Luigi and ORiordan, Lee and Moran, Niall, oct, 2021, arXiv: 2110.05162, Computer Science - Distributed, Parallel, and Cluster Computing, arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/3EWDFN2G/Brayford et al. - 2021 - Deploying Containerized QuantEx Quantum Simulation.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/5MVWSDFR/2110.html:text/html, 10</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <unstructured_citation>: A Package for Simulation, Tomography and Analysis of Quantum Computers, Torlai, Giacomo and Fishman, Matthew, 2020, https://github.com/GTorlai/PastaQ.jl/</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <doi>10.21105/joss.00819</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <unstructured_citation>Jet: Fast quantum circuit simulations with parallel task-based tensor-network contraction, Jet, http://arxiv.org/abs/2107.09793, We introduce a new open-source software library Jet, which uses task-based parallelism to obtain speed-ups in classical tensor-network simulations of quantum circuits. These speed-ups result from i) the increased parallelism introduced by mapping the tensor-network simulation to a task-based framework, ii) a novel method of reusing shared work between tensor-network contraction tasks, and iii) the concurrent contraction of tensor networks on all available hardware. We demonstrate the advantages of our method by benchmarking our code on several Sycamore-53 and Gaussian boson sampling (GBS) supremacy circuits against other simulators. We also provide and compare theoretical performance estimates for tensor-network simulations of Sycamore-53 and GBS supremacy circuits for the first time., 2021-12-14, arXiv:2107.09793 [quant-ph], Vincent, Trevor and O’Riordan, Lee J. and Andrenkov, Mikhail and Brown, Jack and Killoran, Nathan and Qi, Haoyu and Dhand, Ish, jul, 2021, arXiv: 2107.09793, 81P68, Quantum Physics, arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/SL3ZDHE9/Vincent et al. - 2021 - Jet Fast quantum circuit simulations with paralle.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/HICE3D5R/2107.html:text/html, 7</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <unstructured_citation>ExaTN - A Scalable Exascale Math Library for Hierarchical Tensor Network Representations and Simulations, 2019, https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019APS..MARB22012M, A problem that will benefit from exascale computing is predictive simulation of two- and three-dimensional quantum many-body Hamiltonians. Enabling efficient numerical simulations requires new insights into wavefunction compression that scales on extremely heterogeneous HPC architectures. To address this need, we develop ExaTN: a math library of parallel numerical primitives for processing operations based on hierarchical tensor representations. Our library provides a scalable infrastructure for building a performance portable framework for simulating strongly correlated quantum systems on heterogeneous HPC platforms such as Titan and Summit. Our framework is the first to deliver a massively parallel implementation of the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (MERA), a promising hierarchical tensor decomposition scheme capable of expressing local expectation values in strongly entangled quantum systems efficiently. In this talk, we will present our integrated framework for processing hierarchical tensor representations on exascale HPC systems via a multi-level asynchronous task-based programming model. This provides scientists with a capability for simulating strongly entangled systems in condensed matter physics. Laboratory Directed Research and Development Program ORNL., 2021-12-14, McCaskey, Alexander and Dumitrescu, Eugen and Liakh, Dmitry and Alvarez, Gonzalo and Mintz, Tiffany, jan, 2019, Conference Name: APS March Meeting Abstracts ADS Bibcode: 2019APS..MARB22012M, B22.012, 1</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <unstructured_citation>Efficient 2D Tensor Network Simulation of Quantum Systems, http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.15234, Simulation of quantum systems is challenging due to the exponential size of the state space. Tensor networks provide a systematically improvable approximation for quantum states. 2D tensor networks such as Projected Entangled Pair States (PEPS) are well-suited for key classes of physical systems and quantum circuits. However, direct contraction of PEPS networks has exponential cost, while approximate algorithms require computations with large tensors. We propose new scalable algorithms and software abstractions for PEPS-based methods, accelerating the bottleneck operation of contraction and refactorization of a tensor subnetwork. We employ randomized SVD with an implicit matrix to reduce cost and memory footprint asymptotically. Further, we develop a distributed-memory PEPS library and study accuracy and efficiency of alternative algorithms for PEPS contraction and evolution on the Stampede2 supercomputer. We also simulate a popular near-term quantum algorithm, the Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE), and benchmark Imaginary Time Evolution (ITE), which compute ground states of Hamiltonians., 2021-12-14, arXiv:2006.15234 [physics, physics:quant-ph], Pang, Yuchen and Hao, Tianyi and Dugad, Annika and Zhou, Yiqing and Solomonik, Edgar, sep, 2020, arXiv: 2006.15234, Computer Science - Distributed, Parallel, and Cluster Computing, Physics - Computational Physics, Quantum Physics, arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/VIHLM8IA/Pang et al. - 2020 - Efficient 2D Tensor Network Simulation of Quantum .pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/nmoran/Zotero/storage/KFYANKD7/2006.html:text/html, 9</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
