<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>fc6e7c2237348806455de31ffe3054f2</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20200608225041</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>5</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>50</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>FASMA 2.0: A Python package for stellar parameters and chemical abundances</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Maria</given_name>
            <surname>Tsantaki</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0552-2313</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Daniel</given_name>
            <surname>Andreasen</surname>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Guilherme</given_name>
            <surname>Teixeira</surname>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>06</month>
          <day>08</day>
          <year>2020</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>2048</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.02048</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3885291”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/2048</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.02048</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02048</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.02048/10.21105.joss.02048.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <doi>10.18727/0722-6691/5117</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <doi>10.1117/12.2055132</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201321844</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201629967</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201935465</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <doi>10.1051/aas:1996222</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201423945</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.1086/152374</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <unstructured_citation>Kurucz, R., ATLAS9 Stellar Atmosphere Programs and 2 km/s grid., ATLAS9 Stellar Atmosphere Programs and 2 km/s grid. Kurucz CD-ROM No. 13.  Cambridge, Mass.: Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory, 1993., 1993, 13, http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1993KurCD..13…..K, Provided by the SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361:200809724</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <doi>10.1093/mnras/stx2564</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201527120</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201425433</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <unstructured_citation>Markwardt, C. B., Non-linear Least-squares Fitting in IDL with MPFIT, Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics, Astronomical Data Analysis Software and Systems XVIII, 2009, Bohlender, D. A. and Durand, D. and Dowler, P., 411, Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series, 251, https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2009ASPC..411..251M, Provided by the SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <doi>10.1137/0111030</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref16">
            <doi>10.1088/0031-8949/90/5/054005</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref17">
            <unstructured_citation>Gilmore, G. and Randich, S. and Asplund, M. and Binney, J. and Bonifacio, P. and Drew, J. and Feltzing, S. and Ferguson, A. and Jeffries, R. and Micela, G. and Negueruela, I. and Prusti, T. and Rix, H. -W. and Vallenari, A. and Alfaro, E. and Allende-Prieto, C. and Babusiaux, C. and Bensby, T. and Blomme, R. and Bragaglia, A. and Flaccomio, E. and François, P. and Irwin, M. and Koposov, S. and Korn, A. and Lanzafame, A. and Pancino, E. and Paunzen, E. and Recio-Blanco, A. and Sacco, G. and Smiljanic, R. and Van Eck, S. and Walton, N. and Aden, D. and Aerts, C. and Affer, L. and Alcala, J. -M. and Altavilla, G. and Alves, J. and Antoja, T. and Arenou, F. and Argiroffi, C. and Asensio Ramos, A. and Bailer-Jones, C. and Balaguer-Nunez, L. and Bayo, A. and Barbuy, B. and Barisevicius, G. and Barrado y Navascues, D. and Battistini, C. and Bellas Velidis, I. and Bellazzini, M. and Belokurov, V. and Bergemann, M. and Bertelli, G. and Biazzo, K. and Bienayme, O. and Bland-Hawthorn, J. and Boeche, C. and Bonito, S. and Boudreault, S. and Bouvier, J. and Brandao, I. and Brown, A. and de Bruijne, J. and Burleigh, M. and Caballero, J. and Caffau, E. and Calura, F. and Capuzzo-Dolcetta, R. and Caramazza, M. and Carraro, G. and Casagrande, L. and Casewell, S. and Chapman, S. and Chiappini, C. and Chorniy, Y. and Christlieb, N. and Cignoni, M. and Cocozza, G. and Colless, M. and Collet, R. and Collins, M. and Correnti, M. and Covino, E. and Crnojevic, D. and Cropper, M. and Cunha, M. and Damiani, F. and David, M. and Delgado, A. and Duffau, S. and Edvardsson, B. and Eldridge, J. and Enke, H. and Eriksson, K. and Evans, N. W. and Eyer, L. and Famaey, B. and Fellhauer, M. and Ferreras, I. and Figueras, F. and Fiorentino, G. and Flynn, C. and Folha, D. and Franciosini, E. and Frasca, A. and Freeman, K. and Fremat, Y. and Friel, E. and Gaensicke, B. and Gameiro, J. and Garzon, F. and Geier, S. and Geisler, D. and Gerhard, O. and Gibson, B. and Gomboc, A. and Gomez, A. and Gonzalez-Fernandez, C. and Gonzalez Hernandez, J. and Gosset, E. and Grebel, E. and Greimel, R. and Groenewegen, M. and Grundahl, F. and Guarcello, M. and Gustafsson, B. and Hadrava, P. and Hatzidimitriou, D. and Hambly, N. and Hammersley, P. and Hansen, C. and Haywood, M. and Heber, U. and Heiter, U. and Held, E. and Helmi, A. and Hensler, G. and Herrero, A. and Hill, V. and Hodgkin, S. and Huelamo, N. and Huxor, A. and Ibata, R. and Jackson, R. and de Jong, R. and Jonker, P. and Jordan, S. and Jordi, C. and Jorissen, A. and Katz, D. and Kawata, D. and Keller, S. and Kharchenko, N. and Klement, R. and Klutsch, A. and Knude, J. and Koch, A. and Kochukhov, O. and Kontizas, M. and Koubsky, P. and Lallement, R. and de Laverny, P. and van Leeuwen, F. and Lemasle, B. and Lewis, G. and Lind, K. and Lindstrom, H. P. E. and Lobel, A. and Lopez Santiago, J. and Lucas, P. and Ludwig, H. and Lueftinger, T. and Magrini, L. and Maiz Apellaniz, J. and Maldonado, J. and Marconi, G. and Marino, A. and Martayan, C. and Martinez-Valpuesta, I. and Matijevic, G. and McMahon, R. and Messina, S. and Meyer, M. and Miglio, A. and Mikolaitis, S. and Minchev, I. and Minniti, D. and Moitinho, A. and Momany, Y. and Monaco, L. and Montalto, M. and Monteiro, M. J. and Monier, R. and Montes, D. and Mora, A. and Moraux, E. and Morel, T. and Mowlavi, N. and Mucciarelli, A. and Munari, U. and Napiwotzki, R. and Nardetto, N. and Naylor, T. and Naze, Y. and Nelemans, G. and Okamoto, S. and Ortolani, S. and Pace, G. and Palla, F. and Palous, J. and Parker, R. and Penarrubia, J. and Pillitteri, I. and Piotto, G. and Posbic, H. and Prisinzano, L. and Puzeras, E. and Quirrenbach, A. and Ragaini, S. and Read, J. and Read, M. and Reyle, C. and De Ridder, J. and Robichon, N. and Robin, A. and Roeser, S. and Romano, D. and Royer, F. and Ruchti, G. and Ruzicka, A. and Ryan, S. and Ryde, N. and Santos, N. and Sanz Forcada, J. and Sarro Baro, L. M. and Sbordone, L. and Schilbach, E. and Schmeja, S. and Schnurr, O. and Schoenrich, R. and Scholz, R. -D. and Seabroke, G. and Sharma, S. and De Silva, G. and Smith, M. and Solano, E. and Sordo, R. and Soubiran, C. and Sousa, S. and Spagna, A. and Steffen, M. and Steinmetz, M. and Stelzer, B. and Stempels, E. and Tabernero, H. and Tautvaisiene, G. and Thevenin, F. and Torra, J. and Tosi, M. and Tolstoy, E. and Turon, C. and Walker, M. and Wambsganss, J. and Worley, C. and Venn, K. and Vink, J. and Wyse, R. and Zaggia, S. and Zeilinger, W. and Zoccali, M. and Zorec, J. and Zucker, D. and Zwitter, T. and Gaia-ESO Survey Team, The Gaia-ESO Public Spectroscopic Survey, The Messenger, 2012, mar, 147, 25-31, https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2012Msngr.147…25G, Provided by the SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System, 3</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref18">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201322068</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref19">
            <doi>10.3847/1538-3881/aabc4f</doi>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
