<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Pyret: A Python package for analysis of neurophysiology data</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Benjamin Naecker</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-7525-1635</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Niru Maheswaranathan</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3946-4705</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Surya Ganguli</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2, 3
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Stephen Baccus</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            3
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>neuroscience</tag>
      <tag>sensory</tag>
      <tag>retina</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>01 Dec 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00137</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/baccuslab/pyret</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.232521</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00137/10.21105.joss.00137.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>The <em>pyret</em> package contains tools for analyzing neural electrophysiology data. It focuses on applications in sensory neuroscience, broadly construed as any experiment in which one would like to characterize neural responses to a sensory stimulus. Pyret contains methods for manipulating spike trains (e.g. binning and smoothing), pre-processing experimental stimuli (e.g. resampling), computing spike-triggered averages and ensembles <span class="citation">(Schwartz et al. 2006)</span>, estimating linear-nonlinear cascade models to predict neural responses to different stimuli <span class="citation">(Chichilnisky 2001)</span>, part of which follows the scikit-learn API <span class="citation">(Pedregosa et al. 2011)</span>, as well as a suite of visualization tools for all the above. We designed <em>pyret</em> to be simple, robust, and efficient with broad applicability across a range of sensory neuroscience analyses.</p>
    <p>Full API documentation and a short tutorial can be found at <a href="http://pyret.readthedocs.io/" class="uri">http://pyret.readthedocs.io/</a></p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-chichilnisky2001">
    <p>Chichilnisky, EJ. 2001. “A Simple White Noise Analysis of Neuronal Light Responses.” <em>Network: Computation in Neural Systems</em> 12 (2). Taylor &amp; Francis: 199–213.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-pedregosa2011">
    <p>Pedregosa, Fabian, Gaël Varoquaux, Alexandre Gramfort, Vincent Michel, Bertrand Thirion, Olivier Grisel, Mathieu Blondel, et al. 2011. “Scikit-Learn: Machine Learning in Python.” <em>Journal of Machine Learning Research</em> 12 (Oct): 2825–30.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-schwartz2006">
    <p>Schwartz, Odelia, Jonathan W Pillow, Nicole C Rust, and Eero P Simoncelli. 2006. “Spike-Triggered Neural Characterization.” <em>Journal of Vision</em> 6 (4). The Association for Research in Vision; Ophthalmology: 13–13.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
