<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>lawn: An R client for the Turf Javascript Library for Geospatial Analysis</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Scott Chamberlain</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-1444-9135</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Jeffrey W. Hollister</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-9254-9740</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>geospatial</tag>
      <tag>GeoJSON</tag>
      <tag>javascript</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>16 December 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00194</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropensci/lawn</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.345991</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00194/10.21105.joss.00194.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><code>lawn</code> is an R package to provide access to the geospatial analysis capabilities in the <code>Turf</code> javascript library <span class="citation">(R Core Team 2016; Herlocker 2016)</span>. <code>Turf</code> expects data in GeoJSON format. Given that many datasets are now available natively in GeoJSON providing an easier method for conducting geospatial analyses on these datasets in R is desired. Additionally, many existing packages (e.g. <code>sp</code> and <code>rgeos</code>) do provide similar analysis capabilities; however, they require data be converted to <code>sp</code> objects and also have external dependencies (e.g. <code>gdal</code> and <code>geos</code>) that can be challenging to maintain on some systems <span class="citation">(Roger S Bivand, Pebesma, and Gómez-Rubio 2013; Roger S. Bivand and Rundel 2016; GDAL Development Team 2015; Team 2016)</span>. To address these challenges and facilitate geospatial analysis of GeoJSON formatted data, we developed the <code>lawn</code> package.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-bivand2013asdar">
    <p>Bivand, Roger S, Edzer Pebesma, and Virgilio Gómez-Rubio. 2013. <em>Applied Spatial Data Analysis with R</em>. 2nd ed. Springer.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-rgeos">
    <p>Bivand, Roger S., and C. Rundel. 2016. <em>Rgeos: Interface to Geometry Engine - Open Source (Geos)</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rgeos" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=rgeos</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-gdal">
    <p>GDAL Development Team. 2015. <em>GDAL - Geospatial Data Abstraction Library, Version 1.11.3</em>. Open Source Geospatial Foundation. <a href="http://www.gdal.org" class="uri">http://www.gdal.org</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-turfjs">
    <p>Herlocker, Morgan. 2016. “Turf: Advanced Geospatial Analysis for Browsers and Node.” <a href="http://turfjs.org/" class="uri">http://turfjs.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-r">
    <p>R Core Team. 2016. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-geos">
    <p>Team, GEOS Development. 2016. <em>GEOS - Geometry Engine, Open Source</em>. Open Source Geospatial Foundation. <a href="https://trac.osgeo.org/geos/" class="uri">https://trac.osgeo.org/geos/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
