<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>gwdegree: Improving interpretation of geometrically-weighted degree estimates in exponential random graph models</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Michael A Levy</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4188-2527</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            University of California, Davis; Department of Environmental Science and Policy
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>social network analysis</tag>
      <tag>ERGM</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>05 July 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00036</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/michaellevy/gwdegree</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.57495</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00036/10.21105.joss.00036.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Exponential random graph models (ERGMs) are maximum entropy statistical models that provide estimates on network tie formation of variables both exogenous (covariate) and endogenous (structural) to a network. Network centralization -- the tendency for edges to accrue among a small number of popular nodes -- is a key network variable in many fields, and in ERGMs it is primarily modeled via the geometrically-weighted degree (GWD) statistic <span class="citation">(Snijders et al. 2006; Hunter 2007)</span>. However, the published literature is ambiguous about how to interpret GWD estimates, and there is little guidance on how to interpret or fix values of the GWD shape-parameter, <span class="math inline"><em>θ</em><sub><em>S</em></sub></span>. This Shiny application seeks to improve the use of GWD in ERGMs by demonstrating:</p>
    <ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
    <li><p>how the GWD statistic responds to adding edges to nodes of various degrees, contingent on the value of the shape parameter, <span class="math inline"><em>θ</em><sub><em>S</em></sub></span>;</p></li>
    <li><p>how the degree distribution of networks of various size and density are shaped by GWD parameter and <span class="math inline"><em>θ</em><sub><em>S</em></sub></span> values;</p></li>
    <li><p>how GWD and GWESP -- an ERGM term used to model triadic closure -- interact to affect network centralization and clustering.</p></li>
    </ol>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-hunter_curved_2007">
    <p>Hunter, David R. 2007. “Curved Exponential Family Models for Social Networks.” <em>Social Networks</em>, Special section: Advances in exponential random graph (p*) models, 29 (2): 216–30. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.005">10.1016/j.socnet.2006.08.005</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-snijders_new_2006">
    <p>Snijders, Tom A. B., Philippa E. Pattison, Garry L. Robins, and Mark S. Handcock. 2006. “New Specifications for Exponential Random Graph Models.” <em>Sociological Methodology</em> 36 (1): 99–153. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9531.2006.00176.x">10.1111/j.1467-9531.2006.00176.x</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
