<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>ivporbit:An R package to estimate the instrumental variables probit model</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Taha Zaghdoudi</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4488-5774</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>limited-dependent variable models</tag>
      <tag>Amemiya’s Generalized Least Squares estimators</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>ivprobit</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>13 December 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00523</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/zedtaha/ivprobit-1.0</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1183253</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00523/10.21105.joss.00523.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>ivprobit <span class="citation" data-cites="zaghdoudi">(Zaghdoudi 2017)</span> is an open source R package that fit the instrumental variables probit model. The package comprises function that deal with endogeneity misspecification especially when correlation between regressors and error term is determinited and which produce inconsistent results. To avoid this problem, authors applied the instrumental variable method in which they use the correlated variables as instruments. Nevertheless, a two-stage method are used by some authors <span class="citation" data-cites="blundell2004endogeneity">(Blundell and Powell 2004)</span> to fit the probit model but it produce non efficient result.</p>
    <p>However, <span class="citation" data-cites="newey1987efficient">(Newey 1987)</span> expose an efficient way to estimate limited-dependent variable model by using the Amemiya’s Generalized Least Squares estimators (AGLS) <span class="citation" data-cites="Amemiya1978">(Amemiya 1978)</span>. Likewise, in the ivprobit package we use the AGLS method and we include in the two-stage model a continuous endogenous regressor. This method is used when the maximum likelihood method (MLE) fail to estimate the model.</p>
    <p>ivprobit is GPL-3 licensed and can be retrieved from GitHub <a href="https://github.com/cran/ivprobit">Repository</a></p>
    <p><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ivprobit/index.html">ivprobit CRAN</a></p>
    <p><a href="https://zenodo.org/record/1183253#.Wo7IEYPOXIU">Archive</a></p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Amemiya1978">
    <p>Amemiya, Takeshi. 1978. “The Estimation of a Simultaneous Equation Generalized Probit Model.” <em>Econometrica: Journal of the Econometric Society</em> 46:1193–1205.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-blundell2004endogeneity">
    <p>Blundell, Richard W, and James L Powell. 2004. “Endogeneity in Semiparametric Binary Response Models.” <em>The Review of Economic Studies</em> 71 (3):655–79. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-937X.2004.00299.x" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-937X.2004.00299.x</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-newey1987efficient">
    <p>Newey, Whitney K. 1987. “Efficient Estimation of Limited Dependent Variable Models with Endogenous Explanatory Variables.” <em>Journal of Econometrics</em> 36 (3):231–50. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0304-4076(87)90001-7" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/0304-4076(87)90001-7</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-zaghdoudi">
    <p>Zaghdoudi, Taha. 2017. “Ivporbit: An R Package to Estimate the Instrumental Variables Probit Model.” 2017. <a href="https://github.com/zedtaha/ivprobit-1.0/" class="uri">https://github.com/zedtaha/ivprobit-1.0/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
