<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>iheatmapr: Interactive complex heatmaps in R</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Alicia N Schep</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3915-0618</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1,2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Sarah K Kummerfeld</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-0089-2358</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>visualization</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
      <tag>heatmap</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>2 March 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00359</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/ropensci/iheatmapr</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.841331</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/raw/master/joss.00359/10.21105.joss.00359.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>The iheatmapr package is an R package <span class="citation">(Team 2000)</span> for creating complex, interactive heatmaps. Heatmaps are commonly used to visualize patterns in high-dimensional data, particularly in genomics research. Adding annotations and summary plots along the rows or columns of a heatmap can enhance a heatmap visualization. Pairing several heatmaps horizontally can enable association of data across multiple assays. Adding interactive features like tooltips and zooming can further enhance these complex heatmaps, enabling information-rich visualizations linking diverse, high-dimensional data sets.</p>
    <p>There are great tools in R for creating simple interactive heatmaps <span class="citation">(Galili 2016, <span class="citation">Cheng and Galili (2016)</span>)</span> or creating static complex heatmaps <span class="citation">(Gu, Eils, and Schlesner 2016)</span>. However, there are no tools facilitating the creation of complex, interactive heatmaps. The iheatmapr package fills this gap, enabling creation of highly customizable, interactive, complex heatmaps using the plotly library <span class="citation">(Sievert et al. 2016)</span>. The resulting interactive visualizations can easily be incorporated into reproducible R Markdown reports for sharing with collaborators.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-d3heatmap">
    <p>Cheng, Joe, and Tal Galili. 2016. <em>D3heatmap: Interactive Heat Maps Using ’Htmlwidgets’ and ’D3.js’</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=d3heatmap" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=d3heatmap</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-heatmaply">
    <p>Galili, Tal. 2016. <em>Heatmaply: Interactive Heat Maps Using ’Plotly’</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=heatmaply" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=heatmaply</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-ComplexHeatmap">
    <p>Gu, Zuguang, Roland Eils, and Matthias Schlesner. 2016. “Complex Heatmaps Reveal Patterns and Correlations in Multidimensional Genomic Data.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 32 (18). Oxford Univ Press: 2847–9. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw313">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw313</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-plotly">
    <p>Sievert, Carson, Chris Parmer, Toby Hocking, Scott Chamberlain, Karthik Ram, Marianne Corvellec, and Pedro Despouy. 2016. <em>Plotly: Create Interactive Web Graphics via ’Plotly.js’</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=plotly" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=plotly</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-team2000r">
    <p>Team, R Core. 2000. “R Language Definition.” <em>Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing</em>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
