<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>chloroExtractor: extraction and assembly of the chloroplast genome from whole genome shotgun data</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Markus J Ankenbrand</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-6620-807X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1, a
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Simon Pfaff</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-8505-9439</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2, a
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Niklas Terhoeven</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2, 3
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Musga Qureischi</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-9661-8494</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            3, 4
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Maik Gündel</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-0502-4576</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            3
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Clemens L. Weiß</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            5
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Thomas Hackl</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-0022-320X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            6
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Frank Förster</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-4166-5423</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2, 3, 7
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>chloroplast</tag>
      <tag>genome</tag>
      <tag>assembly</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>28 September 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00464</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/chloroExtractorTeam/chloroExtractor</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1148955</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00464/10.21105.joss.00464.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>This is an automated pipeline that extracts and reconstructs chloroplast genomes from whole genome shotgun data. It is capable to assemble the incidentally sequenced chloropast DNA, which is present in almost all plant sequencing projects, due to the extraction of whole cellular DNA. It works by analyzing the k-mer distribution (determined with Jellyfish, <span class="citation" data-cites="marcais_fast_2011">(Marçais and Kingsford 2011)</span>, peak detection with R <span class="citation" data-cites="GnuR">(R Core Team 2008)</span>) of the raw sequencing reads. Usually the coverage of the chloroplast genome is much higher than that of the nuclear genome. Using mapping to reference chloroplast sequences (using bowtie2 <span class="citation" data-cites="bowtie2">(Langmead and Salzberg 2012)</span>, samtools <span class="citation" data-cites="Samtools">(“The Sequence Alignment/Map Format and Samtools” 2009)</span>, and bedtools <span class="citation" data-cites="Bedtools">(Quinland and Hall 2010)</span>) and the k-mer distribution candidate chloroplast reads are extracted from the complete set (Figure 1). Afterwards, the targeted assembly of those sequences is much faster and yields less contigs compared to an assembly of all reads. Assemblers usually fail to assemble chloroplast genomes as a single contig due to their structure, consisting of two single copy regions and an inverted repeat. The size of the inverted repeat is in most cases multiple kilobasepairs in size, therefore it can not be resolved using short reads only. However SPAdes <span class="citation" data-cites="Spades_2013">(Nurk et al. 2013)</span> returns the assembly graph where the typical chloroplast structure can be recognized and reconstructed using the knowledge of its structure. Using our demo set, one can achieve a single contig assembly of the chloroplast of <em>Spinacia oleracea</em> . If the assembly process does not finish with a single chloroplast sequence all remaining sequences are BLASTed <span class="citation" data-cites="blastPlus">(Camacho et al. 2009)</span> against a database of reference chloroplasts to retain all partial sequences of interest. The final chloroplast sequence can be further annotated with tools like DOGMA <span class="citation" data-cites="dogma2004">(Wyman, Jansen, and Boore 2004)</span>, cpGAVAS <span class="citation" data-cites="Liu2012">(Liu et al. 2012)</span> and VERDANT <span class="citation" data-cites="Mckain2017">(McKain et al. 2017)</span>. Such assemblies, can be used to remove chloroplast reads before a genomic assembly of the remaining nuclear DNA. Moreover, chloroplast genomes are useful in phylogenetic reconstruction <span class="citation" data-cites="huang_2016">(Huang et al. 2016)</span> or barcoding applications <span class="citation" data-cites="Coissac_2016">(Coissac et al. 2016)</span>. A similar tool, aiming the assembly of whole chloroplast genomes is the Python program <a href="https://git.metabarcoding.org/org-asm/org-asm">org.ASM</a>, but it is not production ready, yet. Also plasmid SPAdes <span class="citation" data-cites="plasmidspades_2016">(Antipov et al. 2016)</span> could possibly be used for this purpose although it is not intended for it. In the future, we plan to use our chloroExtractor to screen NCBI’s Sequence Read Archive <span class="citation" data-cites="sra2011">(Leinonen, Sugawara, and Shumway 2011)</span> for chloroplast genomes in public sequencing datasets that are not yet available in chloroplast databases, eg. chloroDB <span class="citation" data-cites="chlordb2006">(Cui et al. 2006)</span> to broaden our knowledge about chloroplasts.</p>
    <figure>
    <img src="workflow.png" alt="Schematic workflow of chloroExtractor." style="width:70.0%" /><figcaption>Schematic workflow of chloroExtractor.</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>In addition to the components cited above the chloroExtractor uses <a href="https://www.ghostscript.com/">Ghostscript</a>, <a href="https://www.python.org/">Phyton</a>, and <a href="https://www.perl.org/">Perl</a>. Further the following Perl modules are used: <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~ether/Moose-2.2009/lib/Moose.pm">Moose</a>, <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~mschilli/Log-Log4perl-1.49/lib/Log/Log4perl.pm">Log::Log4Perl</a>, <a href="http://search.cpan.org/dist/Graph/lib/Graph.pod">Graph</a>, <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~manwar/Term-ProgressBar-2.21/lib/Term/ProgressBar.pm">Term::ProgressBar</a>, <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~toddr/IPC-Run-0.96/lib/IPC/Run.pm">IPC::Run</a>, and <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~plicease/File-Which-1.22/lib/File/Which.pm">File::Which</a>.</p>
    <h1 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h1>
    <p>MJA was supported by a grant of the German Excellence Initiative to the Graduate School of Life Sciences, University of Würzburg. We thank Daniel Amsel for his help testing and solving the Mac-based issues with our docker container.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-plasmidspades_2016">
    <p>Antipov, Dmitry, Nolan Hartwick, Max Shen, Mikhail Raiko, Alla Lapidus, and Pavel Pevzner. 2016. “PlasmidSPAdes: Assembling Plasmids from Whole Genome Sequencing Data.” <em>bioRxiv</em>. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/048942" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1101/048942</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-blastPlus">
    <p>Camacho, Christiam, George Coulouris, Vahram Avagyan, Ning Ma, Jason Papadopoulos, Kevin Bealer, and Thomas L. Madden. 2009. “BLAST+: Architecture and Applications.” <em>BMC Bioinformatics</em> 10 (1). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-10-421" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Coissac_2016">
    <p>Coissac, Eric, Peter M. Hollingsworth, Sébastien Lavergne, and Pierre Taberlet. 2016. “From Barcodes to Genomes: Extending the Concept of Dna Barcoding.” <em>Molecular Ecology</em> 25 (7):1423–8. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.13549" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.13549</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-chlordb2006">
    <p>Cui, Liying, Narayanan Veeraraghavan, Alexander Richter, Kerr Wall, Robert K. Jansen, Jim Leebens-Mack, Izabela Makalowska, and Claude W. dePamphilis. 2006. “ChloroplastDB: The Chloroplast Genome Database.” <em>Nucleic Acids Research</em> 34:D692–D696. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkj055" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkj055</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-huang_2016">
    <p>Huang, Yuling, Xiaojuan Li, Zhenyan Yang, Chengjin Yang, Junbo Yang, and Yunheng Ji. 2016. “Analysis of Complete Chloroplast Genome Sequences Improves Phylogenetic Resolution in Paris (Melanthiaceae).” <em>Frontiers in Plant Science</em> 7:1797. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2016.01797" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2016.01797</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-bowtie2">
    <p>Langmead, Ben, and Steven L. Salzberg. 2012. “Fast Gapped-Read Alignment with Bowtie 2.” <em>Nature Methods</em> 9. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1923" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1923</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-sra2011">
    <p>Leinonen, Rasko, Hideaki Sugawara, and Martin Shumway. 2011. “The Sequence Read Archive.” <em>Nucleic Acids Research</em> 39:D19–D21. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq1019" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq1019</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Liu2012">
    <p>Liu, Chang, Linchun Shi, Yingjie Zhu, Haimei Chen, Jianhui Zhang, Xiaohan Lin, and Xiaojun Guan. 2012. “CpGAVAS, an Integrated Web Server for the Annotation, Visualization, Analysis, and Genbank Submission of Completely Sequenced Chloroplast Genome Sequences.” <em>BMC Genomics</em> 13 (1):715. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-13-715" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-13-715</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-marcais_fast_2011">
    <p>Marçais, Guillaume, and Carl Kingsford. 2011. “A Fast, Lock-Free Approach for Efficient Parallel Counting of Occurrences of K-Mers.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 27 (6):764–70. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btr011" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btr011</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Mckain2017">
    <p>McKain, Michael R., Ryan H. Hartsock, Molly M. Wohl, and Elizabeth A. Kellogg. 2017. “Verdant: Automated Annotation, Alignment and Phylogenetic Analysis of Whole Chloroplast Genomes.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 33 (1):130–32. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw583" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btw583</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Spades_2013">
    <p>Nurk, Sergey, Anton Bankevich, Dmitry Antipov, Alexey Gurevich, Anton Korobeynikov, Alla Lapidus, Andrey Prjibelsky, et al. 2013. “Assembling Genomes and Mini-Metagenomes from Highly Chimeric Reads.” In <em>Research in Computational Molecular Biology: 17th Annual International Conference, Recomb 2013, Beijing, China, April 7-10, 2013. Proceedings</em>, edited by Minghua Deng, Rui Jiang, Fengzhu Sun, and Xuegong Zhang, 158–70. Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer Berlin Heidelberg. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-37195-0_13" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-37195-0_13</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Bedtools">
    <p>Quinland, Aaron R., and Ira M. Hall. 2010. “BEDTools: A Flexible Suite of Utilities for Comparing Genomic Features.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 26 (1). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-GnuR">
    <p>R Core Team. 2008. “R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing.” Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Samtools">
    <p>“The Sequence Alignment/Map Format and Samtools.” 2009. <em>Bioinformatics</em> 25 (1). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-dogma2004">
    <p>Wyman, Stacia K., Robert K. Jansen, and Jeffrey L. Boore. 2004. “Automatic Annotation of Organellar Genomes with Dogma.” <em>Bioinformatics</em> 20 (17):3252–5. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bth352" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bth352</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
