<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>3bb171d89558e0ab3554b66143476de0</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20210813065329</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>08</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>6</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>64</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>WDPM: the Wetland DEM Ponding Model</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Kevin</given_name>
            <surname>Shook</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0363-9929</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Raymond</given_name>
            <surname>Spiteri</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3513-6237</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>John</given_name>
            <surname>Pomeroy</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4782-7457</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Tonghe</given_name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2714-3103</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Oluwaseun</given_name>
            <surname>Sharomi</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1368-5670</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>08</month>
          <day>13</day>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>2276</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.02276</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5165172”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/2276</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.02276</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02276</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02276.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <doi>10.1016/j.envsoft.2020.104850</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <unstructured_citation>USING THE WETLAND DEM PONDING MODEL AS A DIAGNOSTIC TOOL FOR PRAIRIE FLOOD HAZARD ASSESSMENT, Putting Prediction in Ungauged Basins into Practice, Armstrong, Robert and Kayter, Cameron and Shook, Kevin and Hill, Harvey, 2013, 255–270, /home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/NTA77NKG/Armstrong et al. - USING THE WETLAND DEM PONDING MODEL AS A DIAGNOSTI.pdf, en</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <doi>10.5194/esurf-7-737-2019</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <doi>10.1029/2020WR027984</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <doi>10.1007/s10669-018-9684-7</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <doi>10.1016/S0022-1694(98)00098-5</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <unstructured_citation>Predictive Mapping of Wetland Types and Associated Soils through Digital Elevation Model Analyses in the Canadian Prairie Pothole Region, Kiss, Jeremy, 2018, sep, https://harvest.usask.ca/handle/10388/11058, 2020-07-14, Effective management strategies are needed to control phosphorus loading of prairie watersheds that contribute to the eutrophication issues of Lake Winnipeg. Prairie Pothole Region (PPR) wetlands provide many ecosystems services including reducing nutrient mobility. Preferential conservation of PPR wetlands with calcium carbonate (CaCO3)-enriched soils may be a more effective strategy for controlling phosphorus loading, as these soils have greater potential to retain phosphorus from agricultural runoff. The spatial distribution of CaCO3-enriched wetland soils is controlled by hydrologic processes that may be modellable using high-resolution digital elevation models (DEMs). Two modelling approaches were tested to map spatial distributions of wetlands and wetland soils expected to be enriched with CaCO3. The models were trained and tested with wetland salinity and soil profile information collected at three Saskatchewan PPR sites, near Swift Current, St. Denis, and Smith Creek. The first model was developed to approximate landscape-scale hydrologic processes from high-resolution DEMs to predict the distributions of fresh and solute-rich wetlands; the solute-rich wetlands represent wetlands expected to have CaCO3-enriched soils. Spill channel connections between wetlands were modelled to characterize wetlands in terms of the runoff contributions they receive, their potential for contributing runoff downslope, and their relative position within the landscape; solute-richness predictions were based on these characteristics. This model was successful and achieved acceptable predictive accuracies based on external validation tests. Digital soil mapping (DSM) methodologies were tested for predicting the spatial distribution of wetland soil classes within PPR landscapes. Target soil classes were defined by hydropedological units that reflect differences in soil CaCO3 enrichment. Multiple machine-learning techniques were tested, which incorporated many topographic attributes derived from the DEMs as predictor variables, including knowledge-based topographic attributes developed specifically to characterize the PPR’s morphology. Certain DSM models achieved acceptable predictive accuracy based on external validation tests and mapped soils in expected distributions, but none predicted the occurrence of wetlands with CaCO3-enriched soils distributed throughout their basins. Both modelling approaches could potentially be used to 1) identify wetlands with CaCO3-enriched soils to target for conservation efforts to maximize phosphorus retention and 2) create upscaled estimates of phosphorus retention across the PPR., Accepted: 2018-09-25T17:39:31Z, /home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/CEIB4XDD/Kiss - 2018 - Predictive mapping of wetland types and associated.pdf;/home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/75NVPAHR/11058.html, en, University of Saskatchewan, Master’s Thesis, 9</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.1002/hyp.6787</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <unstructured_citation>Hydrology of the Delta Marsh Watershed: Water Balance Characterization and Analysis of Land Use Changes, Hydrology of the Delta Marsh Watershed, Schellenberg, Gregory John, 2017, dec, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada, https://mspace.lib.umanitoba.ca/xmlui/handle/1993/32779, 2020-07-14, A hydrological model was used to examine the water balance of the Delta Marsh Watershed (DMW) currently and as impacted by land use changes. Understanding DMW hydrology can help to improve conditions in the Delta Marsh. MIKE SHE model results showed that the water balance is typical of prairie conditions with limited wintertime activity, significant spring melt runoff, and high summertime evapotranspiration and infiltration. Results showed that the DMW contributes approximately 40 million m3 of water to the Delta Marsh in an average year, or 710 m3/ha/yr. Portage Creek is the single greatest inflow from the watershed (31% of total) and the West Marsh area also receives large runoff volumes (combined 37% of total). Analysis of land use changes showed that urban expansion in the DMW would increase annual marsh inflows by over 50% under one urbanization scenario due to associated decreases in infiltration and transpiration. An agricultural shift towards row crop predominance would have minimal impact on the DMW water balance. Conversion of cropland to natural vegetation would decrease annual runoff by 12% to the marsh due to increased surface ponding, infiltration, and transpiration., Accepted: 2018-01-10T17:22:16Z, /home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/Y7JIG4FQ/Schellenberg - 2017 - Hydrology of the Delta Marsh Watershed water bala.pdf;/home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/9CI56T9V/32779.html, University of Manitoba, MSc Thesis, 12</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <unstructured_citation>R.MAPCALC. An Algebra for GIS and Image Processing, Shapiro, Michael and Westervelt, Jim, 1992, 1–22, U.S. Army Construction Engineering Research Laboratory, Champaign, Illinois 61801, U.S.A., /home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/9RD6YKJE/Shapiro, Westervelt - 1992 - An Algebra for GIS and Image Processing.pdf</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <doi>10.1002/hyp.9409</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <doi>10.1002/hyp.8381</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <doi>10.1016/j.jhydrol.2020.125846</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <doi>10.1002/hyp.9867</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <doi>10.1016/S0022-1694(03)00175-6</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref16">
            <doi>10.3390/w11122486</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref17">
            <unstructured_citation>Climate Adaptation Using Natural Infrastructure Town of Virden &amp; the Rural Municipality of Wallace - Woodworth, Venema, Henry David, 2020, mar, 45, Strategic Community Consulting, www.strategiccc.ca, /home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/I3LZNL3X/Venema, Henry David - 2020 - Climate Adaptation Using Natural Infrastructure To.pdf, 3</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref18">
            <unstructured_citation>Flood Risk Mapping Study Rural Municipality of Springfield, Venema, Henry David, 2020, jun, 105, Strategic Community Consulting, www.strategiccc.ca, /home/kevin/data/zotero/storage/3K3UYQ3P/Springfield Flood Risk Mapping SCC Final Report.pdf, 6</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
