<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Mordecai: Full Text Geoparsing and Event Geocoding</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Andrew Halterman</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-9716-9555</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>geocoding</tag>
      <tag>geoparsing</tag>
      <tag>natural language processing</tag>
      <tag>Python</tag>
      <tag>word embeddings</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>8 December 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00091</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/openeventdata/mordecai</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.250879</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00091/10.21105.joss.00091.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Mordecai is a new full-text geoparsing system that extracts place names from text, resolves them to their correct entries in a gazetteer, and returns structured geographic information for the resolved place name. Geoparsing can be used in a number of tasks, including media monitoring, improved information extraction, document annotation for search, and geolocating text-derived event data, which is the task for which is was built. Mordecai was created to provide provide several features missing in existing geoparsers, including better handling of non-US place names, easy and portable setup and use though a Docker REST architecture, and easy customization with Python and swappable named entity recognition systems. Mordecai's key technical innovations are in a language-agnostic architecture that uses word2vec <span class="citation">(Mikolov et al. 2013)</span> for inferring the correct country for a set of locations in a piece of text and easily changed named entity recognition models. As a gazetteer, it uses Geonames <span class="citation">(Geonames 2016)</span> in a custom-build Elasticsearch database.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-geonames">
    <p>Geonames. 2016. “Geonames.” <a href="http://geonames.org" class="uri">http://geonames.org</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-mikolov2013efficient">
    <p>Mikolov, Tomas, Kai Chen, Greg Corrado, and Jeffrey Dean. 2013. “Efficient Estimation of Word Representations in Vector Space.” <em>ArXiv Preprint ArXiv:1301.3781</em>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
