<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>09bef6d3ac915063bea9bd3c9ac7df98</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20210820205835</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>08</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>6</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>64</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>The MarINvaders Toolkit</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Radek</given_name>
            <surname>Lonka</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5815-8682</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Francesca</given_name>
            <surname>Verones</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2908-328X</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Konstantin</given_name>
            <surname>Stadler</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1548-201X</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>08</month>
          <day>20</day>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>3575</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.03575</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4621392”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/3575</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.03575</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03575</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03575.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <unstructured_citation>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species, Established in 1964, the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species has evolved to become the world’s most comprehensive information source on the global conservation status of animal, fungi and plant species., https://www.iucnredlist.org/en, 2020, IUCN Red List of Threatened Species</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <unstructured_citation>OBIS: Ocean Biodiversity Information System - Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission of UNESCO., 2020, https://obis.org/</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <unstructured_citation>GISD: Global Invasive Species Database, 2021, http://www.iucngisd.org/gisd/</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <doi>10.3391/ai.2014.9.4.01</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <unstructured_citation>Ecosystems and Human Well-Being: Synthesis, Ecosystems and Human Well-Being, (Program), Millennium Ecosystem Assessment, MEA, 2005, Island Press, Washington, DC, OCLC: ocm59279709, 978-1-59726-040-4, Ecosystem management,Human ecology, en, GF50 .E269 2005</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <doi>10.1890/070064</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <doi>10.1038/ncomms14435</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.1111/gcb.15333</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <doi>10.1641/B570707</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <unstructured_citation>World Register of Marine Species (WoRMS), Horton, T. and Kroh, A. and Ahyong, S. and Bailly, N. and Boyko, C.B. and Brandão, S.N. and Gofas, S. and Hooper, J.N.A. and Hernandez, F. and Holovachov, O. and Mees, J. and Molodtsova, T.N. and Paulay, G. and Decock, W. and Dekeyzer, S. and Poffyn, G. and Vandepitte, L. and Vanhoorne, B. and Adlard, R. and Agatha, S. and Ahn, K.J. and Akkari, N. and Alvarez, B. and Anderberg, A. and Anderson, G. and Angel, M.V. and Antic, D. and Arango, C. and Artois, T. and Atkinson, S. and Auffenberg, K. and Baldwin, B.G. and Bank, R. and Barber, A. and Barbosa, J.P. and Bartsch, I. and Bellan-Santini, D. and Bergh, N. and Bernot, J. and Berta, A. and Bezerra, T.N. and Bieler, R. and Blanco, S. and Blasco-Costa, I. and Blazewicz, M. and Bock, P. and Bonifacino de León, M. and Böttger-Schnack, R. and Bouchet, P. and Boury-Esnault, N. and Boxshall, G. and Bray, R. and Bruce, N.L. and Cairns, S. and Calvo Casas, J. and Carballo, J.L. and Cárdenas, P. and Carstens, E. and Chan, B.K. and Chan, T.Y. and Cheng, L. and Christenhusz, M. and Churchill, M. and Coleman, C.O. and Collins, A.G. and Collins, G.E. and Corbari, L. and Cordeiro, R. and Cornils, A. and Coste, M. and Costello, M.J. and Crandall, K.A. and Cremonte, F. and Cribb, T. and Cutmore, S. and Dahdouh-Guebas, F. and Daly, M. and Daneliya, M. and Dauvin, J.C. and Davie, P. and De Broyer, C. and De Grave, S. and de Mazancourt, V. and de Voogd, N.J. and Decker, P. and Defaye, D. and d’Hondt, J.L. and Dippenaar, S. and Dohrmann, M. and Dolan, J. and Domning, D. and Downey, R. and Ector, L. and Eisendle, U. and Eitel, M. and Encarnação, S.C.d. and Enghoff, H. and Epler, J. and Ewers-Saucedo, C. and Faber, M. and Figueroa, D. and Finn, J. and Fišer, C. and Fordyce, E. and Foster, W. and Frank, J.H. and Fransen, C. and Freire, S. and Furuya, H. and Galea, H. and Gao, T. and Garcia-Alvarez, O. and Garcia-Jacas, N. and Garic, R. and Garnett, S. and Gasca, R. and Gaviria-Melo, S. and Gerken, S. and Gibson, D. and Gibson, R. and Gil, J. and Gittenberger, A. and Glasby, C. and Glover, A. and Gómez-Noguera, S.E. and González-Solís, D. and Gordon, D. and Gostel, M. and Grabowski, M. and Gravili, C. and Guerra-García, J.M.. and Guidetti, R. and Guiry, M.D. and Gutierrez, D. and Hadfield, K.A. and Hajdu, E. and Hallermann, J. and Hayward, B.W. and Heiden, G. and Hendrycks, E. and Herbert, D. and Herrera Bachiller, A. and Ho, J.s. and Hodda, M. and Høeg, J. and Hoeksema, B. and Houart, R. and Hughes, L. and Hyžný, M. and Iniesta, L.F.M. and Iseto, T. and Ivanenko, S. and Iwataki, M. and Janssen, R. and Jarms, G. and Jaume, D. and Jazdzewski, K. and Jersabek, C.D. and Jóźwiak, P. and Kabat, A. and Kantor, Y. and Karanovic, I. and Karthick, B. and Kathirithamby, J. and Katinas, L. and Kim, Y.H. and King, R. and Kirk, P.M. and Klautau, M. and Kociolek, J.P. and Köhler, F. and Kolb, J. and Konowalik, K. and Kotov, A. and Kremenetskaia, A. and Kristensen, R.M. and Kulikovskiy, M. and Kullander, S. and Kupriyanova, E. and Lambert, G. and Lazarus, D. and Le Coze, F. and LeCroy, S. and Leduc, D. and Lefkowitz, E.J. and Lemaitre, R. and Lichter-Marck, I.H. and Lindsay, D. and Liu, Y. and Loeuille, B. and Lörz, A.N. and Lowry, J. and Ludwig, T. and Lundholm, N. and Macpherson, E. and Madin, L. and Mah, C. and Mamo, B. and Mamos, T. and Manconi, R. and Mapstone, G. and Marek, P.E. and Marshall, B. and Marshall, D.J. and Martin, P. and Mast, R. and McFadden, C. and McInnes, S.J. and Meidla, T. and Meland, K. and Melo da Silva, D.C. and Merrin, K.L. and Messing, C. and Mills, C. and Moestrup, Ø. and Mokievsky, V. and Monniot, F. and Mooi, R. and Morandini, A.C. and Moreira da Rocha, R. and Morrow, C. and Mortelmans, J. and Mortimer, J. and Musco, L. and Nesom, G. and Neubauer, T.A. and Neubert, E. and Neuhaus, B. and Ng, P. and Nguyen, A.D. and Nielsen, C. and Nishikawa, T. and Norenburg, J. and O’Hara, T. and Opresko, D. and Osawa, M. and Osigus, H.J. and Ota, Y. and Páll-Gergely, B. and Panero, J.L. and Pasini, E. and Patterson, D. and Paxton, H. and Pelser, P. and Peña-Santiago, R. and Perrier, V. and Petrescu, I. and Pica, D. and Picton, B. and Pilger, J.F. and Pisera, A.B. and Polhemus, D. and Poore, G.C. and Potapova, M. and Pugh, P. and Read, G. and Reich, M. and Reimer, J.D. and Reip, H. and Reuscher, M. and Reynolds, J.W. and Richling, I. and Rimet, F. and Ríos, P. and Rius, M. and Rodríguez, E. and Rogers, D.C. and Roque, N. and Rosenberg, G. and Rützler, K. and Sabbe, K. and Saiz-Salinas, J. and Sala, S. and Santagata, S. and Santos, S. and Sar, E. and Satoh, A. and Saucède, T. and Schatz, H. and Schierwater, B. and Schilling, E. and Schmidt-Rhaesa, A. and Schneider, S. and Schönberg, C. and Schuchert, P. and Senna, A.R. and Sennikov, A. and Serejo, C. and Shaik, S. and Shamsi, S. and Sharma, J. and Shear, W.A. and Shenkar, N. and Shinn, A. and Short, M. and Sicinski, J. and Sierwald, P. and Simmons, E. and Sinniger, F. and Sivell, D. and Sket, B. and Smit, H. and Smit, N. and Smol, N. and Souza-Filho, J.F.. and Spelda, J. and Sterrer, W. and Stienen, E. and Stoev, P. and Stöhr, S. and Strand, M. and Suárez-Morales, E. and Summers, M. and Suppan, L. and Susanna, A. and Suttle, C. and Swalla, B.J. and Taiti, S. and Tanaka, M. and Tandberg, A.H. and Tang, D. and Tasker, M. and Taylor, J. and Taylor, J. and Tchesunov, A. and Temereva, E. and ten Hove, H. and ter Poorten, J.J. and Thomas, J.D. and Thuesen, E.V. and Thurston, M. and Thuy, B. and Timi, J.T. and Timm, T. and Todaro, A. and Turon, X. and Uetz, P. and Urbatsch, L. and Uribe-Palomino, J. and Urtubey, E. and Utevsky, S. and Vacelet, J. and Vachard, D. and Vader, W. and Väinölä, R. and Van de Vijver, B. and van der Meij, S.E. and van Haaren, T. and van Soest, R.W. and Vanreusel, A. and Venekey, V. and Vinarski, M. and Vonk, R. and Vos, C. and Walker-Smith, G. and Walter, T.C. and Watling, L. and Wayland, M. and Wesener, T. and Wetzel, C.E. and Whipps, C. and White, K. and Wieneke, U. and Williams, D.M. and Williams, G. and Wilson, R. and Witkowski, A. and Witkowski, J. and Wyatt, N. and Wylezich, C. and Xu, K. and Zanol, J. and Zeidler, W. and Zhao, Z., 2021, WoRMS Editorial Board, The aim of the World Register of Marine Species (WoRMS) is to provide an authoritative and comprehensive list of names of marine organisms, including information on synonymy, https://www.marinespecies.org</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
