<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Xenomapper: Mapping reads in a mixed species context</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Matthew J. Wakefield</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-6624-4698</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            The University of Melbourne
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>bioinformatics</tag>
      <tag>short read mapping</tag>
      <tag>multispecies</tag>
      <tag>xenograft</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>12 May 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00018</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>http://github.com/genomematt/xenomapper/</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.51798</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00018/10.21105.joss.00018.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Xenomapper is a utility for post processing mapped DNA sequencing reads that have been aligned to a primary genome and a secondary genome, and binning reads into species specific, multimapping in each species, unmapped and unassigned categories. It can be used on single end or paired end sequencing data across a wide range of genomics methods including RNAseq. In paired end data evidence of sequence specificity for either read will be used to assign both reads.</p>
    <p>Use cases include xenografts of human cancers and host pathogen interactions.</p>
    <p>Xenomapper is most effective with mapped reads that include an XS or ZS score that gives the mapping score of the next best read. These include Bowtie2 <span class="citation">(Langmead and Salzberg 2012)</span> and HISAT <span class="citation">(Kim, Langmead, and Salzberg 2015)</span>.</p>
    <p>This work builds upon a similar approach by Rossello et. al. <span class="citation">(Rossello et al. 2013)</span> with a more rigorous implementation and extensions for paired end data and exon aware aligners.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-HISAT">
    <p>Kim, D., B. Langmead, and S. L. Salzberg. 2015. “HISAT: A Fast Spliced Aligner with Low Memory Requirements.” Journal Article. <em>Nat Methods</em> 12 (4): 357–60. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.3317">10.1038/nmeth.3317</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-BOWTIE2">
    <p>Langmead, B., and S. L. Salzberg. 2012. “Fast Gapped-Read Alignment with Bowtie 2.” Journal Article. <em>Nat Methods</em> 9 (4): 357–9. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.1923">10.1038/nmeth.1923</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-ROSSELLO">
    <p>Rossello, F. J., R. W. Tothill, K. Britt, K. D. Marini, J. Falzon, D. M. Thomas, C. D. Peacock, et al. 2013. “Next-Generation Sequence Analysis of Cancer Xenograft Models.” Journal Article. <em>PLoS One</em> 8 (9): e74432. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0074432">10.1371/journal.pone.0074432</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
