<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Masks2Metrics (M2M): A Matlab Toolbox for Gold Standard Morphometrics</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Shadia Mikhael</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-2490-9548</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Calum Gray</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1, 2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>metrics</tag>
      <tag>gyrus</tag>
      <tag>masks</tag>
      <tag>thickness</tag>
      <tag>volume</tag>
      <tag>surface area</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>20 October 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00436</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/Edinburgh-Imaging/Masks2Metrics</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.7488/ds/2302</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00436/10.21105.joss.00436.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Human brains undergo morphometric changes over a lifetime, from conception through to birth, infancy, adolescence, adulthood, and old age (<span class="citation" data-cites="Thambisetty_2012">Thambisetty et al. (2010)</span>; <span class="citation" data-cites="Madan_2016">Madan and Kensinger (2016)</span>). This is further compounded by the changes associated with various brain pathologies such as tumours (e.g. <span class="citation" data-cites="Bauer_2013">Bauer et al. (2013)</span>) and dementia (e.g., <span class="citation" data-cites="Dickerson_2011">B. C. Dickerson et al. (2011)</span>). It is therefore essential to accurately and scientifically characterise such changes by using an array of morphologic measurements, for a better understanding of the natural progression of ageing and disease (<span class="citation" data-cites="Mills_2016">Mills et al. (2016)</span>; <span class="citation" data-cites="Madan_2017">Madan (2017)</span>). While many existing brain image analysis tools (e.g., FreeSurfer (<span class="citation" data-cites="Fischl_2004">Fischl et al. (2004)</span>; <span class="citation" data-cites="Desikan_2006">Desikan et al. (2006)</span>), BrainSuite (<span class="citation" data-cites="Shattuck_2002">Shattuck and Leahy (2002)</span>), and BrainVISA (<span class="citation" data-cites="Kochunov_2012">Kochunov et al. (2012)</span>)) automatically compute such data from a 3-dimensional (3D) brain image, they lack the ability to do so for the equivalent manually-traced regions of interest (ROIs). This is all the more significant as such ROIs are considered as the gold standard, thus making knowledge of their metrics essential.</p>
    <p>We have developed an automated Matlab-based tool, Masks2Metrics (<span class="citation" data-cites="Mikhael_2017">Mikhael and Gray (2017)</span>), that calculates three metrics for a given ROI in a 3D image: thickness, volume and suface area. An ROI is defined by a pair of binary masks (in NIfTI file format) representing its outer and inner borders, each of which are drawn continuously along one direction (x-, y- or z-axis). In the specific case of brain images, when the ROI describes a gyrus, its paired masks would correspond to grey matter (GM) and white matter (WM) curves. The paired ROI NIfTI (.nii) masks are expected to be of the form subj_roi_hem_gm/wmsegments.nii. For example, a pair corresponding to subject 1’s right SFG (superior frontal gyrus) would be 1_sfg_r_gm1.nii and 1_sfg_r_wm1.nii. A special feature of M2M is that multiple pairs, or segments, can be used rather than a single continuous ROI. These segments can be manually or automatically derived. The generated ROI metrics are grey matter thickness (GMth), grey matter volume (GMvol),and white matter surface area (WMsa), also classically calculated by popular existing automated tools (Fischl_2000; Shattuck_2002) . Additionally, the ROI’s corresponding mean Fréchet(<span class="citation" data-cites="Ursell_2013">Ursell (2013)</span>) and mean Modified Hausdorff Distance (<span class="citation" data-cites="SasiKanth_2011">SasiKanth (2011)</span>) are calculated and saved as matrices.</p>
    <p>M2M is freely available on GitHub at https://github.com/Edinburgh-Imaging/Masks2Metrics under a GNU General Public License, along with external code that is called by the tool. It can be downloaded into ‘Masks2Metrics’ folder, added to the list of Matlab paths, and consequently run by calling ‘masks2metrics’ with the appropriate input and output parameters. As part of the tool’s wiki, we provide a sample 3-segment ROI outlining part of a subject’s superior frontal gyrus for demonstration purposes. The gyrus was manually segmented over a 3D image acquired by a Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) machine.</p>
    <p>This tool not only provides invaluable gold standard data for the brain imaging field, but equally so for any other field investigating morphometrics of manually and automatically-derived 3D ROIs represented as paired binary masks.</p>
    <h1 id="authors-and-affiliations">Authors and Affiliations</h1>
    <p>Shadia Mikhael, Edinburgh Imaging, Centre for Clinical Brain Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK.<br />
    Calum Gray, Edinburgh Imaging and Edinburgh Clinical Research Facility, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK.</p>
    <h1 id="contributors">Contributors</h1>
    <p>Maria del C. Valdés Hernández, Edinburgh Imaging, Centre for Clinical Brain Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK.<br />
    Corne, Hoogendoorn, Toshiba Medical Visualization Systems Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK.<br />
    Cyril R. Pernet, Edinburgh Imaging, Centre for Clinical Brain Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Bauer_2013">
    <p>Bauer, Stefan, Roland Wiest, Lutz-P Nolte, and Mauricio Reyes. 2013. “A Survey of Mri-Based Medical Image Analysis for Brain Tumor Studies” 58 (June):R97–R129. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0031-9155/58/13/R97" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1088/0031-9155/58/13/R97</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Desikan_2006">
    <p>Desikan, Rahul S., Florent Ségonne, Bruce Fischl, Brian T. Quinn, Bradford C. Dickerson, Deborah Blacker, Randy L. Buckner, et al. 2006. “An Automated Labeling System for Subdividing the Human Cerebral Cortex on Mri Scans into Gyral Based Regions of Interest.” <em>NeuroImage</em> 31 (3):968–80. <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.01.021" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.01.021</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Dickerson_2011">
    <p>Dickerson, B. C., T. R. Stoub, R. C. Shah, R. A. Sperling, R. J. Killiany, M. S. Albert, B. T. Hyman, D. Blacker, and L. deToledo-Morrell. 2011. “Alzheimer-signature MRI biomarker predicts AD dementia in cognitively normal adults.” <em>Neurology</em> 76 (16):1395–1402. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1212/wnl.0b013e3182166e96" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1212/wnl.0b013e3182166e96</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Fischl_2004">
    <p>Fischl, Bruce, André van der Kouwe, Christophe Destrieux, Eric Halgren, Florent Ségonne, David H. Salat, Evelina Busa, et al. 2004. “Automatically Parcellating the Human Cerebral Cortex.” <em>Cerebral Cortex</em> 14 (1):11–22. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhg087" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhg087</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Kochunov_2012">
    <p>Kochunov, Peter, William Rogers, Jean-Francois Mangin, and Jack Lancaster. 2012. “A Library of Cortical Morphology Analysis Tools to Study Development, Aging and Genetics of Cerebral Cortex.” <em>Neuroinformatics</em> 10 (1):81–96. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12021-011-9127-9" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s12021-011-9127-9</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Madan_2017">
    <p>Madan, Christopher R. 2017. “Advances in Studying Brain Morphology: The Benefits of Open-Access Data.” <em>Frontiers in Human Neuroscience</em> 11:405. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fnhum.2017.00405" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.3389/fnhum.2017.00405</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Madan_2016">
    <p>Madan, Christopher R., and Elizabeth A. Kensinger. 2016. “Cortical Complexity as a Measure of Age-Related Brain Atrophy.” <em>NeuroImage</em> 134 (Supplement C):617–29. <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.04.029" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.04.029</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Mikhael_2017">
    <p>Mikhael, Shadia, and Calum Gray. 2017. “Masks2Metrics.” 2017. <a href="https://github.com/Edinburgh-Imaging/Masks2Metrics" class="uri">https://github.com/Edinburgh-Imaging/Masks2Metrics</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Mills_2016">
    <p>Mills, Kathryn L., Anne-Lise Goddings, Megan M. Herting, Rosa Meuwese, Sarah-Jayne Blakemore, Eveline A. Crone, Ronald E. Dahl, et al. 2016. “Structural Brain Development Between Childhood and Adulthood: Convergence Across Four Longitudinal Samples.” <em>NeuroImage</em> 141 (Supplement C):273–81. <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.07.044" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.07.044</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-SasiKanth_2011">
    <p>SasiKanth, S. 2011. “Modified Hausdorff Distance.” 2011. <a href="http://uk.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/29968-modified-hausdorff-distance" class="uri">http://uk.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/29968-modified-hausdorff-distance</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Shattuck_2002">
    <p>Shattuck, David W, and Richard M Leahy. 2002. “BrainSuite: An Automated Cortical Surface Identification Tool.” <em>Medical Image Analysis</em> 6 (2):129–42. <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/S1361-8415(02)00054-3" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/S1361-8415(02)00054-3</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Thambisetty_2012">
    <p>Thambisetty, Madhav, Jing Wan, Aaron Carass, Yang An, Jerry L. Prince, and Susan M. Resnick. 2010. “Longitudinal Changes in Cortical Thickness Associated with Normal Aging.” <em>NeuroImage</em> 52 (4):1215–23. <a href="https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.04.258" class="uri">https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.04.258</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Ursell_2013">
    <p>Ursell, Tristan. 2013. “Frechet Distance Calculator.” 2013. <a href="https://uk.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/41956-frechet-distance-calculator" class="uri">https://uk.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/41956-frechet-distance-calculator</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
