<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>OpenEPSim: An Open Exclusion Process Simulation Tool</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Caley Finn</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-8593-1987</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Java</tag>
      <tag>Simulation</tag>
      <tag>Exclusion Process</tag>
      <tag>Statistical Physics</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>9 March 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00650</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/caley/OpenEPSim</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1218513</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00650/10.21105.joss.00650.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>OpenEPSim is a tool for running Monte Carlo simulations of exclusion processes - the canonical example of such models is the asymmetric exclusion process (ASEP) <span class="citation" data-cites="BlytheE07">(Blythe and Evans 2007)</span>. The ASEP describes the motion of particles on a one-dimensional lattice, where particles move stochastically with specified rates. The rates for the open boundary ASEP are shown below, and allow particles to enter and exit at the lattice boundaries.</p>
    <figure>
    <img src="aseprules.png" alt="ASEP hopping rates" /><figcaption>ASEP hopping rates</figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>The ASEP (as we describe it here) is a continuous time Markov process, with the time evolution determined by the master equation. The dynamics (the hopping rates) are encoded in the <em>transition matrix</em> (for an introductory review see <span class="citation" data-cites="GolinelliM06">(Golinelli and Mallick 2006)</span>). The ASEP is a well-studied model, through exact results <span class="citation" data-cites="DerridaEHP93">(Derrida et al. 1993)</span>, approximate or phenomenological methods <span class="citation" data-cites="KolomeiskySKS98">(A. B. Kolomeisky et al. 1998)</span>, and simulation studies. However, there is ongoing interest in extensions and variations of the model - some examples include <span class="citation" data-cites="CrampeRRV16 AyyerR17 AyyerFR18">(Crampe et al. 2016; Ayyer and Roy 2017; Ayyer, Finn, and Roy 2018)</span>. The aim of OpenEPSim is to make simulating such variations as simple as defining the model mathematically.</p>
    <p>An OpenEPSim simulation is configured by specifying the transition matrix of the model, in much the same way as it is specified mathematically. It supports multi-species models, arbitrary local interactions involving 1 or more neighbouring sites, and open boundary conditions. The model, once defined, is simulated using the Gillespie algorithm<span class="citation" data-cites="Gillespie76">(Gillespie 1976)</span>, and time-averaged statistics collected. The implementation of the Gillespie algorithm is optimised, taking advantage of the local nature of the transition matrix. The primary aim of OpenEPSim is to make defining and running simulations easy, but it also attempts to perform the simulations in an efficient manner. Results of the simulations are output in JSON format, allowing easy import into analysis software.</p>
    <p>Documentation, source code, and the compiled software can be found on the <a href="https://github.com/caley/OpenEPSim">OpenEPSim GitHub page</a>.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-AyyerR17">
    <p>Ayyer, A., and D. Roy. 2017. “The Exact Phase Diagram for a Class of Open Multispecies Asymmetric Exclusion Processes.” <em>Scientific Reports</em> 7:13555. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-12768-8" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-12768-8</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-AyyerFR18">
    <p>Ayyer, A., C. Finn, and D. Roy. 2018. “Matrix Product Solution of a Left-Permeable Two-Species Asymmetric Exclusion Process.” <em>Phys. Rev. E</em> 97 (1):012151. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.97.012151" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.97.012151</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-BlytheE07">
    <p>Blythe, R A, and M R Evans. 2007. “Nonequilibrium Steady States of Matrix-Product Form: A Solver’s Guide.” <em>J. Phys. A: Math. Theor.</em> 40 (46):R333. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/1751-8113/40/46/R01" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1088/1751-8113/40/46/R01</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-CrampeRRV16">
    <p>Crampe, N., E. Ragoucy, V. Rittenberg, and M. Vanicat. 2016. “Integrable Dissipative Exclusion Process: Correlation Functions and Physical Properties.” <em>Phys. Rev. E</em> 94 (3). American Physical Society:032102. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.94.032102" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.94.032102</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-DerridaEHP93">
    <p>Derrida, B, M R Evans, V Hakim, and V Pasquier. 1993. “Exact Solution of a 1D Asymmetric Exclusion Model Using a Matrix Formulation.” <em>J. Phys. A: Math. Gen.</em> 26:1493. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/26/7/011" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/26/7/011</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Gillespie76">
    <p>Gillespie, Daniel T. 1976. “A General Method for Numerically Simulating the Stochastic Time Evolution of Coupled Chemical Reactions.” <em>Journal of Computational Physics</em> 22 (4):403–34. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0021-9991(76)90041-3" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/0021-9991(76)90041-3</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-GolinelliM06">
    <p>Golinelli, Olivier, and Kirone Mallick. 2006. “The Asymmetric Simple Exclusion Process: An Integrable Model for Non-Equilibrium Statistical Mechanics.” <em>J. Phys. A: Math. Gen.</em> 39:12679. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/39/41/S03" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/39/41/S03</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-KolomeiskySKS98">
    <p>Kolomeisky, Anatoly B, Gunter M Schütz, Eugene B Kolomeisky, and Joseph P Straley. 1998. “Phase Diagram of One-Dimensional Driven Lattice Gases with Open Boundaries.” <em>J. Phys. A: Math. Gen.</em> 31:6911. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/31/33/003" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1088/0305-4470/31/33/003</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
