<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>1b0e969848f49458b0d26f88c1c11359</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20210514055100</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>6</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>61</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>mikropml: User-Friendly R Package for Supervised Machine Learning Pipelines</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Begüm</given_name>
            <surname>Topçuoğlu</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3140-537X</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Zena</given_name>
            <surname>Lapp</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4674-2176</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Kelly</given_name>
            <surname>Sovacool</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3283-829X</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Evan</given_name>
            <surname>Snitkin</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8409-278X</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Jenna</given_name>
            <surname>Wiens</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1057-7722</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Patrick</given_name>
            <surname>Schloss</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6935-4275</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>05</month>
          <day>14</day>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>3073</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.03073</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4759346”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/3073</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.03073</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03073</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03073.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <unstructured_citation>Future.Apply: Apply Function to Elements in Parallel Using Futures, Future.Apply, Bengtsson, Henrik and Team, R Core, 2020, jul, Implementations of apply(), by(), eapply(), lapply(), Map(), .mapply(), mapply(), replicate(), sapply(), tapply(), and vapply() that can be resolved using any future-supported backend, e.g. parallel on the local machine or distributed on a compute cluster. These future apply() functions come with the same pros and cons as the corresponding base-R apply() functions but with the additional feature of being able to be processed via the future framework., GPL-2 | GPL-3 [expanded from: GPL (≥ 2)], 7</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <doi>10.1023/A:1010933404324</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <unstructured_citation>Xgboost: Extreme Gradient Boosting, Xgboost, Chen, Tianqi and He, Tong and Benesty, Michael and Khotilovich, Vadim and Tang, Yuan and Cho, Hyunsu and Chen, Kailong and Mitchell, Rory and Cano, Ignacio and Zhou, Tianyi and Li, Mu and Xie, Junyuan and Lin, Min and Geng, Yifeng and Li, Yutian and implementation), XGBoost contributors (base XGBoost, 2020, jun, Extreme Gradient Boosting, which is an efficient implementation of the gradient boosting framework from Chen &amp; Guestrin (2016) &lt;doi:10.1145/2939672.2939785&gt;. This package is its R interface. The package includes efficient linear model solver and tree learning algorithms. The package can automatically do parallel computation on a single machine which could be more than 10 times faster than existing gradient boosting packages. It supports various objective functions, including regression, classification and ranking. The package is made to be extensible, so that users are also allowed to define their own objectives easily., Apache License (== 2.0) | file LICENSE, HighPerformanceComputing,MachineLearning,ModelDeployment, 6</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <unstructured_citation>All Models Are Wrong, but Many Are Useful: Learning a Variable’s Importance by Studying an Entire Class of Prediction Models Simultaneously, Fisher, Aaron and Rudin, Cynthia and Dominici, Francesca, 2018</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <doi>10.18637/jss.v033.i01</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <unstructured_citation>H2O: Scalable Machine Learning Platform, H2O.ai, 2020, Manual</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <doi>10.1128/mBio.01680-20</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <unstructured_citation>Rlang: Functions for Base Types and Core R and ’Tidyverse’ Features, Rlang, Henry, Lionel and Wickham, Hadley and RStudio, 2020, jul, A toolbox for working with base types, core R features like the condition system, and core ’Tidyverse’ features like tidy evaluation., GPL-3, 7</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <doi>10.18637/jss.v011.i09</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <doi>10.1093/bioinformatics/bts480</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <doi>10.18637/jss.v028.i05</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <unstructured_citation>Tidymodels: Easily Install and Load the ’Tidymodels’ Packages, Tidymodels, Kuhn, Max and Wickham, Hadley and RStudio, 2020, jul, The tidy modeling “verse” is a collection of packages for modeling and statistical analysis that share the underlying design philosophy, grammar, and data structures of the tidyverse., GPL-3 | file LICENSE, 7</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <doi>10.1101/2020.07.06.20147306</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <unstructured_citation>Classification and Regression by randomForest, Liaw, Andy and Wiener, Matthew, 2002, 2, 5, /Volumes/GoogleDrive/My Drive/Zotero/storage/YZD2ALMT/Liaw and Wiener - 2002 - Classiﬁcation and Regression by randomForest.pdf, English</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <unstructured_citation>E1071: Misc Functions of the Department of Statistics, Probability Theory Group (Formerly: E1071), TU Wien, E1071, Meyer, David and Dimitriadou, Evgenia and Hornik, Kurt and Weingessel, Andreas and Leisch, Friedrich and C++-code), Chih-Chung Chang (libsvm and C++-code), Chih-Chen Lin (libsvm, 2020, oct, Functions for latent class analysis, short time Fourier transform, fuzzy clustering, support vector machines, shortest path computation, bagged clustering, naive Bayes classifier, …, GPL-2 | GPL-3, Cluster,Distributions,Environmetrics,MachineLearning,Multivariate,Psychometrics, 10</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref16">
            <unstructured_citation>Scikit-Learn: Machine Learning in Python, Scikit-Learn, Pedregosa, Fabian and Varoquaux, Gaël and Gramfort, Alexandre and Michel, Vincent and Thirion, Bertrand and Grisel, Olivier and Blondel, Mathieu and Prettenhofer, Peter and Weiss, Ron and Dubourg, Vincent and Vanderplas, Jake and Passos, Alexandre and Cournapeau, David and Brucher, Matthieu and Perrot, Matthieu and Duchesnay, Édouard, 2011, 12, 2825–2830, Scikit-learn is a Python module integrating a wide range of state-of-the-art machine learning algorithms for medium-scale supervised and unsupervised problems. This package focuses on bringing machine learning to non-specialists using a general-purpose high-level language. Emphasis is put on ease of use, performance, documentation, and API consistency. It has minimal dependencies and is distributed under the simplified BSD license, encouraging its use in both academic and commercial settings. Source code, binaries, and documentation can be downloaded from http://scikit-learn.sourceforge.net., /Volumes/GoogleDrive/My Drive/Zotero/storage/WM7EF3D2/Pedregosa et al. - 2011 - Scikit-learn Machine Learning in Python.pdf, Journal of Machine Learning Research, 85</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref17">
            <doi>10.1016/S2589-7500(19)30112-8</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref18">
            <unstructured_citation>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing, R Core Team, 2020, R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref19">
            <doi>10.1093/jamia/ocaa139</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref20">
            <doi>10.1038/s41563-018-0241-z</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref21">
            <unstructured_citation>Rpart: Recursive Partitioning and Regression Trees, Rpart, Therneau, Terry and Atkinson, Beth and port, Brian Ripley (producer of the initial R. and 1999-2017), maintainer, 2019, apr, Recursive partitioning for classification, regression and survival trees. An implementation of most of the functionality of the 1984 book by Breiman, Friedman, Olshen and Stone., GPL-2 | GPL-3, Environmetrics,MachineLearning,Multivariate,Survival, 4</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref22">
            <doi>10.1128/mBio.00434-20</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref23">
            <unstructured_citation>Dplyr: A Grammar of Data Manipulation, Dplyr, Wickham, Hadley and François, Romain and Henry, Lionel and Müller, Kirill and RStudio, 2020, aug, A fast, consistent tool for working with data frame like objects, both in memory and out of memory., MIT + file LICENSE, Databases,ModelDeployment, 8</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref24">
            <doi>10.1007/978-3-319-24277-4</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref25">
            <doi>10.1038/s41591-019-0548-6</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref26">
            <unstructured_citation>MLmetrics: Machine Learning Evaluation Metrics, MLmetrics, Yan, Yachen, 2016, may, A collection of evaluation metrics, including loss, score and utility functions, that measure regression, classification and ranking performance., GPL-2, 5</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
