<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>spatial-efd: A spatial-aware implementation of elliptical Fourier analysis</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Stuart W D Grieve</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-1893-7363</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1, 2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Elliptical Fourier descriptors</tag>
      <tag>Elliptical Fourier analysis</tag>
      <tag>GIS</tag>
      <tag>GeoScience</tag>
      <tag>Shapefile</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>23 February 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00189</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/sgrieve/spatial_efd</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.322453</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00189/10.21105.joss.00189.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>A Python implementation of the calculation of elliptical Fourier descriptors as described by <span class="citation">Kuhl and Giardina (1982)</span>. This package is designed to allow the rapid analysis of spatial data stored as ESRI shapefiles, handling all of the geometric conversions. The computed Fourier ellipses can then be written back to shapefiles to allow analysis with other spatial data, or can be plotted using matplotlib <span class="citation">(Hunter 2007)</span>. The code is built upon the pyefd module <span class="citation">(Blidh 2013)</span> and it is hoped that this package will make analyzing spatial data using Fourier ellipses more straightforward.</p>
    <p>This package implements the original methodology of <span class="citation">Kuhl and Giardina (1982)</span> to compute Fourier coefficients from polygon data loaded from shapefiles, and to transform these coefficients back into spatial coordinates with a range of different coordinate normalization schemes. The number of harmonics required to describe a polygon to a user defined threshold Fourier power can be computed, following <span class="citation">Costa et al. (2009)</span>. The averaging of Fourier coefficients is also implemented, as described by <span class="citation">Raj and Cannon (1999)</span>, which can be used to provide averaged shapes to machine learning algorithms. Functions are available to handle the challenges of relating spatial coordinates to the normalized Fourier ellipse coordinates, to allow the calculated Fourier ellipses to be output as shapefiles for further analysis in GIS packages.</p>
    <p>The latest stable release of the software can be installed via <code>pip</code>, the development version is available from github (https://github.com/sgrieve/spatial-efd/) and the full documentation and API can be found at https://spatial-efd.readthedocs.io.</p>
    <div class="figure">
    <img src="../_static/figure_1.png" alt="Examples of Fourier ellipses (black) being fitted to a shapefile outline (red), for increasing numbers of harmonics." id="id" class="class" width="400" />
    <p class="caption">Examples of Fourier ellipses (black) being fitted to a shapefile outline (red), for increasing numbers of harmonics.</p>
    </div>
    <h1 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h1>
    <p>The development of this software has been supported by Natural Environment Research Council grants NE/J009970/1 and NE/N01300X/1.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-pyefd">
    <p>Blidh, Henrik. 2013. “Python Implementation of Elliptic Fourier Features of a Closed Contour.” <a href="https://github.com/hbldh/pyefd" class="uri">https://github.com/hbldh/pyefd</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-costa2009quantitative">
    <p>Costa, Corrado, Paolo Menesatti, Graziella Paglia, Federico Pallottino, Jacopo Aguzzi, Valentina Rimatori, Giuseppe Russo, Santo Recupero, and Giuseppe Reforgiato Recupero. 2009. “Quantitative Evaluation of Tarocco Sweet Orange Fruit Shape Using Optoelectronic Elliptic Fourier Based Analysis.” <em>Postharvest Biology and Technology</em> 54 (1). Elsevier: 38–47.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Hunter2007">
    <p>Hunter, J. D. 2007. “Matplotlib: A 2D Graphics Environment.” <em>Computing In Science &amp; Engineering</em> 9 (3). IEEE COMPUTER SOC: 90–95. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2007.55">10.1109/MCSE.2007.55</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-kuhl1982elliptic">
    <p>Kuhl, Frank P, and Charles R Giardina. 1982. “Elliptic Fourier Features of a Closed Contour.” <em>Computer Graphics and Image Processing</em> 18 (3). Elsevier: 236–58.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-raj1992">
    <p>Raj, P Markondeya, and W Roger Cannon. 1999. “2-d Particle Shape Averaging and Comparison Using Fourier Descriptors.” <em>Powder Technology</em> 104 (2). Elsevier: 180–89.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
