<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>LAS: an integrated language analysis tool for multiple languages</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Eetu Mäkelä</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-8366-8414</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>NLP</tag>
      <tag>language analysis</tag>
      <tag>morphological analysis</tag>
      <tag>lemmatization</tag>
      <tag>language identification</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>29 June 2016</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00035</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/jiemakel/las</software_repository>
    <software_archive>https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.160256</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/blob/master/joss.00035/10.21105.joss.00035.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>LAS is a command-line tool for lemmatizing, morphological analysis, inflected form generation, hyphenation and language identification of multiple languages.</p>
    <p>These functionalities are of use as part of many workflows requiring natural language processing. Indeed, LAS has been used for example as part of a pipeline for entity recognition <span class="citation">(Mäkelä 2014)</span>, in creating a contextual reader for texts in English, Finnish and Latin <span class="citation">(Mäkelä, Lindquist, and Hyvönen 2016)</span>, and for processing a Finnish historical newspaper collection in preparation for data publication <span class="citation">(Pääkkönen et al. 2016)</span>.</p>
    <p>The functionalities of LAS are mostly based on integrating existing tools into a common package. Particularly, the tool bases on: * Finite state transducers provided by the <a href="http://hfst.sourceforge.net/">HFST</a> <span class="citation">(Linden et al. 2013)</span>, <a href="https://github.com/flammie/omorfi/">Omorfi</a> <span class="citation">(T. A. Pirinen 2015)</span> and <a href="http://giellatekno.uit.no/">Giellatekno</a> <span class="citation">(Moshagen et al., n.d.)</span> projects * <a href="http://snowballstem.org/">Snowball</a> stemmers * the <a href="https://github.com/optimaize/language-detector">language-detector</a> library * Statistical language models from <a href="http://turkunlp.github.io/Finnish-dep-parser/">Turku NLP</a> <span class="citation">(Haverinen et al. 2014)</span></p>
    <p>While LAS supports many languages, the most complete support it has is for Finnish, where considerable work has gone into improving the results.</p>
    <p>Aside from a being available as a command-line tool, the functionalities in LAS are also available as a web service, at http://demo.seco.tkk.fi/las/.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-haverinen2013tdt">
    <p>Haverinen, Katri, Jenna Nyblom, Timo Viljanen, Veronika Laippala, Samuel Kohonen, Anna Missilä, Stina Ojala, Tapio Salakoski, and Filip Ginter. 2014. “Building the Essential Resources for Finnish: The Turku Dependency Treebank.” <em>Language Resources and Evaluation</em> 48 (3). Springer Netherlands: 493–531. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10579-013-9244-1">10.1007/s10579-013-9244-1</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-hfst">
    <p>Linden, Krister, Erik Axelson, Senka Drobac, Sam Hardwick, Juha Kuokkala, Jyrki Niemi, Tommi Pirinen, and Miikka Silfverberg. 2013. “HFST – a System for Creating NLP Tools.” In <em>Systems and Frameworks for Computational Morphology</em>, edited by Cerstin Mahlow and Michael Piotrowski, 380:53–71. Communications in Computer and Information Science. Berlin Heidelberg: Springer.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-makela-sarpa-2014">
    <p>Mäkelä, Eetu. 2014. “Combining a REST Lexical Analysis Web Service with SPARQL for Mashup Semantic Annotation from Text.” In <em>The Semantic Web: ESWC 2014 Satellite Events: ESWC 2014 Satellite Events, Anissaras, Crete, Greece, May 25-29, 2014, Revised Selected Papers</em>, edited by Valentina Presutti, Eva Blomqvist, Raphael Troncy, Harald Sack, Ioannis Papadakis, and Anna Tordai, 424–28. Cham: Springer International Publishing. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-11955-7_60">10.1007/978-3-319-11955-7_60</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-makela-et-al-core-dh2016">
    <p>Mäkelä, Eetu, Thea Lindquist, and Eero Hyvönen. 2016. “CORE - a Contextual Reader Based on Linked Data.” In <em>Proceedings of Digital Humanities 2016, Long Papers</em>. Kraków, Poland.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-moshagenopen">
    <p>Moshagen, Sjur, Jack Rueter, Tommi Pirinen, Trond Trosterud, and Francis M Tyers. n.d. “Open-Source Infrastructures for Collaborative Work on Under-Resourced Languages.” In <em>Proceedings of the Ninth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation, LREC</em>, 71–77.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-dhn2016">
    <p>Pääkkönen, Tuula, Jukka Kervinen, Asko Nivala, Kimmo Kettunen, and Eetu Mäkelä. 2016. “Exporting Finnish Digitized Historical Newspaper Contents for Offline Use.” <em>D-Lib Magazine</em> 22 (7/8). Corporation for National Research Initiatives. doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.1045/july2016-paakkonen">10.1045/july2016-paakkonen</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-pirinen2015omorfi">
    <p>Pirinen, Tommi A. 2015. “Omorfi—Free and Open Source Morphological Lexical Database for Finnish.” In <em>Proceedings of the 20th Nordic Conference of Computational Linguistics, NODALIDA 2015, May 11-13, 2015, Vilnius, Lithuania</em>, 313–15. 109. Linköping University Electronic Press.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
