<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>3171d66b91aa308e0d4493c8cdbdcee4</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20180205154011</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>The Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>http://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>02</month>
          <year>2018</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>3</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>22</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>CheckQC: Quick quality control of Illumina sequencing runs</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors><person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author"><given_name>Matilda</given_name><surname>Åslin</surname><ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2450-6415</ORCID></person_name><person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author"><given_name>Monika</given_name><surname>Brandt</surname><ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8184-9465</ORCID></person_name><person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author"><given_name>Johan</given_name><surname>Dahlberg</surname><ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6962-1460</ORCID></person_name></contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>02</month>
          <day>05</day>
          <year>2018</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>556</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.00556</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1166052</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/556</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.00556</doi>
          <resource>http://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.00556</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00556/10.21105.joss.00556.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list><citation key="ref1"><unstructured_citation>bcl2fastq Conversion Software, Combines per-cycle BCL files from a run and translates them into demultiplexed FASTQ files for downstream data analysis., \urlhttps://support.illumina.com/sequencing/sequencing_software/bcl2fastq-conversion-software.html, Accessed: 2018-1-26</unstructured_citation></citation><citation key="ref2"><unstructured_citation>Arteria: An automation system for a sequencing core facility, Dahlberg, Johan and Hermansson, Johan and Sturlaugsson, Steinar and Larsson, Pontus, Arteria is an automation system aimed at sequencing core facilities. It is built on existing open source technologies, with a modular design allowing for a community-driven effort to create plug-and-play micro-services. Herein we describe the Arteria system and elaborate on the underlying conceptual framework. The Arteria system breaks down into three conceptual levels; orchestration, process and execution. At the orchestration level it utilizes an event-based model of automation. It models processes, e.g. the steps involved in processing sequencing data, as workflows and executes these in a micro-service based environment. This creates a system which is both flexible and scalable. The Arteria Project code is available as open source software at http://www.github.com/arteria-project., bioRxiv, 214858, nov, 2017, en, 11</unstructured_citation></citation><citation key="ref3"><unstructured_citation>FastQC A Quality Control tool for High Throughput Sequence Data, \urlhttps://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/, Accessed: 2018-1-26</unstructured_citation></citation><citation key="ref4"><unstructured_citation>DNA sequencing technologies: 2006-2016, Mardis, Elaine R, McDonnell Genome Institute, Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri, USA., Recent advances in the field of genomics have largely been due to the ability to sequence DNA at increasing throughput and decreasing cost. DNA sequencing was first introduced in 1977, and next-generation sequencing technologies have been available only during the past decade, but the diverse experiments and corresponding analyses facilitated by these techniques have transformed biological and biomedical research. Here, I review developments in DNA sequencing technologies over the past 10 years and look to the future for further applications., Nat. Protoc., 12, 2, 213–218, feb, 2017, en, 2</unstructured_citation></citation><citation key="ref5"><unstructured_citation>Recommendations on e-infrastructures for next-generation sequencing, Spjuth, Ola and Bongcam-Rudloff, Erik and Dahlberg, Johan and Dahlö, Martin and Kallio, Aleksi and Pireddu, Luca and Vezzi, Francesco and Korpelainen, Eija, Department of Pharmaceutical Biosciences and Science for Life Laboratory, Uppsala University, Uppsala, P.O. Box 591, SE-75124, Sweden. ola.spjuth@farmbio.uu.se. SLU-Global Bioinformatics Centre, Department of Animal Breeding and Genetics, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Uppsala, Sweden. National Genomics Infrastructure, Science for Life Laboratory, Uppsala University, Stockholm, P.O. Box 1031, SE-17121, Sweden. Department of Pharmaceutical Biosciences and Science for Life Laboratory, Uppsala University, Uppsala, P.O. Box 591, SE-75124, Sweden. Science for Life Laboratory, Uppsala University, Husargatan 3, Uppsala, SE-75123, Sweden. CSC - IT Center for Science Ltd., Espoo, P.O. Box 405, FI-02101, Finland. CRS4, Polaris, Loc. Piscina Manna Ed. 1, Pula, 09010, Italy. University of Cagliari, Cagliari, 09124, Italy. Science for Life Laboratory, Stockholm University, Stockholm, SE-17121, Sweden. CSC - IT Center for Science Ltd., Espoo, P.O. Box 405, FI-02101, Finland., With ever-increasing amounts of data being produced by next-generation sequencing (NGS) experiments, the requirements placed on supporting e-infrastructures have grown. In this work, we provide recommendations based on the collective experiences from participants in the EU COST Action SeqAhead for the tasks of data preprocessing, upstream processing, data delivery, and downstream analysis, as well as long-term storage and archiving. We cover demands on computational and storage resources, networks, software stacks, automation of analysis, education, and also discuss emerging trends in the field. E-infrastructures for NGS require substantial effort to set up and maintain over time, and with sequencing technologies and best practices for data analysis evolving rapidly it is important to prioritize both processing capacity and e-infrastructure flexibility when making strategic decisions to support the data analysis demands of tomorrow. Due to increasingly demanding technical requirements we recommend that e-infrastructure development and maintenance be handled by a professional service unit, be it internal or external to the organization, and emphasis should be placed on collaboration between researchers and IT professionals., Gigascience, 5, 26, jun, 2016, Cloud computing; E-infrastructure; High-performance computing; Next-generation sequencing, en, 6</unstructured_citation></citation><citation key="ref6"><unstructured_citation>Initial sequencing and analysis of the human genome, Lander, E S and Linton, L M and Birren, B and Nusbaum, C and Zody, M C and Baldwin, J and Devon, K and Dewar, K and Doyle, M and FitzHugh, W and Funke, R and Gage, D and Harris, K and Heaford, A and Howland, J and Kann, L and Lehoczky, J and LeVine, R and McEwan, P and McKernan, K and Meldrim, J and Mesirov, J P and Miranda, C and Morris, W and Naylor, J and Raymond, C and Rosetti, M and Santos, R and Sheridan, A and Sougnez, C and Stange-Thomann, Y and Stojanovic, N and Subramanian, A and Wyman, D and Rogers, J and Sulston, J and Ainscough, R and Beck, S and Bentley, D and Burton, J and Clee, C and Carter, N and Coulson, A and Deadman, R and Deloukas, P and Dunham, A and Dunham, I and Durbin, R and French, L and Grafham, D and Gregory, S and Hubbard, T and Humphray, S and Hunt, A and Jones, M and Lloyd, C and McMurray, A and Matthews, L and Mercer, S and Milne, S and Mullikin, J C and Mungall, A and Plumb, R and Ross, M and Shownkeen, R and Sims, S and Waterston, R H and Wilson, R K and Hillier, L W and McPherson, J D and Marra, M A and Mardis, E R and Fulton, L A and Chinwalla, A T and Pepin, K H and Gish, W R and Chissoe, S L and Wendl, M C and Delehaunty, K D and Miner, T L and Delehaunty, A and Kramer, J B and Cook, L L and Fulton, R S and Johnson, D L and Minx, P J and Clifton, S W and Hawkins, T and Branscomb, E and Predki, P and Richardson, P and Wenning, S and Slezak, T and Doggett, N and Cheng, J F and Olsen, A and Lucas, S and Elkin, C and Uberbacher, E and Frazier, M and Gibbs, R A and Muzny, D M and Scherer, S E and Bouck, J B and Sodergren, E J and Worley, K C and Rives, C M and Gorrell, J H and Metzker, M L and Naylor, S L and Kucherlapati, R S and Nelson, D L and Weinstock, G M and Sakaki, Y and Fujiyama, A and Hattori, M and Yada, T and Toyoda, A and Itoh, T and Kawagoe, C and Watanabe, H and Totoki, Y and Taylor, T and Weissenbach, J and Heilig, R and Saurin, W and Artiguenave, F and Brottier, P and Bruls, T and Pelletier, E and Robert, C and Wincker, P and Smith, D R and Doucette-Stamm, L and Rubenfield, M and Weinstock, K and Lee, H M and Dubois, J and Rosenthal, A and Platzer, M and Nyakatura, G and Taudien, S and Rump, A and Yang, H and Yu, J and Wang, J and Huang, G and Gu, J and Hood, L and Rowen, L and Madan, A and Qin, S and Davis, R W and Federspiel, N A and Abola, A P and Proctor, M J and Myers, R M and Schmutz, J and Dickson, M and Grimwood, J and Cox, D R and Olson, M V and Kaul, R and Raymond, C and Shimizu, N and Kawasaki, K and Minoshima, S and Evans, G A and Athanasiou, M and Schultz, R and Roe, B A and Chen, F and Pan, H and Ramser, J and Lehrach, H and Reinhardt, R and McCombie, W R and de la Bastide, M and Dedhia, N and Blöcker, H and Hornischer, K and Nordsiek, G and Agarwala, R and Aravind, L and Bailey, J A and Bateman, A and Batzoglou, S and Birney, E and Bork, P and Brown, D G and Burge, C B and Cerutti, L and Chen, H C and Church, D and Clamp, M and Copley, R R and Doerks, T and Eddy, S R and Eichler, E E and Furey, T S and Galagan, J and Gilbert, J G and Harmon, C and Hayashizaki, Y and Haussler, D and Hermjakob, H and Hokamp, K and Jang, W and Johnson, L S and Jones, T A and Kasif, S and Kaspryzk, A and Kennedy, S and Kent, W J and Kitts, P and Koonin, E V and Korf, I and Kulp, D and Lancet, D and Lowe, T M and McLysaght, A and Mikkelsen, T and Moran, J V and Mulder, N and Pollara, V J and Ponting, C P and Schuler, G and Schultz, J and Slater, G and Smit, A F and Stupka, E and Szustakowki, J and Thierry-Mieg, D and Thierry-Mieg, J and Wagner, L and Wallis, J and Wheeler, R and Williams, A and Wolf, Y I and Wolfe, K H and Yang, S P and Yeh, R F and Collins, F and Guyer, M S and Peterson, J and Felsenfeld, A and Wetterstrand, K A and Patrinos, A and Morgan, M J and de Jong, P and Catanese, J J and Osoegawa, K and Shizuya, H and Choi, S and Chen, Y J and Szustakowki, J and International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, Whitehead Institute for Biomedical Research, Center for Genome Research, Cambridge, MA 02142, USA. lander@genome.wi.mit.edu, The human genome holds an extraordinary trove of information about human development, physiology, medicine and evolution. Here we report the results of an international collaboration to produce and make freely available a draft sequence of the human genome. We also present an initial analysis of the data, describing some of the insights that can be gleaned from the sequence., Nature, 409, 6822, 860–921, feb, 2001, en, 2</unstructured_citation></citation><citation key="ref7"><doi>10.18129/B9.bioc.basecallQC</doi></citation><citation key="ref8"><unstructured_citation>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing, R Core Team, R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, 2017, https://www.R-project.org/</unstructured_citation></citation></citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
