<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>MicroBenthos: a modeling framework for microbial benthic ecology</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Arjun Chennu</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-0389-5589</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>marine biology</tag>
      <tag>biogeochemistry</tag>
      <tag>microbial ecology</tag>
      <tag>microbial mats</tag>
      <tag>sediments</tag>
      <tag>modeling</tag>
      <tag>simulation</tag>
      <tag>microbenthic habitat</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>4 April 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00674</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/achennu/microbenthos</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1240940</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00674/10.21105.joss.00674.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Microbial benthic habitats, such as microbial mats and sediments, exhibit extremely steep gradients in the physical, chemical and biotic parameters within the space of a few millimeters. These micro-environments drive the localization and exploitation of physico-chemical niches by a variety of microbial groups, such as cyanobacteria, sulfur-oxidizing bacteria, etc <span class="citation" data-cites="VanGemerden-1993">(Van Gemerden 1993)</span>. Studies of biogeochemistry and microbial ecology in these systems use various sensors to profile micro-environments and infer the local budgets and productivities of the microbial groups and metabolisms <span class="citation" data-cites="Revsbech-1983">(Revsbech et al. 1983)</span>. Microbenthic habitats are typically modeled as diffusive-reactive systems <span class="citation" data-cites="deWit-1995">(Wit, Ende, and Gemerden 1995)</span>, i.e. the dominant mass transport mode is physical diffusion of solutes within the porespaces of the sediment matrix. The “reactive” aspect refers to the presence of a large number of local sources and sinks within the mat system.</p>
    <p>MicroBenthos is a modeling framework created to study <em>in silico</em> microbenthic habitats. The main perspective is to recognize that while modeling physical diffusion is straightforward, the larger challenge is to have a flexible way to define, compose and study various microbial metabolisms under dynamic conditions. MicroBenthos enables this by providing a high-level abstraction to compose and simulate microbenthic systems in terms of solar irradiance, chemical solutes, microbial groups and chemical or metabolic processes. While the software is written in python, with a modular structure for ease of extensibility, it can be used without programming through a (YAML) structured text file as the interface. This allows the user to focus on specifying the constitutive relations between environmental parameters and processes as a simple mathematical formula, which is then symbolically cast (using sympy <span class="citation" data-cites="Meurer-2017">(Meurer et al. 2017)</span>) into a set of coupled partial differential equations for the full model. Using a simple command, the equations can be numerically solved (using fipy <span class="citation" data-cites="Guyer-2009">(Guyer, Wheeler, and Warren 2009)</span>) to study the evolution of the various model variables.</p>
    <p>MicroBenthos provides several useful features:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Modular and extensible abstractions to create microbenthic systems</li>
    <li>Non-programming interface to define processes and model structure</li>
    <li>On-line visualization of running simulations and video export</li>
    <li>Stateful simulations that can be interrupted and resumed</li>
    <li>Export of detailed model data in open archival format</li>
    <li>Open-source software (MIT license): https://github.com/achennu/microbenthos</li>
    <li>Detailed documentation and tutorials: https://microbenthos.readthedocs.io</li>
    </ul>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Guyer-2009">
    <p>Guyer, Jonathan E., Daniel Wheeler, and James A. Warren. 2009. “FiPy: Partial Differential Equations with Python.” <em>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</em> 11 (3). Institute of Electrical; Electronics Engineers (IEEE):6–15. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/mcse.2009.52" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1109/mcse.2009.52</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Meurer-2017">
    <p>Meurer, Aaron, Christopher P. Smith, Mateusz Paprocki, Ondřej Čertík, Sergey B. Kirpichev, Matthew Rocklin, AMiT Kumar, et al. 2017. “SymPy: Symbolic Computing in Python.” <em>PeerJ Computer Science</em> 3 (January). PeerJ:e103. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj-cs.103" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj-cs.103</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Revsbech-1983">
    <p>Revsbech, Niels Peter, Bo Barker Jørgensen, T Henry Blackburn, and Yehuda Cohen. 1983. “Microelectrode Studies of the Photosynthesis and O2, H2S, and pH Profiles of a Microbial Mat.” <em>Limnology and Oceanography</em> 28 (6):1062–74. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4319/lo.1983.28.6.1062" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.4319/lo.1983.28.6.1062</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-VanGemerden-1993">
    <p>Van Gemerden, Hans. 1993. “Microbial Mats: A Joint Venture.” <em>Marine Geology</em> 113 (1). Elsevier:3–25. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0025-3227(93)90146-M" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/0025-3227(93)90146-M</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-deWit-1995">
    <p>Wit, Rutger de, Frank P. van den Ende, and Hans van Gemerden. 1995. “Mathematical Simulation of the Interactions Among Cyanobacteria, Purple Sulfur Bacteria and Chemotrophic Sulfur Bacteria in Microbial Mat Communities.” <em>FEMS Microbiology Ecology</em> 17 (2). Oxford University Press (OUP):117–36. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6941.1995.tb00136.x" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6941.1995.tb00136.x</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
