<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>TSrepr R package: Time Series Representations</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Peter Laurinec</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3501-8783</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>time series</tag>
      <tag>data mining</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>8 March 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00577</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/PetoLau/TSrepr</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1195877</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00577/10.21105.joss.00577.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p><code>TSrepr</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="tsrepr">(Laurinec 2018)</span> is an R package for time series representations computing. Time series representations are, in other words, methods for dimensionality reduction, feature extraction or for the preprocessing of time series. They are used for <span class="citation" data-cites="Esling">(Esling and Agon 2012)</span>:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Significant reduction of the time series dimensionality,</li>
    <li>Emphasis of fundamental (essential) shape characteristics,</li>
    <li>Implicit noise handling,</li>
    <li>Dimension reduction will reduce the memory requirements and computational complexity of consequent machine learning methods (e.g., classification or clustering).</li>
    </ul>
    <p>The <code>TSrepr</code> package contains various methods and types of time series representations including the Piecewise Aggregate Approximation (PAA), the Discrete Fourier Transform (DFT), the Perceptually Important Points (PIP), the Symbolic Aggregate approXimation (SAX), the Piecewise Linear Approximation (PLA) and Clipping. Except for these well-known methods, additional methods suitable for seasonal time series are implemented. These methods are based on the model, for example multiple linear regression, robust regression, generalised additive model or triple exponential smoothing <span class="citation" data-cites="Lau1">(Laurinec and Lucká 2016, <span class="citation" data-cites="Lau2">Laurinec et al. (2016)</span>)</span>. Own developed feature extraction methods from the Clipping representation are also implemented - FeaClip and FeaTrend. In Figure 1, the comparison of all eight available model-based representations in the <code>TSrepr</code> on electricity consumption time series from the randomly picked residential consumer is shown.</p>
    <p><embed src="modelBased.pdf" /> Figure 1. The comparison of model-based time series representations on electricity consumption time series. The length of representations is <span class="math inline">48</span>, the same as frequency of the daily season of the used time series.</p>
    <p>Additional useful functions and methods related to time series representations were also implemented. The <code>TSrepr</code> package includes functions for normalisations and denormalisations of time series - z-score and min-max methods. It supports the simple computation of the windowing method, a matrix of representations and forecasting accuracy measures (MAE, RMSE, MAPE, sMAPE etc.). Methods (functions) were implemented in base R and also in C++ for fast computations. In R, C++ programmes can be written thanks to the package Rcpp <span class="citation" data-cites="rcpp">(Eddelbuettel and Francois 2011)</span>.</p>
    <p>So far, no general package for time series representations computations has been created. The CRAN’s time series task view proves the previous statement. Packages <code>TSMining</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="tsmining">(Fan 2015)</span> and <code>jmotif</code> <span class="citation" data-cites="jmotif">(Senin 2016)</span> both includes implementations of PAA and SAX time series representations methods. However, these packages are mainly focused on motif discovery in time series.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-rcpp">
    <p>Eddelbuettel, Dirk, and Romain Francois. 2011. “Rcpp: Seamless R and C++ Integration.” <em>Journal of Statistical Software, Articles</em> 40 (8):1–18. <a href="https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v040.i08" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v040.i08</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Esling">
    <p>Esling, Philippe, and Carlos Agon. 2012. “Time-series data mining.” <em>ACM Computing Surveys</em> 45 (1). ACM:1–34.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-tsmining">
    <p>Fan, Cheng. 2015. <em>TSMining: Mining Univariate and Multivariate Motifs in Time-Series Data</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=TSMining" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=TSMining</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-tsrepr">
    <p>Laurinec, Peter. 2018. <em>TSrepr: Time Series Representations</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=TSrepr" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=TSrepr</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Lau1">
    <p>Laurinec, Peter, and Mária Lucká. 2016. “Comparison of Representations of Time Series for Clustering Smart Meter Data.” In <em>Lecture Notes in Engineering and Computer Science: Proceedings of the World Congress on Engineering and Computer Science 2016</em>, 458–63.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Lau2">
    <p>Laurinec, Peter, Marek Lóderer, Petra Vrablecová, Mária Lucká, Viera Rozinajová, and Anna Bou Ezzeddine. 2016. “Adaptive Time Series Forecasting of Energy Consumption Using Optimized Cluster Analysis.” In <em>Data Mining Workshops (Icdmw), 2016 Ieee 16th International Conference on</em>, 398–405. IEEE.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-jmotif">
    <p>Senin, Pavel. 2016. <em>Jmotif: Time Series Analysis Toolkit Based on Symbolic Aggregate Dicretization, I.e. SAX</em>. <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=jmotif" class="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=jmotif</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
