<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>BATMAN: Statistical analysis for expensive computer codes made easy</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Pamphile T. Roy</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-9816-1416</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Sophie Ricci</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4232-5626</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Romain Dupuis</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            2
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Robin Campet</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-4434-0854</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Jean-Christophe Jouhaud</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Cyril Fournier</name>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Python</tag>
      <tag>Uncertainty Quantification</tag>
      <tag>Statistical Analysis</tag>
      <tag>Surrogate Model</tag>
      <tag>Design of Experiments</tag>
      <tag>Uncertainty Visualization</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>23 November 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00493</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://gitlab.com/cerfacs/batman</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1163545</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00493/10.21105.joss.00493.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>Bayesian Analysis Tool for Modelling and uncertAinty quaNtification (batman) is an open source Python package dedicated to statistical analysis based on non-intrusive ensemble experiment.</p>
    <p>Numerical software has reached a sufficient maturity to represent physical phenomena. High fidelity simulation is possible with continuous advances in numerical methods and in High Performance Computing (HPC). Still, deterministic simulations only provide limited knowledge on a system as uncertainties in the numerical model and its inputs translate into uncertainties in the outputs. Ensemble-based methods are used to construct a numerical or experimental dataset from which statistics are inferred.</p>
    <p><em>batman</em> library provides a convenient, modular and efficient framework for design of experiments, surrogate model and uncertainty quantification. <em>batman</em> relies on open source python packages dedicated to statistics (<em>openTURNS</em> and <em>scikit-learn</em> <span class="citation" data-cites="openturns">(Baudin et al. 2015, <span class="citation" data-cites="scikit-learn">Pedregosa et al. (2011)</span>)</span>). It also implements advanced methods for resampling, robust optimization and uncertainty visualization <span class="citation" data-cites="roy2017a">(Pamphile Tupui Roy, Segui, et al. 2017)</span>.</p>
    <p><em>batman</em> handles the workflow for statistical analysis. It makes the most of HPC resources by managing asynchronous parallel tasks. The internal parallelism of each task does not conflict with <em>batman</em>’s parallel environment.</p>
    <p><em>batman</em> analysis is launched from a <em>command line interface</em> and a setting file. <em>batman</em> functionalities can also be accessed through an API. <em>batman</em> has been successfully used for geosciences and turbomachinery Computational Fluid Dynamics applications <span class="citation" data-cites="roy2017a">(Pamphile Tupui Roy, Segui, et al. 2017, <span class="citation" data-cites="roy2017b">Pamphile T. Roy et al. (2017)</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="roy2017c">Pamphile Tupui Roy, El Moçayd, et al. (2017)</span>)</span>.</p>
    <p><em>batman</em> is CECILL-B licensed; it is actively developed and maintained by researchers at CERFACS.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-openturns">
    <p>Baudin, M., A. Dutfoy, B. Iooss, and A.-L. Popelin. 2015. “Open TURNS: An industrial software for uncertainty quantification in simulation.” <em>ArXiv E-Prints</em>, January.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-scikit-learn">
    <p>Pedregosa, F., G. Varoquaux, A. Gramfort, V. Michel, B. Thirion, O. Grisel, M. Blondel, et al. 2011. “Scikit-Learn: Machine Learning in Python.” <em>Journal of Machine Learning Research</em> 12:2825–30.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-roy2017b">
    <p>Roy, Pamphile T., G. Daviller, J.-C. Jouhaud, and B. Cuenot. 2017. “Uncertainty Quantification-Driven Robust Design Assessment of a Swirler’s Geometry.” Paris-Saclay: SAFRAN TECH. <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/320518082_Uncertainty_Quantification-Driven_Robust_Design_Assessment_of_a_Swirler%27s_Geometry">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/320518082_Uncertainty_Quantification-Driven_Robust_Design_Assessment_of_a_Swirler%27s_Geometry</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-roy2017c">
    <p>Roy, Pamphile Tupui, Nabil El Moçayd, Sophie Ricci, Jean-Christophe Jouhaud, Nicole Goutal, Matthias De Lozzo, and Mélanie C. Rochoux. 2017. “Comparison of Polynomial Chaos and Gaussian Process Surrogates for Uncertainty Quantification and Correlation Estimation of Spatially Distributed Open-Channel Steady Flows.” <em>Stochastic Environmental Research and Risk Assessment</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00477-017-1470-4" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00477-017-1470-4</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-roy2017a">
    <p>Roy, Pamphile Tupui, Luis Miguel Segui, Jean-Christophe Jouhaud, and Laurent Gicquel. 2017. “Resampling Strategies to Improve Surrogate Model-Based Uncertainty Quantification - Application to Les of Ls89.” <em>In Review in: International Journal for Numerical Methods in Fluids</em>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
