<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>biotmle: Targeted Learning for Biomarker Discovery</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Nima S. Hejazi</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-7127-2789</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Weixin Cai</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-2680-3066</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Alan E. Hubbard</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3769-0127</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>targeted learning</tag>
      <tag>variable importance</tag>
      <tag>causal inference</tag>
      <tag>bioinformatics</tag>
      <tag>genomics</tag>
      <tag>R</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>26 July 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00295</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/nhejazi/biotmle</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.834849</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/raw/master/joss.00295/10.21105.joss.00295.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>The <code>biotmle</code> package provides an implementation of a biomarker discovery methodology based on targeted minimum loss-Based estimation (TMLE) <span class="citation">(van der Laan and Rose 2011)</span> and a generalization of the moderated t-statistic of <span class="citation">(Smyth 2004)</span>, designed for use with biological sequencing data (e.g., microarrays, RNA-seq). The statistical approach made available in this package relies on the use of TMLE to rigorously evaluate the association between a set of potential biomarkers and another variable of interest while adjusting for potential confounding from another set of user-specified covariates. The implementation is in the form of a package for the R language for statistical computing <span class="citation">(R Core Team 2017)</span>.</p>
    <p>There are two principal ways in which the biomarker discovery techniques in the <code>biotmle</code> R package can be used: to evaluate the association between (1) a phenotypic measure (say, environmental exposure) and a biomarker of interest, and (2) an outcome of interest (e.g., survival status at a given time) and a biomarker measurement, both while controlling for background covariates (e.g., BMI, age). By using an estimation procedure based on TMLE, the package produces results based on the Average Treatment Effect (ATE), a statistical parameter with a well-studied causal interpretation (see <span class="citation">van der Laan and Rose (2011)</span> for extended discussions), making the <code>biotmle</code> R package well-suited for applications in bioinformatics, epidemiology, and genomics.</p>
    <p>After adjusting our data set to be consistent with the expect input format -- please consult the vignette accompanying the R package for details -- we would call the principal function of this R package: <code>biomarkertmle</code>.</p>
    <p>We would perform a moderated test on the output of the <code>biomarkertmle</code> function using the function <code>modtest_ic</code>.</p>
    <p>While the principal table of results produced by this R package matches those produced by the well-known <code>limma</code> R package <span class="citation">(Smyth 2005)</span>, there are also several plot methods made available for the <code>bioTMLE</code> S4 class -- subclassed from the popular <code>SummarizedExperiment</code> class -- introduced by this package <span class="citation">(Huber et al. 2015)</span>. For illustrative purposes, we demonstrate the ouput of two such functions on anonymized experimental data below:</p>
    <div class="figure">
    <img src="figs/heatmap_biotmle.png" alt="Heatmap visualizing the Average Treatment Effect contribution of a change in exposure to each biomarker of interest" />
    <p class="caption">Heatmap visualizing the Average Treatment Effect contribution of a change in exposure to each biomarker of interest</p>
    </div>
    <div class="figure">
    <img src="figs/volcanoplot_biotmle.png" alt="Volcano plot visualizing the log fold change in the Average Treatment Effect against the raw p-value from the moderated t-test performed on each biomarker" />
    <p class="caption">Volcano plot visualizing the log fold change in the Average Treatment Effect against the raw p-value from the moderated t-test performed on each biomarker</p>
    </div>
    
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-huber2015orchestrating">
    <p>Huber, Wolfgang, Vincent J Carey, Robert Gentleman, Simon Anders, Marc Carlson, Benilton S Carvalho, Hector Corrada Bravo, et al. 2015. “Orchestrating High-Throughput Genomic Analysis with Bioconductor.” <em>Nature Methods</em> 12 (2). Nature Research: 115–21.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R">
    <p>R Core Team. 2017. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-smyth2004linear">
    <p>Smyth, Gordon K. 2004. “Linear Models and Empirical Bayes Methods for Assessing Differential Expression in Microarray Experiments.” <em>Statistical Applications in Genetics and Molecular Biology</em> 3 (1): 1–25.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-smyth2005limma">
    <p>———. 2005. “Limma: Linear Models for Microarray Data.” In <em>Bioinformatics and Computational Biology Solutions Using R and Bioconductor</em>, 397–420. Springer.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-vdl2011targeted">
    <p>van der Laan, Mark J, and Sherri Rose. 2011. <em>Targeted Learning: Causal Inference for Observational and Experimental Data</em>. Springer Science &amp; Business Media.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
