<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>18dee78216c6cdec9d7d7abb1ff26d61</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20210119104100</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>01</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>6</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>57</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>ELDAM: A Python software for Life Cycle Inventory data management</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Gustave</given_name>
            <surname>Coste</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5867-0507</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Yannick</given_name>
            <surname>Biard</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3974-3536</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Philippe</given_name>
            <surname>Roux</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9409-3193</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Arnaud</given_name>
            <surname>Hélias</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8652-5611</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>01</month>
          <day>19</day>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>2765</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.02765</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.15454/6EKXJQ”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/2765</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.02765</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02765</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02765.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <unstructured_citation>The Qt Company, Qt: Cross-platform software development for embedded and desktop, 2020, The Qt Company, Company website, https://www.qt.io/</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <unstructured_citation>PRé Sustainability B.V., SimaPro: The world’s leading LCA software, 2020, PRé Sustainability B.V., Company website, https://simapro.com/</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <doi>10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.124099</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <unstructured_citation>Up to what extent decentralised wastewater systems are more sustainable than centralised ones? Insights from a life-cycle assessment perspective, Water Research, 2020, Risch, Eva and Boutin, Catherine and Roux, Philippe, submitted</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <unstructured_citation>Bordeaux, France, Developing a quality management system for LCA datasets : the case of the LCA - CIRAD platform for tropical products, Since 2009, CIRAD (French Agricultural Research Centre for International Development) has been developing an ambitious LCA platform for analysing the life cycle of tropical agricultural products, involving a team of around 15 LCA practitioners, calculation tools and pooled databases. Implementing LCA in Mediterranean and tropical contexts raises specific challenges. In particular, data scarcity on foreground agricultural systems and the lack of LCI data sets for background processes in those contexts require significant resources to collect large amounts of LCI data on-site. Where primary data are not available, proxies must be found and adapted. Hence large data sets need to be compiled, changes tracked and experiences shared. Creating high-quality shareable data sets based on high-quality data was the main ambition for the new LCA platform right from the start. To this end, data sets must be created with the greatest care and transparency, especially when they are implemented in a pooled database, where providers of data sets and potential users may be distinct. The best way to ensure that data sets can be properly reused is to develop an integrated quality management system (QMS) at practitioner level, based on common procedures for data collection, data and metadata implementation in LCA software and nomenclature for data set review processes. The LCA-CIRAD team started to develop its QMS in 2012. The QMS is managed by a database engineer in charge of standardising and pooling the resources of the platform. The QMS is based on four activities:1) LCA data quality management: corpus of procedures on data set quality (compulsory acceptance) and training for practitioners.2) Data &amp; tool management: mirroring of calculation tools, remote access to the platform, versioning control.3) Intellectual Property management: licence development, specific training in database property rights, intellectual property policy and licensing.4) Practitioner skill management: technical support, in-service training in advanced features of tools. Since it has been deployed, the LCA-CIRAD QMS has followed an on-going improvement cycle, with regular feedback from practitioners, leading to regular updates of procedures. The implementation of QMS guidelines by permanent LCA scientists, interns and PhD students at CIRAD has markedly improved the quality of LCI metadata, data set transparency and reuse of LCA projects. (Texte intégral), eng, 2016-01-21, ISM, Biard, Yannick and Basset-Mens, Claudine and Bessou, Cécile and Tran, Thierry and Benoist, Anthony, sep, 2015, Section: CIRAD-PERSYST-UPR HortSys (FRA); CIRAD-PERSYST-UPR HortSys (FRA); CIRAD-PERSYST-UPR Systèmes de pérennes (FRA); CIRAD-PERSYST-UMR Qualisud (THA); CIRAD-PERSYST-UPR BioWooEB (FRA), 121–122, Life Cycle Management Conference 2015: list of abstracts, 9</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <unstructured_citation>Bangkok, Thaïlande, ELDAM , a new quality management system for LCI datasets exchange and review, https://agritrop.cirad.fr/589978/, When exchanging LCI data between LCA dedicated software, LCA practitioners often face technical restrictions of the software as well as potential lack of metadata on the datasets quality, limiting their reuse, update and improvement. To address these issues and facilitate LCI dataset exchanges within a community of scientists working on separate LCA software and LCI database, a set of data quality guidelines have been set up along with a tailor-made import-export and review tool for improving these rules applicability in an operational context., eng, 2018-12-14, Life Cycle Assessment, Coste, Gustave and Biard, Yannick and Roux, Philippe and Helias, Arnaud, , oct, 2018, Section: Montpellier SupAgro (FRA); CIRAD-PERSYST-UPR HortSys (FRA); IRSTEA (FRA); INRA (FRA), Book of abstracts of the 11th International Conference on Life Cycle Assessment of Food 2018 (LCA Food) “Global food challenges towards sustainable consumption and production”, 58–58, 10</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
