<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>coalitions: Coalition probabilities in multi-party democracies</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Andreas Bender</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-5628-8611</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Alexander Bauer</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-3495-5131</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>coalitions</tag>
      <tag>rstats</tag>
      <tag>coalition probabilities</tag>
      <tag>political science</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>03 March 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00606</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/adibender/coalitions</software_repository>
    <software_archive></software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00606/10.21105.joss.00606.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>In multi-party democracies, election coverage usually focuses on raw results from polls on questions like</p>
    <blockquote>
    <p>Who would you vote for if the election was tomorrow?</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>Whether a coalition (union of multiple parties) will obtain enough votes to form a governing coalition is discussed by adding up votes obtained by the parties in question, while ignoring sample uncertainty and redistribution of votes for parties beneath a specific threshold (e.g., 5% in Germany).</p>
    <p>The <a href="https://www.r-project.org/"><strong>R</strong></a> <span class="citation" data-cites="R">(R Core Team 2016)</span> package <a href="https://adibender.github.io/coalitions/"><code>coalitions</code></a> <span class="citation" data-cites="coalitions_zenodo">(Bender and Bauer 2018)</span> implements methods that overcome those shortcomings and quantifies sample uncertainty in terms of probabilities for events of interest. Specifically, it contains functions to</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Obtain survey results from different polling agencies,</li>
    <li>Aggregate (pool) multiple surveys (from different pollsters) within a pre-specified time-window, taking into account the correlation between different polling agencies</li>
    <li>Perform Monte Carlo simulations of election outcomes based on the (pooled) survey results</li>
    <li>Redistribute votes based on the method specific to the election of interest (e.g., Saint-Lague-Scheppers for German <em>Bundestag</em> election)</li>
    <li>Calculate Bayesian posterior probabilities for specific events, e.g., to obtain enough votes (&gt; 50%) to form a governing coalition</li>
    </ul>
    <p>To get started</p>
    <ul>
    <li>the <a href="https://adibender.github.io/coalitions/articles/workflow.html">workflow vignette</a> describes the usual steps during the analysis</li>
    <li>the <a href="https://adibender.github.io/coalitions/articles/pooling.html">pooling vignette</a> gives details on the aggregation of multiple surveys.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>An example for the (backend) application of the package can be found at</p>
    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://koala.stat.uni-muenchen.de" class="uri">http://koala.stat.uni-muenchen.de</a>,</li>
    </ul>
    <p>where it is applied to German (federal and state wide) elections/surveys.</p>
    <p>Currently, the functionality focuses on German federal and state-wide elections. However, it can be easily extended to other multi-party democracies, given the user can obtain the necessary data and transform it to a suitable format. For example, the methods have been successfully applied to calculate coalition probabilities for the 2017 elections in Austria. <br> Contributions are welcome at: <a href="https://github.com/adibender/coalitions" class="uri">https://github.com/adibender/coalitions</a></p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-coalitions_zenodo">
    <p>Bender, Andreas, and Alexander Bauer. 2018. “Adibender/Coalitions: V.0.6.0.” <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1188812" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1188812</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R">
    <p>R Core Team. 2016. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
