<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>7dbc11d284586879aaf31cd4ab9d0415</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20210928132036</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>6</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>65</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>SiSyPHE: A Python package for the Simulation of Systems of interacting mean-field Particles with High Efficiency</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Antoine</given_name>
            <surname>Diez</surname>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>09</month>
          <day>28</day>
          <year>2021</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>3653</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.03653</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5532924”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/3653</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.03653</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03653</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.03653.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <doi>10.1137/15M1019726</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <doi>10.1007/978-3-662-12616-5</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <doi>10.1007/978-3-319-16375-8</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <doi>10.1103/PhysRevLett.75.1226</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <doi>10.1142/S0218202508003005</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <unstructured_citation>Del Moral, P., Del Moral - 2016 - Mean field simulation for Monte Carlo integration.pdf:/Users/AntoineDiez/Zotero/storage/XRJNBV7J/Del Moral - 2016 - Mean field simulation for Monte Carlo integration.pdf:application/pdf, 9781466504059, 126, CRC Press, Taylor &amp; Francis Group, Monographs on Statistics and Applied Probability, Mean field simulation for Monte Carlo integration, 2013</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <doi>10.1142/S0218202516500330</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.1007/978-3-030-15096-9_2</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <unstructured_citation>Over the last decades, various “non-linear” MCMC methods have arised. While appealing for their convergence speed and efficiency, their practical implementation and theoretical study remain challenging. In this paper, we introduce a large class of non-linear samplers that can be studied and simulated as the mean-field limit of a system of interacting particles. The practical implementation we propose leverages the computational power of modern hardware (GPU)., Clarté, G. and Diez, A. and Feydy, J., arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/AntoineDiez/Zotero/storage/ZUT2L3QG/Clarté et al. - 2021 - Collective Proposal Distributions for Nonlinear MC.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/AntoineDiez/Zotero/storage/9IB524SG/1909.html:text/html, arXiv preprint: arXiv:1909.08988, Mathematics - Probability, Mathematics - Statistics Theory, Statistics - Methodology, Collective Proposal Distributions for Nonlinear MCMC samplers, Collective Proposal Distributions for Nonlinear MCMC samplers: Mean-Field Theory and Fast Implementation, http://arxiv.org/abs/1909.08988, 2021, http://arxiv.org/abs/1909.08988</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <unstructured_citation>In this chapter we give an overview of the consensus-based global optimization algorithm and its recent variants. We recall the formulation and analytical results of the original model, then we discuss variants using component-wise independent or common noise. In combination with mini-batch approaches those variants were tailored for machine learning applications. Moreover, it turns out that the analytical estimates are dimension independent, which is useful for high-dimensional problems. We discuss the relationship of consensus-based optimization with particle swarm optimization, a method widely used in the engineering community. Then we survey a variant of consensus-based optimization that is proposed for global optimization problems constrained to hyper-surfaces. We conclude the chapter with remarks on applications, preprints and open problems., Totzeck, C., arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/AntoineDiez/Zotero/storage/W88N2ZL8/Totzeck - 2021 - Trends in Consensus-based optimization.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/AntoineDiez/Zotero/storage/AECHAQQ3/2104.html:text/html, arXiv preprint: arXiv:2104.01383, Mathematics - Optimization and Control, Trends in Consensus-based optimization, http://arxiv.org/abs/2104.01383, 2021, http://arxiv.org/abs/2104.01383</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <doi>10.1142/S0218202517400061</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <doi>10.1142/s0218202521500342</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref13">
            <unstructured_citation>In this paper, we demonstrate the existence of topological states in a new collective dynamics model. This individual-based model (IBM) describes self-propelled rigid bodies moving with constant speed and adjusting their rigid-body attitude to that of their neighbors. In previous works, a macroscopic model has been derived from this IBM in a suitable scaling limit. In the present work, we exhibit explicit solutions of the macroscopic model characterized by a non-trivial topology. We show that these solutions are well approximated by the IBM during a certain time but then the IBM transitions towards topologically trivial states. Using a set of appropriately defined topological indicators, we reveal that the breakage of the non-trivial topology requires the system to go through a phase of maximal disorder. We also show that similar but topologically trivial initial conditions result in markedly different dynamics, suggesting that topology plays a key role in the dynamics of this system., Degond, P. and Diez, A. and Na, M., arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/AntoineDiez/Zotero/storage/WZ7T6WWE/Degond et al. - 2021 - Bulk topological states in a new collective dynami.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/AntoineDiez/Zotero/storage/Q8YE4DVN/2101.html:text/html, arXiv preprint: arXiv:2101.10864, Condensed Matter - Statistical Mechanics, Bulk topological states in a new collective dynamics model, http://arxiv.org/abs/2101.10864, 2021, http://arxiv.org/abs/2101.10864</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref14">
            <unstructured_citation>Charlier, B. and Feydy, J. and Glaunès, J. A. and Collin, F.-D. and Durif, G., J. Mach. Learn. Res., 74, 1–6, Kernel Operations on the GPU, with Autodiff, without Memory Overflows, 22, 2021</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref15">
            <doi>10.1214/aoap/1028903535</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref16">
            <doi>10.1109/ICNN.1995.488968</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref17">
            <doi>10.1103/PhysRevE.77.046113</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref18">
            <doi>10.1007/978-1-4757-3437-9</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref19">
            <doi>10.1198/106186004X12803</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref20">
            <unstructured_citation>Motsch, S., GitHub repository, Vicsek_microFlat, https://github.com/smotsch/Vicsek_microFlat, 2016, https://github.com/smotsch/Vicsek_microFlat</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref21">
            <unstructured_citation>Paszke, A. and Gross, S. and Massa, F. and Lerer, A. and Bradbury, J. and Chanan, G. and Killeen, T. and Lin, Z. and Gimelshein, N. and Antiga, L. and Desmaison, A. and Kopf, A. and Yang, E. and DeVito, Z. and Raison, M. and Tejani, A. and Chilamkurthy, S. and Steiner, B. and Fang, L. and Bai, J. and Chintala, S., Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, Wallach, H. and Larochelle, H. and Beygelzimer, A. and Alché-Buc, F. and Fox, E. and Garnett, R., Curran Associates, Inc., PyTorch: An Imperative Style, High-Performance Deep Learning Library, https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2019/file/bdbca288fee7f92f2bfa9f7012727740-Paper.pdf, 32, 2019, https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2019/file/bdbca288fee7f92f2bfa9f7012727740-Paper.pdf</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
