<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>skedm: Empirical Dynamic Modeling</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Nicholas Cortale</name>
        <orcid>0000-0003-2262-663X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
      <author>
        <name>Dylan McNamara</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-8752-1586</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Empirical Dynamic Modeling</tag>
      <tag>Nonlinear Forecasting</tag>
      <tag>Dynamic Systems</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>24 January 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00207</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/NickC1/skedm</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4887398.v1</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/raw/master/joss.00207/10.21105.joss.00207.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>This python package implements nonlinear time series analysis techniques, also referred to as empirical dynamic modeling, based on many of the workflows and routines within TISEAN<span class="citation">(Hegger and Schreiber 1999)</span> and <span class="citation">(Ye et al. 2017)</span>. The package provides a modern api, is written in pure python, and provides additional analysis routines not provided by TISEAN. skedm is capable of reconstructing state spaces from one, two, and even three-dimensional series. Additionally, it provides various methods for analyzing the evolution of nearby neighbors in the reconstructed state spaces. skedm also includes numerous one, two, and three-dimensional synthetic datasets for researchers to explore.</p>
    <p>The code makes use of scikit-learn's <span class="citation">(Pedregosa et al. 2011)</span> efficient near neighbor implementation, and allows users familiar with the scikit-learn's API <span class="citation">(Buitinck et al. 2013)</span> to easily use skedm.</p>
    <p>-<img src="forecasting_example.png" alt="Forecasting Example" /></p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-scikit-learn-api">
    <p>Buitinck, Lars, Gilles Louppe, Mathieu Blondel, Fabian Pedregosa, Andreas Mueller, Olivier Grisel, Vlad Niculae, et al. 2013. “API Design for Machine Learning Software: Experiences from the Scikit-Learn Project.” <em>arXiv Preprint arXiv:1309.0238</em>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-tisean">
    <p>Hegger, Holger Kantz, Rainer, and Thomas Schreiber. 1999. “Practical Implementation of Nonlinear Time Series Methods: The Tisean Package.” <em>Chaos: An Interdisciplinary Journal of Nonlinear Science</em> 9.2: 413–35.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-scikit-learn">
    <p>Pedregosa, Fabian, Gaél Varoquaux, Alexandre Gramfort, Vincent Michel, Bertrand Thirion, Olivier Grisel, Mathieu Blondel, et al. 2011. “Scikit-Learn: Machine Learning in Python.” <em>The Journal of Machine Learning Research</em> 12. JMLR. org: 2825–30.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-hao_ye_2017_376663">
    <p>Ye, Hao, Jun Cai, Adam Clark, janecowles, Oliver Keyes, and Ethan White. 2017. “Ha0ye/rEDM: Added Readme.” doi:<a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.376663">10.5281/zenodo.376663</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
