<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Varistran: Anscombe's variance stabilizing transformation for RNA-seq gene expression data</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Paul Francis Harrison</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-3980-268X</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>RNA-seq</tag>
      <tag>gene expression</tag>
      <tag>variance stabilizing transformation</tag>
      <tag>R package</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>8 March 2017</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00257</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/MonashBioinformaticsPlatform/varistran</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.846925</software_archive>
    <paper_url>https://github.com/openjournals/joss-papers/raw/master/joss.00257/10.21105.joss.00257.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>RNA-seq measures RNA expression levels in a biological sample using high-throughput cDNA sequencing, producing counts of the number of reads aligning to each gene. Noise in RNA-seq read count data is commonly modelled as following a negative binomial distribution, where the variance is a quadratic function of the expression level. However many statistical, machine learning, and visualization methods work best when the noise in a data set has equal variance. Varistran is an R package that uses Anscombe's <span class="citation">(1948)</span> variance stabilizing transformation for the negative binomial distribution to transform RNA-seq count data, so that the noise has equal variance across all measured gene expression levels. The transformed data may be treated as log<sub>2</sub> transformed gene expression levels, but with variability reduced at low read counts. Varistran also includes a function to open a Shiny report with simple diagnostic visualizations, including a plot to assess how effective the variance stabilization was, a biplot of samples and genes, and a heatmap. This allows defective samples, sample mislabling, and batch effects to be easily identified.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-Anscombe1948">
    <p>Anscombe, Francis J. 1948. “The Transformation of Poisson, Binomial and Negative-Binomial Data.” <em>Biometrika</em> 35 (3/4): 246–54.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
