<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0" xmlns:ai="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd" xmlns:rel="http://www.crossref.org/relations.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="4.4.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/4.4.0 http://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref4.4.0.xsd">
  <head>
    <doi_batch_id>3bb471da771e44401554436a2f83ea3a</doi_batch_id>
    <timestamp>20201217213402</timestamp>
    <depositor>
      <depositor_name>JOSS Admin</depositor_name>
      <email_address>admin@theoj.org</email_address>
    </depositor>
    <registrant>The Open Journal</registrant>
  </head>
  <body>
    <journal>
      <journal_metadata>
        <full_title>Journal of Open Source Software</full_title>
        <abbrev_title>JOSS</abbrev_title>
        <issn media_type="electronic">2475-9066</issn>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org</resource>
        </doi_data>
      </journal_metadata>
      <journal_issue>
        <publication_date media_type="online">
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2020</year>
        </publication_date>
        <journal_volume>
          <volume>5</volume>
        </journal_volume>
        <issue>56</issue>
      </journal_issue>
      <journal_article publication_type="full_text">
        <titles>
          <title>ADI.jl: A Julia Package for High-Contrast Imaging</title>
        </titles>
        <contributors>
          <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Miles</given_name>
            <surname>Lucas</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6341-310X</ORCID>
          </person_name>
          <person_name sequence="additional" contributor_role="author">
            <given_name>Michael</given_name>
            <surname>Bottom</surname>
            <ORCID>http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1341-5531</ORCID>
          </person_name>
        </contributors>
        <publication_date>
          <month>12</month>
          <day>17</day>
          <year>2020</year>
        </publication_date>
        <pages>
          <first_page>2843</first_page>
        </pages>
        <publisher_item>
          <identifier id_type="doi">10.21105/joss.02843</identifier>
        </publisher_item>
        <ai:program name="AccessIndicators">
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="vor">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="am">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
          <ai:license_ref applies_to="tdm">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ai:license_ref>
        </ai:program>
        <rel:program>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>Software archive</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="references" identifier-type="doi">“https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4323554”</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
          <rel:related_item>
            <rel:description>GitHub review issue</rel:description>
            <rel:inter_work_relation relationship-type="hasReview" identifier-type="uri">https://github.com/openjournals/joss-reviews/issues/2843</rel:inter_work_relation>
          </rel:related_item>
        </rel:program>
        <doi_data>
          <doi>10.21105/joss.02843</doi>
          <resource>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02843</resource>
          <collection property="text-mining">
            <item>
              <resource mime_type="application/pdf">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02843.pdf</resource>
            </item>
          </collection>
        </doi_data>
        <citation_list>
          <citation key="ref1">
            <unstructured_citation>Reference-less algorithm for circumstellar disks imaging, http://arxiv.org/abs/1812.01333, Circumstellar disks play a key role in the understanding of stellar systems. Direct imaging of such extended structures is a challenging task. Current post-processing techniques, first tailored for exoplanets imaging, tend to produce deformed images of the circumstellar disks, hindering our capability to study their shape and photometry in details. We address here the reasons of this shortcoming and propose an algorithm that produces more faithful images of disks taken with ground-based telescopes. We also show that our algorithm is a good candidate for exoplanets imaging. We then explain how our approach can be extended in the form of a regularized inverse problem., 2020-06-09, arXiv:1812.01333 [astro-ph], Pairet, Benoît and Cantalloube, Faustine and Jacques, Laurent, feb, 2019, arXiv: 1812.01333, Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics, arXiv Fulltext PDF:/Users/miles/Zotero/storage/VQXBNH9F/Pairet et al. - 2019 - Reference-less algorithm for circumstellar disks i.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/miles/Zotero/storage/T6HJQUN6/1812.html:text/html, 2</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref2">
            <doi>10.1088/1538-3873/128/968/102001</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref3">
            <doi>10.1126/science.1102929</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref4">
            <doi>10.1086/500401</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref5">
            <unstructured_citation>VIP: Vortex Image Processing pipeline for high-contrast direct imaging of exoplanets, VIP, http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2016ascl.soft03003G, VIP (Vortex Image Processing pipeline) provides pre- and post-processing algorithms for high-contrast direct imaging of exoplanets. Written in Python, VIP provides a very flexible framework for data exploration and image processing and supports high-contrast imaging observational techniques, including angular, reference-star and multi-spectral differential imaging. Several post-processing algorithms for PSF subtraction based on principal component analysis are available as well as the LLSG (Local Low-rank plus Sparse plus Gaussian-noise decomposition) algorithm for angular differential imaging. VIP also implements the negative fake companion technique coupled with MCMC sampling for rigorous estimation of the flux and position of potential companions., 2020-07-29, Astrophysics Source Code Library, Gomez Gonzalez, Carlos Alberto and Wertz, Olivier and Christiaens, Valentin and Absil, Olivier and Mawet, Dimitri, mar, 2016, Software, ascl:1603.003, 3</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref6">
            <doi>10.1088/2041-8205/755/2/L28</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref7">
            <unstructured_citation>MAYONNAISE: a morphological components analysis pipeline for circumstellar disks and exoplanets imaging in the near infrared, MAYONNAISE, http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.05170, Imaging circumstellar disks in the near-infrared provides unprecedented information about the formation and evolution of planetary systems. However, current post-processing techniques for high-contrast imaging have a limited sensitivity to extended signals and their morphology is often plagued with strong morphological distortions. Moreover, it is challenging to disentangle planetary signals from the disk when the two components are closed or intertwined. We propose a pipeline that is capable of detecting a wide variety of disks and preserving their shapes and flux distributions. By construction, our approach separates planets from disks. After analyzing the distortions induced by the current angular differential imaging (ADI) post-processing techniques, we establish a direct model of the different components constituting a temporal sequence of high-contrast images. In an inverse problem framework, we jointly estimate the starlight residuals and the potential extended sources and point sources hidden in the images, using low-complexity priors for each signal. To verify and estimate the performance of our approach, we tested it on VLT/SPHERE-IRDIS data, in which we injected synthetic disks and planets. We also applied our approach on observations containing real disks. Our technique makes it possible to detect disks from ADI datasets of a contrast above \3}times10^{-6} with respect to the host star. As no specific shape of the disks is assumed, we are capable of extracting a wide diversity of disks, including face-on disks. The intensity distribution of the detected disk is accurately preserved and point sources are distinguished, even close to the disk., 2020-08-17, arXiv:2008.05170 [astro-ph], Pairet, Benoît and Cantalloube, Faustine and Jacques, Laurent, aug, 2020, arXiv: 2008.05170, Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics, Pairet et al_2020_MAYONNAISE.pdf:/Users/miles/Zotero/storage/W2FFGR6E/Pairet et al_2020_MAYONNAISE.pdf:application/pdf;arXiv.org Snapshot:/Users/miles/Zotero/storage/7ZB8F8ND/2008.html:text/html;Pairet et al_2020_MAYONNAISE_annotated.pdf:/Users/miles/Zotero/storage/YDFCTCEK/Pairet et al_2020_MAYONNAISE_annotated.pdf:application/pdf, 8</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref8">
            <doi>10.3847/1538-4357/aaa1f2</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref9">
            <doi>10.1137/141000671</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref10">
            <unstructured_citation>Bezanson, Jeff and Bolewski, Jake and Chen, Jiahao, Fast Flexible Function Dispatch in Julia, arXiv e-prints, Computer Science - Programming Languages, Computer Science - Computation and Language, Computer Science - Mathematical Software, 68N15, D.3.3, G.4, 2018, aug, arXiv:1808.03370, arXiv:1808.03370, arXiv, 1808.03370, cs.PL, https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018arXiv180803370B, Provided by the SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System, 8</unstructured_citation>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref11">
            <doi>10.1051/0004-6361/201834136</doi>
          </citation>
          <citation key="ref12">
            <doi>10.1109/TPDS.2018.2872064</doi>
          </citation>
        </citation_list>
      </journal_article>
    </journal>
  </body>
</doi_batch>
