<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Discrete Laplace mixture model with applications in forensic genetics</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Mikkel Meyer Andersen</name>
        <orcid>0000-0002-0234-0266</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>Y-chromosome</tag>
      <tag>forensic genetics</tag>
      <tag>population genetics</tag>
      <tag>weight of evidence</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>23 April 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00748</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/mikldk/disclapmix</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1257887</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00748/10.21105.joss.00748.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>This R package implements a model based on a mixture of multivariate discrete Laplace distributions that has applications in forensic genetics. The implementation consists of parameter estimation and various functionalities. The method and this package were (and still are) used by multiple groups for e.g. frequency estimation <span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenDisclap2013 YHRD15 Willuweit2018 Roewer2018 Familias CeredaDIP CeredaRare">(Andersen, Eriksen, and Morling 2013; S Willuweit and Roewer 2015; S. Willuweit et al. 2018; Roewer and Willuweit 2018; Egeland, Kling, and Mostad 2016; Cereda et al. 2014; Cereda 2017)</span>, cluster analysis <span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenDisclapCluster2014">(Andersen, Eriksen, and Morling 2014)</span>, and mixture interpretation [<span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenDisclapMixture2015">Andersen et al. (2015)</span>; Taylor2018]. Below, background for the method and package is described.</p>
    <p>Estimating haplotype frequencies is important in e.g. forensic genetics, where the frequencies are used to calculate the likelihood ratio for the evidential weight of a DNA profile found at a crime scene <span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenDisclap2013 DJBwoe2">(Andersen, Eriksen, and Morling 2013; Steele and Balding 2015)</span>. Estimation is naturally based on a population model, motivating the investigation of the Fisher-Wright model <span class="citation" data-cites="Fisher1930 Wright1931 Ewens1972 OhtaKimura1973">(Fisher 1930; Wright 1931; Ewens 1972; Ohta and Kimura 1973)</span> of evolution for haploid lineage DNA markers.</p>
    <p>An exponential family (a class of probability distributions that is well understood in probability theory) called the ‘discrete Laplace distribution’ was described in <span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenDisclap2013">(Andersen, Eriksen, and Morling 2013)</span> that also illustrates how well the discrete Laplace distribution approximates a more complicated distribution that arises by investigating the well-known population genetic Fisher-Wright model of evolution by a single-step mutation process <span class="citation" data-cites="Caliebe2010">(Caliebe et al. 2010)</span>.</p>
    <p>In <span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenDisclap2013">(Andersen, Eriksen, and Morling 2013)</span>, it was also shown that the discrete Laplace distribution can be used to estimate haplotype frequencies for haploid lineage DNA markers (such as Y-chromosomal short tandem repeats), which in turn can be used to assess the evidential weight of a DNA profile found at a crime scene. This was done by making inference in a mixture of multivariate discrete Laplace distributions using the EM algorithm to estimate the probabilities of membership of a set of unobserved subpopulations and also estimate the central haplotypes of the subpopulations. The implementation was made efficient by avoiding to construct the model matrix explicitely which made it possible to perform the calculations on a normal computer.</p>
    <p>This package implements the method described in <span class="citation" data-cites="AndersenDisclap2013">(Andersen, Eriksen, and Morling 2013)</span> as a freely available open source software R package using both R <span class="citation" data-cites="R">(R Core Team 2018)</span> and C++ <span class="citation" data-cites="Rcpp">(Eddelbuettel and Balamuta 2017)</span>. The documentation of <code>disclapmix</code> consists of manual pages for the various available functions, articles describing how to perform contiguous analyses (<em>vignettes</em>), and unit tests.</p>
    <p>I would like to thank Poul Svante Eriksen (Aalborg University, Denmark) for tips, hints, helpful discussions and help with implementation and debugging.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-AndersenDisclap2013">
    <p>Andersen, Mikkel Meyer, Poul Svante Eriksen, and Niels Morling. 2013. “The discrete Laplace exponential family and estimation of Y-STR haplotype frequencies.” <em>Journal of Theoretical Biology</em> 329:39–51. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2013.03.009" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2013.03.009</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-AndersenDisclapCluster2014">
    <p>———. 2014. “Cluster analysis of European Y-chromosomal STR haplotypes using the discrete Laplace method.” <em>Forensic Science International: Genetics</em> 11:182–94. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsigen.2014.03.016" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsigen.2014.03.016</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-AndersenDisclapMixture2015">
    <p>Andersen, Mikkel Meyer, Poul Svante Eriksen, Helle Smidt Mogensen, and Niels Morling. 2015. “Identifying the most likely contributors to a Y-STR mixture using the discrete Laplace method.” <em>Forensic Science International: Genetics</em> 15:76–83. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsigen.2014.09.011" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsigen.2014.09.011</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Caliebe2010">
    <p>Caliebe, Amke, Arne Jochens, Michael Krawczak, and Uwe Rösler. 2010. “A Markov Chain Description of the Stepwise Mutation Model: Local and Global Behaviour of the Allele Process.” <em>Journal of Theoretical Biology</em> 266 (2):336–42. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2010.06.033" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2010.06.033</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-CeredaRare">
    <p>Cereda, G. 2017. “Impact of Model Choice on LR Assessment in Case of Rare Haplotype Match (Frequentist Approach).” <em>Scandinavian Journal of Statistics</em> 44. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/sjos.12250" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/sjos.12250</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-CeredaDIP">
    <p>Cereda, G., A. Biedermann, D. Hall, and F. Taroni. 2014. “An investigation of the potential of DIP-STR markers for DNA mixture analyses.” <em>Forensic Science International: Genetics</em> 11. <a href="https://doi.org/j.fsigen.2014.04.001" class="uri">https://doi.org/j.fsigen.2014.04.001</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Rcpp">
    <p>Eddelbuettel, D, and JJ Balamuta. 2017. “Extending <em>R</em> with <em>C++</em>: A Brief Introduction to <em>Rcpp</em>.” <em>PeerJ Preprints</em> 5 (August):e3188v1. <a href="https://doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.3188v1" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.3188v1</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Familias">
    <p>Egeland, Thore, Daniel Kling, and Petter Mostad. 2016. <em>Relationship Inference with Familias and R</em>. Academic Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/C2014-0-01828-X" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/C2014-0-01828-X</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Ewens1972">
    <p>Ewens, W.J. 1972. “The sampling theory of selectively neutral alleles.” <em>Theoretical Population Biology</em> 3:87–112.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Fisher1930">
    <p>Fisher, R. A. 1930. <em>The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection</em>. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-OhtaKimura1973">
    <p>Ohta, T., and M. Kimura. 1973. “A Model of Mutation Appropriate to Estimate the Number of Electrophoretically Detectable Alleles in a Finite Population.” <em>Genet. Res.</em> 22:201–4.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-R">
    <p>R Core Team. 2018. <em>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</em>. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. <a href="https://www.R-project.org/" class="uri">https://www.R-project.org/</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Roewer2018">
    <p>Roewer, L., and S. Willuweit. 2018. “Y‑chromosomale STR-Analyse in der forensischen Praxis.” <em>Rechtsmedizin</em> 28 (2):149–64. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00194-018-0229-7" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00194-018-0229-7</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-DJBwoe2">
    <p>Steele, CD, and DJ Balding. 2015. <em>Weight of Evidence for Forensic DNA Profiles</em>. 2nd ed. Wiley. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470867693" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470867693</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-YHRD15">
    <p>Willuweit, S, and L Roewer. 2015. “The New Y Chromosome Haplotype Reference Database.” <em>Forensic Science International: Genetics</em> 15:43–48. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsigen.2014.11.024" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fsigen.2014.11.024</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Willuweit2018">
    <p>Willuweit, S., K. Anslinger, G. Bäßler, M. Eckert, R. Fimmers, C. Hohoff, M. Kraft, et al. 2018. “Gemeinsame Empfehlungen der Projektgruppe ”Biostatistische DNA-Berechnungen“ und der Spurenkommission zur biostatistischen Bewertung von Y‑chromosomalen DNA-Befunden.” <em>Rechtsmedizin</em> 28 (2):138–42. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00194-018-0244-8" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00194-018-0244-8</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-Wright1931">
    <p>Wright, S. 1931. “Evolution in Mendelian populations.” <em>Genetics</em> 16:97–159.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
