<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>G³M-f a global gradient-based groundwater modelling framwork</title>
    <authors>
      <author>
        <name>Robert Reinecke</name>
        <orcid>0000-0001-5699-8584</orcid>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>
            1
          </orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <tags>
      <tag>groundwater</tag>
      <tag>gradient-based</tag>
      <tag>global</tag>
      <tag>conjugate-gradient</tag>
    </tags>
    <date>02 January 2018</date>
    <paper_doi>10.21105/joss.00548</paper_doi>
    <software_repository>https://github.com/rreinecke/global-gradient-based-groundwater-model</software_repository>
    <software_archive>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1175540</software_archive>
    <paper_url>http://www.theoj.org/joss-papers/joss.00548/10.21105.joss.00548.pdf</paper_url>
  </articleinfo>
  <body>
    <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
    <p>In order to represent groundwater-surface water interactions as well as the impact of capillary rise on evapotranspiration in global-scale hydrological models, it is necessary to simulate the location and temporal variation of the groundwater table. This requires replacing simulation of groundwater dynamics using groundwater storage variations in individual grid cells (independent from the storage variation in neighbouring cells) with hydraulic head gradient-based groundwater modelling.</p>
    <p>The global gradient-based groundwater model framework G³M-f is an extesible model framework. Its main purpose is to be used as a main building block for the global groundwater mode G³M. G³M is a newly developed gradient-based groundwater model, which adapts MODFLOW <span class="citation" data-cites="harbaugh2005modflow">(Harbaugh 2005)</span> principles for the global scale. It is written in C++ and intended to be coupled to the global hydrology model WaterGAP (http://watergap.de) <span class="citation" data-cites="alcamo2003development doll2003global doll2012impact doell2014global muller2014sensitivity">(Alcamo et al. 2003; Döll, Kaspar, and Lehner 2003; Döll et al. 2012; Doell et al. 2014; Müller Schmied et al. 2014)</span>, but can also be used for regional groundwater models and coupling to other hydrology models. While it is intended to be used as a in memory coupled model it is also capable of running a standard standalone groundwater model. The code is available on globalgroundwatermodel.org <span class="citation" data-cites="g3m">(Reinecke 2018)</span>.</p>
    <h1 id="references" class="unnumbered">References</h1>
    <div id="refs" class="references">
    <div id="ref-alcamo2003development">
    <p>Alcamo, Joseph, Petra Döll, Thomas Henrichs, Frank Kaspar, Bernhard Lehner, Thomas Rösch, and Stefan Siebert. 2003. “Development and Testing of the Watergap 2 Global Model of Water Use and Availability.” <em>Hydrological Sciences Journal</em> 48 (3). Taylor &amp; Francis:317–37. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1623/hysj.48.3.317.45290" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1623/hysj.48.3.317.45290</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-doell2014global">
    <p>Doell, Petra, Hannes Mueller Schmied, Carina Schuh, Felix T Portmann, and Annette Eicker. 2014. “Global-Scale Assessment of Groundwater Depletion and Related Groundwater Abstractions: Combining Hydrological Modeling with Information from Well Observations and Grace Satellites.” <em>Water Resources Research</em> 50 (7). Wiley Online Library:5698–5720. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/2014WR015595" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1002/2014WR015595</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-doll2012impact">
    <p>Döll, Petra, Heike Hoffmann-Dobrev, Felix T Portmann, Stefan Siebert, Annette Eicker, Matthew Rodell, Gil Strassberg, and BR Scanlon. 2012. “Impact of Water Withdrawals from Groundwater and Surface Water on Continental Water Storage Variations.” <em>Journal of Geodynamics</em> 59. Elsevier:143–56. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jog.2011.05.001" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jog.2011.05.001</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-doll2003global">
    <p>Döll, Petra, Frank Kaspar, and Bernhard Lehner. 2003. “A Global Hydrological Model for Deriving Water Availability Indicators: Model Tuning and Validation.” <em>Journal of Hydrology</em> 270 (1). Elsevier:105–34. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0022-1694(02)00283-4" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0022-1694(02)00283-4</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-harbaugh2005modflow">
    <p>Harbaugh, Arlen W. 2005. <em>MODFLOW-2005, the Us Geological Survey Modular Ground-Water Model: The Ground-Water Flow Process</em>. US Department of the Interior, US Geological Survey Reston. <a href="https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tm6A16" class="uri">https://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/tm6A16</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-muller2014sensitivity">
    <p>Müller Schmied, Hannes, Stephanie Eisner, Daniela Franz, Martin Wattenbach, Felix Theodor Portmann, Martina Flörke, and Petra Döll. 2014. “Sensitivity of Simulated Global-Scale Freshwater Fluxes and Storages to Input Data, Hydrological Model Structure, Human Water Use and Calibration.” <em>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences</em> 18 (9). Copernicus GmbH:3511–38. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-18-3511-2014" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-18-3511-2014</a>.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="ref-g3m">
    <p>Reinecke, Robert. 2018. “G³M-F a Global Gradient-Based Groundwater Modelling Framwork.” <a href="globalgroundwatermodel.org" class="uri">globalgroundwatermodel.org</a>. <a href="https://doi.org/no doi yet" class="uri">https://doi.org/no doi yet</a>.</p>
    </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</article>
